<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/all.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-30T17:51:14-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed/all.xml</id><title type="html">regpaq | All</title><subtitle>B2B Marketer. Avid reader &amp; writer.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;regpaq&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">I’m Learning Virtue is Its Own Reward</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/virtue-is-its-own-reward" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I'm Learning Virtue is Its Own Reward" /><published>2019-11-29T06:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-11-29T06:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/virtue-is-its-own-reward</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/virtue-is-its-own-reward">&lt;p&gt;Before learning about &lt;a href=&quot;/philosophy&quot;&gt;philosophy&lt;/a&gt;, I used to believe the amount of impact one has on the world was the highest objective we should aim to achieve in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or in other words, build the biggest legacy. &lt;strong&gt;And if my life ended without a legacy, if there wasn’t a large subset of people who remembered me or knew who I was even just 50 years after I died, my life was… well meaningless.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a demoralizing point-of-view, but I couldn’t reason or justify a better measurement for meaning. I’d rather accept a harsh reality as true than keep my head in the sand and believe a false reality to feel better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I was conflicted when reading how strong &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt; and the Stoics believed accepting fate and doing good as the highest objective he strived to achieve in life. This is one of my favorite Aurelius quotes about this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No matter what anyone says or does, my task is to be good. Like gold or emerald or purple repeating to itself, “No matter what anyone says or does, my task is to be emerald, my color undiminished.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this quote because he says his task is to be good, like an emerald’s task is to be emerald in color. An emerald can’t be anything but emerald. And Aurelius strives to be good to his core so he couldn’t do anything but good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I didn’t understand how striving to achieve virtue could lead to a meaningful life. But then I understood Aurelius didn’t seek to achieve meaning. &lt;strong&gt;Rather, he sought to achieve goodness.&lt;/strong&gt; So what did Aurelius know about meaning to disregard it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;according-to-marcus-aurelius-life-and-legacy-are-trivial-and-meaningless&quot;&gt;According to Marcus Aurelius, Life and Legacy are Trivial and Meaningless&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s my understanding that Aurelius never believed in a “meaningful” life. In one meditation, he equated the entirety of life to a rock being thrown in the air and coming back down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A rock thrown in the air. It loses nothing by coming down, gained nothing by going up.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another, he wrote about exercising awareness in the moment, not to appreciate it, but to realize it’s not much to miss out on when he dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Stop whatever you’re doing for a moment and ask yourself: Am I afraid of death because I won’t be able to do this anymore?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 10.29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have the impression Aurelius believed life was something that had to be done and put up with as fate demanded. Why? Because death scared him and he wanted to believe he wouldn’t be missing out on anything when he died to better cope with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Human lives are brief and trivial. Yesterday a blob of semen; tomorrow embalming fluid, ash.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“To pass through this brief life as nature demands. To give it up without complaint.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 4.48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-aurelius-had-to-say-about-legacy-and-fame&quot;&gt;What Aurelius had to say about legacy and fame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacies are born out of fame and Aurelius had a disdain for it for two reasons. If you’re working towards achieving fame, it means you care too much about what other people think of you. And second, fame doesn’t last long so it’s pointless to pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…look at how soon we’re all forgotten. The abyss of endless time that swallows it all. The emptiness of all those applauding hands. The people who praise us - how capricious they are, how arbitrary. And the tiny region in which it all takes place. The whole earth a point in space…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 4.3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter if people remember you 50 years after death or 200, you will still be forgotten. Think about how many people you know of who were alive 200 years ago in 1819. All the celebrities, the of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“So many who were remembered already forgotten, and those who remembered them long gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-criticisms-of-marcus-aureliuss-point-of-view&quot;&gt;My Criticisms of Marcus Aurelius’s Point-of-View&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my interpretation of Aurelius’s beliefs, legacy, fame, and being remembered is meaningless. And life itself is void of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only criticism is you can take two people, and objectively determine which had more impact, and thus more meaning. For example, taken to the extreme, it’s easy to identify who had more impact and meant more to society: Steve Jobs vs the average joe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to point out that impact could be positive or negative. For example, Martin Luther King Jr vs Osama Bin Laden. Both had great impact on society, but in opposite directions. If, for sake of argument, we quantified their impact as equal would their meaning be equal? Does meaning take into account positive vs negative impact? I think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius and the Stoics believed being virtuous and doing good as the highest objective. &lt;strong&gt;Then, according to Stoicism, wouldn’t someone who does more good than another have both more impact and more meaning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stoics argued that the only thing in our control is our mind. And it’s rare for people to make an impact at the level of Jobs or MLK. If all it took to make a high impact was desire and tenacity, there would be a lot more people making that high of an impact. But there are lot of factors outside of our control, which makes the highest level of achievement impossible for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Therefore, while there may be objective measures to determine if a life is more impactful or meaningful than another, it’s fruitless to pursue it and make it your highest objective. Instead, the Stoics argue it’s best to make virtue and doing good the highest objective, which is entirely within our control. I’m beginning to understand why.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-how-virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;Understanding How Virtue is Its Own Reward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://dailystoic.com/4-stoic-virtues/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ryan Holiday puts it&lt;/a&gt;, “A Stoic believes they don’t control the world around them, only how they respond — and that they must always respond with courage, temperance, wisdom, and justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the four core virtues of Stoicism. Aurelius believed &lt;strong&gt;justice&lt;/strong&gt; was the most important, because acting with justice is doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“And a commitment to justice in your own acts. Which means: thought and action resulting in the common good. What you were born to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I completed &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt; for the first time two years ago. Since then, I’ve been adopting a Stoic mindset and I’ve seen myself undergo a dramatic transformation. Acting with justice and virtue has given me a new level of patience and resilience, improved my relationships, and fostered an affection for all people. It has redirected my ambition from building a legacy and longing for recognition to a mission of doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started writing out how acting with justice has helped me in all these ways, but I can’t explain it better than Marcus Aurelius himself. Here are some of my favorite meditations on doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel affection for people even when they make mistakes is uniquely human. You can do it, if you simply recognize: that they’re human too, that they act out of ignorance, against their will, and that you’ll both be dead before long. And, above all, that they haven’t really hurt you. They haven’t diminished your ability to choose.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When people injure you, ask yourself what good or harm they thought would come of it. If you understand that, you’ll feel sympathy rather than outrage or anger. Your sense of good and evil may be the same as theirs, or near it, in which case you have to excuse them. Or your sense of good and evil may differ from theirs. In which case they’re misguided and deserve your compassion. Is that so hard?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To do harm is to do yourself harm. To do an injustice is to do yourself an injustice - it degrades you.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When faced with people’s bad behavior, turn around ask when &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; have acted like that. When you saw money as good, or pleasure, or social position. Your anger will subside as soon as you recognize that they acted under compulsion (what else could they do?)…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 10.30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“That you don’t know for sure it &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; a mistake. A lot of things are means to some other end. You have to know an awful lot before you can judge other people’s actions with real understanding.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 11.18.v&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you believe doing good as the highest objective, you feel good when you do it. &lt;strong&gt;Acting with justice and virtue is its own reward because acting virtuously is synonymous with doing good to others and preserving your integrity. With self fulfillment and happiness as a bonus.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What is the goal of virtue, after all, except a life that flows smoothly?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Epictetus, Book I, 108&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with one last meditation that sums up Aurelius’s and the Stoics point-of-view and reason for doing good as the highest objective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…And how does it injure you anyway? You’ll find that none of the people you’re upset about has done anything that could do damage to your mind. But that’s all that “harm” or “injury” could mean. Yes, boorish people do boorish things. What’s strange or unheard of about that? Isn’t it yourself you should reproach - for not anticipating that they’d act this way? The logos gave you the means to see it - that a person would act a given way - but you paid no attention. And now you’re astonished that he’s gone and done it. So when you call someone “untrustworthy” or “ungrateful,” turn the reproach on yourself. It was you who did wrong. By assuming that someone with those traits deserved your trust. Or by doing them a favor and expecting something in return, instead of looking to the action itself for your reward. What else did you expect from helping someone out? Isn’t it enough that you’ve done what your nature demands? You want a salary for it, too? As if your eyes expected a reward for seeing, or your feet for walking. That’s what they were made for. By doing what they were designed to do, they’re performing their function. Whereas humans were made to help others. And when we do help others - or help them to do something - we’re doing what we were designed for. We perform our function.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Before learning about philosophy, I used to believe the amount of impact one has on the world was the highest objective we should aim to achieve in life.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Effective Executive — Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Effective Executive — Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2019-08-12T07:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-12T07:30:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker">&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Drucker&quot;&gt;Peter Drucker&lt;/a&gt;, there are eight practices that make effective executives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “what needs to be done?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “what is right for the company?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop action plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take responsibility for decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take responsibility for communicating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on opportunities rather than problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run productive meetings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think and say “we” rather than “I”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two give you the knowledge you need. The next four convert that knowledge into effective action. The last two gets your team to feel responsible and inspired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Effective Executive, Drucker explains what an effective executive is and how to become one. He believed being an effective executive could be learned and this book served as a handbook to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Executives are doers; they execute. Knowledge is useless to executives until it has been translated into deeds. But before springing into action, the executive needs to plan his course. He needs to think about desired results, probable restraints, future revisions, check-in points, and implications for how he’ll spend his time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-an-executive-effective&quot;&gt;What Makes an Executive Effective?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking “what do I want to do?” ask “what has to be done?” This is crucial for managerial success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The answer to this question “…almost always contains more than one urgent task. But effective executives do not splinter themselves. They concentrate on one task if at all possible. […] I have never encountered an executive who remains effective while tackling more than two tasks at a time. Hence, after asking what needs to be done, the effective executive sets priorities and sticks to them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the top initiatives prioritized, you need to choose which you are especially good at undertaking and then delegate the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives try to focus on jobs they’ll do especially well. They know that enterprises perform if top management performs—and don’t if it doesn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-is-the-beginning-of-your-action-plan&quot;&gt;This is the beginning of your action plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your action plan is a prioritized list of initiatives and tasks for you and your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The action plan is a statement of intentions rather than a commitment. It must not become a straitjacket. It should be revised often, because every success creates new opportunities. So does every failure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Develop the plan in a tool that makes it easy to check-in, provide updates, and move items around as it progresses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Napoleon allegedly said that no successful battle ever followed its plan. Yet Napoleon also planned every one of his battles, far more meticulously than any earlier general had done. Without an action plan, the executive becomes a prisoner of events. And without check-ins to reexamine the plan as events unfold, the executive has no way of knowing which events really matter and which are only noise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And an action plan is useless unless it’s communicated and understood by your teams.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decision has not really been made until people know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is accountable for delivering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the deadline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who and which teams are affected by the decision and therefore have to understand and approve it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who else should be informed of the decision, even if not directly affected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action plan shouldn’t be given as an order from the top. Get and incorporate feedback. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives make sure that both their action plans and their information needs are understood. Specifically, this means that they share their plans with and ask for comments from all their colleagues—superiors, subordinates, and peers. At the same time, they let each person know what information they’ll need to get the job done. The information flow from subordinate to boss is usually what gets the most attention. But executives need to pay equal attention to peers’ and superiors’ information needs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Although problems stick out like a nail begging to be hammered, don’t make fixing a problem a top priority.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Good executives focus on opportunities rather than problems. Problems have to be taken care of, of course; they must not be swept under the rug. But problem solving, however necessary, does not produce results. It prevents damage. Exploiting opportunities produces results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when delegating tasks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives put their best people on opportunities rather than on problems.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When Drucker recalls how an effective executive would run a meeting, he thinks back on an old colleague of his.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“At the beginning of a formal meeting, Sloan announced the meeting’s purpose. He then listened. He never took notes and he rarely spoke except to clarify a confusing point. At the end he summed up, thanked the participants, and left. Then he immediately wrote a short memo addressed to one attendee of the meeting. In that note, he summarized the discussion and its conclusions and spelled out any work assignment decided upon in the meeting (including a decision to hold another meeting on the subject or to study an issue). He specified the deadline and the executive who was to be accountable for the assignment. He sent a copy of the memo to everyone who’d been present at the meeting. It was through these memos—each a small masterpiece—that Sloan made himself into an outstandingly effective executive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;effectiveness-can-be-learned&quot;&gt;Effectiveness Can Be Learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one thing to come up with a good idea. It’s another thing all together to execute that idea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Brilliant men are often strikingly ineffectual; they fail to realize that the brilliant insight is not by itself achievement. […] Intelligence, imagination, and knowledge are essential resources, but only effectiveness converts them into results. By themselves, they only set limits to what can be attained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effective-executive-are-masters-of-their-time&quot;&gt;Effective Executive Are Masters of Their Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the most out of your time and your team’s time is an essential first step to becoming effecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[Effective executives] start with their time. And they do not start out with planning. They start by finding out where their time actually goes. Then they attempt to manage their time and to cut back unproductive demands on their time. Finally they consolidate their “discretionary” time into the largest possible continuing units.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To master your time, follow this three step process:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record your time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;manage your time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consolidate your time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The first step toward executive effectiveness is therefore to record actual time-use.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-on-recording-time&quot;&gt;Tips on Recording Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measure it in real-time, not later from memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recording time is a habit that can improve with constant effort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figure out how to make time management systematic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve been recording your time, you can analyze it and see what the time wasters are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To find these time-wastes, one asks of all activities in the time records: ‘What would happen if this were not done at all?’ And if the answer is, ‘Nothing would happen,’ then obviously the conclusion is to stop doing it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then determine which of the activities left can be delegated to some else. Now you can see how much time you have for important tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The executive who records and analyzes his time and then attempts to manage it can determine how much he has for his important tasks. How much time is there that is “discretionary,” that is, available for the big tasks that will really make a contribution? It is not going to be a great deal, no matter how ruthlessly the executive prunes time-wasters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker discovered that it’s much more effective to block open time in as large of chunks as possible to get into deep work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The effective executive therefore knows that he has to consolidate his [open] time. He knows that he needs large chunks of time and that small driblets are no time at all. Even one quarter of the working day, if consolidated in large time units, is usually enough to get the important things done. But even three quarters of the working day are useless if they are only available as fifteen minutes here or half an hour there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Time is the scarcest resource, and unless it is managed, nothing else can be managed. The analysis of one’s time, moreover, is the one easily accessible and yet systematic way to analyze one’s work and to think through what really matters in it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;executives-are-also-responsible-for-their-teams-time&quot;&gt;Executives are Also Responsible for Their Team’s Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common time waste is when the executive wastes his individual team members’ time. To overcome this, Drucker advises executives to directly as their team if and how he/she wastes their time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives have learned to ask systematically and without coyness: “What do I do that wastes your time without contributing to your effectiveness?” To ask this question, and to ask it without being afraid of the truth, is a mark of the effective executive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-on-managing-meetings&quot;&gt;Tips on Managing Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like to be “in the know” and aware of what’s going on. Effective executives should let the whole team know when a meeting will take place and on what topic. Make it optional for people to join so they don’t feel left out. In any case, summarize the meeting notes, send to the team, and allow for questions and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Meetings are by definition a concession to deficient organization for one either meets or one works. One cannot do both at the same time. In an ideally designed structure (which in a changing world is of course only a dream) there would be no meetings. Everybody would know what he needs to know to do his job. Everyone would have the resources available to him to do his job. We meet because people holding different jobs have to cooperate to get a specific task done. We meet because the knowledge and experience needed in a specific situation are not available in one head, but have to be pieced together out of the experience and knowledge of several people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to run meetings effectively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The effective man always states at the outset of a meeting the specific purpose and contribution it is to achieve. He makes sure that the meeting addresses itself to this purpose. He does not allow a meeting called to inform to degenerate into a “bull session” in which everyone has bright ideas. But a meeting called by him to stimulate thinking and ideas also does not become simply a presentation on the part of one of the members, but is run to challenge and stimulate everybody in the room. He always, at the end of his meetings, goes back to the opening statement and relates the final conclusions to the original intent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-effective-executive-focuses-on-contribution&quot;&gt;The Effective Executive Focuses on Contribution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective executive are always focusing on contribution that makes a positive impact on the company’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The man who focuses on efforts and who stresses his downward authority is a subordinate no matter how exalted his title and rank. But the man who focuses on contribution and who takes responsibility for results, no matter how junior, is in the most literal sense of the phrase, “top management.” He holds himself accountable for the performance of the whole.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to achieve that, you can’t only look inward to what you want to do and what you think you can do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The focus on contribution turns the executive’s attention away from his own specialty, his own narrow skills, his own department, and toward the performance of the whole. It turns his attention to the outside, the only place where there are results. He is likely to have to think through what relationships his skills, his specialty, his function, or his department have to the entire organization and its purpose. He therefore will also come to think in terms of the customer, the client, or the patient, who is the ultimate reason for whatever the organization produces, whether it be economic goods, governmental policies, or health services. As a result, what he does and how he does it will be materially different.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-areas-of-contribution&quot;&gt;Three Areas of Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value building and reaffirmation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If deprived of performance in any one of these areas, it will decay and die. All three therefore have to be built into the contribution of every executive. But their relative importance varies greatly with the personality and the position of the executive as well as with the needs of the organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you focus on contribution, it will help you fulfill the four basic requirements of effective human relations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;communications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;teamwork&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;development of others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helping others be successful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives find themselves asking other people in the organization, their superiors, their subordinates, but above all, their colleagues in other areas: ‘What contribution from me do you require to make your contribution to the organization? When do you need this, how do you need it, and in what form?’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of all, the biggest benefit of focusing on contribution is it counteracts chaos and highlights what’s important to spend time on versus what’s noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The focus on contribution imposes an organizing principle. It imposes relevance on events. Focusing on contribution turns one of the inherent weaknesses of the executive’s situation—his dependence on other people, his being within the organization—into a source of strength. It creates a team. Finally, focusing on contribution fights the temptation to stay within the organization. It leads the executive—especially the top-level man—to lift his eyes from the inside of efforts, work, and relationships, to the outside; that is, to the results of the organization. It makes him try hard to have direct contact with the outside—whether markets and customers, patients in a community, or the various “publics” which are the outside of a government agency. To focus on contribution is to focus on effectiveness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-strengths-productive&quot;&gt;Making Strengths Productive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker makes the argument that it’s best to build on strengths to achieve results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The effective executive fills positions and promotes on the basis of what a man can do. He does not make staffing decisions to minimize weaknesses but to maximize strength.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;staffing-for-strength&quot;&gt;Staffing for Strength&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two rules to staff for strengths:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for strength in one major area. Ask, ‘what can this person do uncommonly well?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make each job demanding with a deep scope so their strengths can produce significant results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…every people-decision is a gamble. By basing it on what a man can do, it becomes at least a rational gamble.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spotting-team-members-not-using-their-strengths&quot;&gt;Spotting Team Members Not Using Their Strengths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your responsibility to spot and guide those on your team who aren’t making their strength’s productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The ones who are enthusiastic and who, in turn, have results to show for their work, are the ones whose abilities are being challenged and used. Those that are deeply frustrated all say, in one way or another: ‘My abilities are not being put to use.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your job to know when this is happening, correct it, and be ahead of it so it’s unlikely to occur again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The assertion that “somebody else will not let me do anything” should always be suspected as a cover-up for inertia. But even where the situation does set limitations—and everyone lives and works within rather stringent limitations—there are usually important, meaningful, pertinent things that can be done. The effective executive looks for them. If he starts out with the question: “What can I do?” he is almost certain to find that he can actually do much more than he has time and resources for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-things-first&quot;&gt;First Things First&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effectiveness is reached by focusing on one thing at time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Concentration is necessary precisely because the executive faces so many tasks clamoring to be done. For doing one thing at a time means doing it fast. The more one can concentrate time, effort, and resources, the greater the number and diversity of tasks one can actually perform.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you don’t focus on one thing at a time, you end up working harder and at the same time get nothing done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The people who get nothing done often work a great deal harder. In the first place, they underestimate the time for any one task. They always expect that everything will go right. Yet, as every executive knows, nothing ever goes right. The unexpected always happens—the unexpected is indeed the only thing one can confidently expect. And almost never is it a pleasant surprise. Effective executives therefore allow a fair margin of time beyond what is actually needed. In the second place, the typical (that is, the more or less ineffectual) executive tries to hurry—and that only puts him further behind. Effective executives do not race. They set an easy pace but keep going steadily. Finally, the typical executive tries to do several things at once. Therefore, he never has the minimum time quantum for any of the tasks in his program. If any one of them runs into trouble, his entire program collapses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always stay updated to the current programs, activities, and tasks. If something isn’t worth doing anymore, it’s better to stop it sooner than later and refocus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Systematic sloughing off of the old is the one and only way to force the new. There is no lack of ideas in any organization I know. “Creativity” is not our problem. But few organizations ever get going on their own good ideas. Everybody is much too busy on the tasks of yesterday. Putting all programs and activities regularly on trial for their lives and getting rid of those that cannot prove their productivity work wonders in stimulating creativity even in the most hidebound bureaucracy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Concentration—that is, the courage to impose on time and events his own decision as to what really matters and comes first—is the executive’s only hope of becoming the master of time and events instead of their whipping boy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-elements-of-decision-making&quot;&gt;The Elements of Decision-Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker has a lot to say on decision making and how to do it effecively. I found these two sections way too long and verbose for my attention span. Although, I really like the below quote about how data-driven decisions should be seen as having a degree of risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Finding the appropriate measurement is thus not a mathematical exercise. It is a risk-taking judgment. Whenever one has to judge, one must have alternatives among which one can choose. A judgment in which one can only say “yes” or “no” is no judgment at all. Only if there are alternatives can one hope to get insight into what is truly at stake. Effective executives therefore insist on alternatives of measurement—so that they can choose the one appropriate one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-topics-on-effectiveness-that-stood-out-to-me&quot;&gt;Other Topics on Effectiveness that Stood Out to Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;generalist-vs-specialist&quot;&gt;Generalist vs specialist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The only meaningful definition of a “generalist” is a specialist who can relate his own small area to the universe of knowledge. Maybe a few people have knowledge in more than a few small areas. But that does not make them generalists; it makes them specialists in several areas. And one can be just as bigoted in three areas as in one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;allowing-people-to-take-risks&quot;&gt;Allowing people to take risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Executives also owe it to the organization and to their fellow workers not to tolerate nonperforming individuals in important jobs. It may not be the employees’ fault that they are underperforming, but even so, they have to be removed. People who have failed in a new job should be given the choice to go back to a job at their former level and salary. This option is rarely exercised; such people, as a rule, leave voluntarily, at least when their employers are U.S. firms. But the very existence of the option can have a powerful effect, encouraging people to leave safe, comfortable jobs and take risky new assignments. The organization’s performance depends on employees’ willingness to take such chances.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-people&quot;&gt;Developing people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“An executive’s focus on contribution by itself is a powerful force in developing people. People adjust to the level of the demands made on them. The executive who sets his sights on contribution raises the sights and standards of everyone with whom he works.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…executives who take responsibility for contribution in their own work will as a rule demand that their subordinates take responsibility too. They will tend to ask their men: “What are the contributions for which this organization and I, your superior, should hold you accountable? What should we expect of you? What is the best utilization of your knowledge and your ability?” And then communication becomes possible, becomes indeed easy. Once the subordinate has thought through what contribution should be expected of him, the superior has, of course, both the right and the responsibility to judge the validity of the proposed contribution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A superior has responsibility for the work of others. He also has power over the careers of others. Making strengths productive is therefore much more than an essential of effectiveness. It is a moral imperative, a responsibility of authority and position. To focus on weakness is not only foolish; it is irresponsible. A superior owes it to his organization to make the strength of every one of his subordinates as productive as it can be. But even more does he owe it to the human beings over whom he exercises authority to help them get the most out of whatever strength they may have.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">According to Peter Drucker, there are eight practices that make effective executives:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/peter-drucker.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/peter-drucker.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Netlify Analytics Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/netlify-analytics-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Netlify Analytics Review" /><published>2019-07-24T18:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T18:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/netlify-analytics-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/netlify-analytics-review">&lt;p&gt;Netlify Analytics is a server side analytics tool that doesn’t slow down your website, protects the privacy of your users, and is GDPR compliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released in July 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/products/analytics/&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics&lt;/a&gt; is a new add-on to Netlify’s popular hosting and deployment platform. Starting at $9/month, it’s an “expensive” alternative to the analytics king, Google Analytics, which is free. But is it worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought it to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-good-about-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;What is Good About Netlify Analytics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netlify Analytics doesn’t slow down your website at all since you don’t need to add any code to your site. Installation was as easy as clicking a button in my Netlify backend. And since it’s anonymous and doesn’t use javascript or cookies, users with adblock are still counted and I didn’t need to add any cookie warnings on my site for GDPR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-can-see-in-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;What You Can See in Netlify Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pageviews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unique visitors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top viewed pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top pages/resources not found&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top sources/referrers (with path)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bandwidth used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-cant-you-see-in-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;What Can’t You See in Netlify Analytics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;you can’t see beyond the last 30 days&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t filter by page or change the date range&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t look at the top sources for an individual page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t see the bounce rate or average time on site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-netlify-analytics-worth-it&quot;&gt;Is Netlify Analytics Worth It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Not right now. At $9/month for a product whose competitors are free and more capable, everyone was expecting more from this release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics-pricing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Netlify Analytics starts at $9/month.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics starts at $9/month.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You only have one “screen” without a single filter to segment your data.&lt;/strong&gt; Most egregious though is they delete data older than 30 days (or at least it’s not accessible). Second, I need to be able to break down referrer and pageviews by URL so I can see from where and how much traffic specific pages are getting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it is now, Netlify Analytics is a great product for people who have a simple curiosity for a site or project’s stats. And if you really care about shaving milliseconds off load times or capturing ad block users, Netlify Analytics could be for you. But if you just casually need analytics, are you going to pay $9/month for it? I’m not sure it’s worth it, but many people are happy to give Netlify $9/month for Analytics because their free hosting and deployment platform is so good that they just want to support them. It’s not all bad news for Netlify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But remember, this is version one of Netlify Analytics. If Netlify can improve the product by adding the above features, it very well could be a game changer - something I’m eagerly anticipating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives-to-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;Alternatives to Netlify Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/&quot;&gt;Fathom Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://simpleanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Simple Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although both Fathom and Simple Analytics are not server-side analytics, they are both GDPR compliant and focused on user privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just signed up for Fathom and will do a review soon to see how it compares to Netlify Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why I stopped blogging on Medium and moved to a static, self hosted blog.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;medium vs self hosted blog&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Netlify Analytics is a server side analytics tool that doesn’t slow down your website, protects the privacy of your users, and is GDPR compliant.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog" /><published>2019-07-19T11:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-19T11:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog">&lt;p&gt;Most people stop blogging on Medium because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t “own” your traffic because your blog is on medium.com&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have less control of converting traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medium promotes other peoples’ articles on your own articles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More readers are dedicated to Medium than dedicated to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the switch wasn’t about the “building a house on rented land” aspect. I was early to Medium publications so I could use my custom domain (regpaq.com) on Medium. Thankfully I got in before they removed this feature so I shouldn’t lose any rankings since I’m still on the same domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what made me want to stop blogging on Medium? The stats.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium’s stats are broken and very limited. I want to be able to see three things for a given period of my choosing. How much is my traffic growing? What’s the distribution of traffic between pages? Where is that traffic coming from? This isn’t possible on Medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problems-with-medium-stats&quot;&gt;The Problems with Medium Stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one huge problem with Medium stats. &lt;strong&gt;They include views of your comments on other people’s articles in your view count!&lt;/strong&gt; And there is no way to filter them out. So no, you can’t see how many total views just your articles received over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-stats.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My last 30 days blogging on Medium for all articles... and comments.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My last 30 days blogging on Medium for all articles... and comments.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The other major problem is you can only view your traffic in 30 day windows.&lt;/strong&gt; If you got a lot of views one day, you can’t look at just that day’s traffic and see what pages got the most views or where that traffic came from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above the graph, Medium suggests you can click a story to see stats for just that story. Unfortunately, when you click on a story it loads a new page and takes five seconds to load. &lt;strong&gt;So you have to click each individual story one by one to uncover which story went “viral” and racked up the most views on a big traffic day.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-referrers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Limited referrer data for a blog post on Medium.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Limited referrer data for a blog post on Medium.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inside an individual story’s stats, you can see the list of referrers. But only the domain.&lt;/strong&gt; In the above example, I can’t see which Reddit threads are talking about my article! Which means I can’t see what people are saying and jump in the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started blogging on Medium, I knew the stats were limited, but I didn’t know by how much. The reason I moved to Medium in the first place was because I wanted simplicity. I wanted simple metrics. I didn’t want to fiddle with the design. I didn’t want to mess with plugins. I wanted a better editor than WordPress. I just wanted to write. But now things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limited-customization-on-medium&quot;&gt;Limited Customization on Medium&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest pros of blogging on Medium is that the design is all done for you. You don’t have to worry about it. It’s always better to write and publish more than to fiddle with the design. What changed for me was a massive increase in interest in learning HTML and CSS. &lt;strong&gt;By moving off of Medium, my blog is now a showcase for my design and dev skills.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I didn’t go back to WordPress and instead used &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator. It was a much bigger process than I anticipated. I designed the site in Adobe XD then developed it. &lt;strong&gt;The end result is a blog I designed and I developed with articles I wrote and I illustrated. It’s a culmination of many of my skills in a single project.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-sites-are-fast&quot;&gt;Static Sites are Fast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit to a static site is the speed. Because WordPress and Medium use a database, it loads much slower. Here is the Pingdom page speed and Google score comparison of the same article on Medium versus the current static site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-pingdom-old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medium article page speed from Pingdom.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Medium article page speed from Pingdom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-google-old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medium article page speed score from Google.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Medium article page speed score from Google.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-pingdom-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Static article page speed from Pingdom.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Static article page speed from Pingdom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-google-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Static article page speed score from Google.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Static article page speed score from Google.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The static site is a massive improvement for speed&lt;/strong&gt; - even without any image optimization. This should improve the bounce rate and thus increase organic rankings. But because people know what to expect when they land on a Medium-designed article, it’s possible the new design increases the bounce rate. I’ll never know for certain because you can’t measure the bounce rate on Medium. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one catch here about the speed of my site. I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;Netlify’s new Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, which is a server side analytics solution. It measures at the server level so it’s not adding an extra request to the page, like Google Analytics would. The problem is Netlify’s Analytics is even worse than Medium’s so I’ll be switching to Google Analytics or Clicky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics Review&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Is it everything the industry has been waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;netlify analytics review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ill-miss-about-blogging-on-medium&quot;&gt;What I’ll Miss About Blogging on Medium&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium’s coolest social feature is “claps.” If people like your article, they can clap for it up to 50 times. It’s nice to get and give claps, but it does have a downside. Medium syndicates and recommends articles to other users based on how many claps it gets. &lt;strong&gt;This made me too focused on claps. I even joined three Facebook groups where people just clap for each others’ articles. It’s a stupid game.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also miss comments until I can figure out a solution. Because static sites don’t have databases, comments are difficult to add. I don’t want to use something like Disqus, which increases load time and prevents me from “owning” the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I won’t miss Medium’s distribution. I never got any meaningful distribution. I could have written more content for more claps, but I didn’t want to play that game.&lt;/strong&gt; I want to write what I want to write about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now onto finding which analytics tool I’m going to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics Review&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Is it everything the industry has been waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;netlify analytics review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Most people stop blogging on Medium because:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stop Comparing Yourself to Others — Use This Benchmark Instead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop Comparing Yourself to Others — Use This Benchmark Instead" /><published>2019-02-13T12:11:11-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T12:11:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others">&lt;p&gt;The frequently given advice to not compare yourself with others and only to who you were yesterday never quite satisfied me. It still left a lot of questions unanswered and I recently discovered on Reddit many other people feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/productivity/comments/ao04vn/stop_comparing_yourself_to_others_and_start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent post on r/productivity&lt;/a&gt;, there were some top comments refuting this advice with how they actually like to use jealousy, greed, and wanting to be better than other people as motivation to achieve “greatness.” Not only is comparing yourself to others the wrong way to achieve true greatness, so is comparing yourself to who you were yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being better than who you were yesterday should be the bare minimum you strive for, because it doesn’t allow you to achieve what you’re fully capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it doesn’t confirm you’re on the right path to begin with. On its own, “compare yourself to who you were yesterday” is only feel-good advice that has very little practical usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why there’s some rationality behind why we tend to compare ourselves to others. You can see in your physical or digital circle who the low achievers are and who the high achievers are — giving you the missing benchmark of effort and success. But in the end, it’s a terrible benchmark that will have devastating effects on your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparing-yourself-to-others-leads-you-to-falsepaths&quot;&gt;Comparing Yourself to Others Leads You to False Paths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, I was introduced to and befriended a very successful guy who day traded for a living. I didn’t know anything about the world of finance, but seeing the success he had and hearing how much he would make in any given day was exhilarating. &lt;strong&gt;As time went on, my benchmark for effort and success expanded to include his. I began to compare what I had achieved to him. “Success” now meant nothing short of what he had achieved.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told myself I needed to do everything I could to achieve that level of success. I decided to learn how to be a day trader and I went so far as to sell my dream car to get the cash to do it. With studying and his mentorship, I started to make a few hundred dollars per week. As my confidence and greed grew, I became less risk-averse. &lt;strong&gt;Half a year later, my losses totaled close to $10k.&lt;/strong&gt; I closed my account and threw my dreams of riches and day trading out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started to compare myself to him, and what I had to what he had, it led me to abandon my path and join the path that made him successful. I never had any prior interest in stocks or studied the financial markets. I was just chasing the money and that led to disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Using others as a benchmark for success can lead to conformity — it can take you away from what you’re happy and good at doing and put you on a false path — chasing money, status, or attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a never ending trap. There will always be someone to compare yourself to with more money, more status, and more fame that will lead you off your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everyone gets one life. Yours is almost used up, and instead of treating yourself with respect, you have entrusted your own happiness to the souls of others.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-fate-and-luck-always-play-a-significant-role-in-someones-success&quot;&gt;Understand Fate and Luck Always Play a Significant Role in Someone’s Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us is a completely unique individual with a unique genetic makeup. We’re all raised by different people, with different values, and in different environments — all of which significantly impact our character and what we do in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will shout, “you can do anything you set your mind to” or “you just need to work harder” or “you’re not sacrificing enough.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/u/65e0b0f45be5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nat Eliason&lt;/a&gt; made some noise when he called out Gary Vaynerchuk as an example of someone who does this in a piece he wrote titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@nateliason/no-more-struggle-porn-202153a01108&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;No More “Struggle Porn.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While we do need to have ruthless discipline to reach our greatest potential, we cannot ignore the limits imposed on us by the cards we’re dealt or we will forever be dissatisfied with who we are and what we’ve accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another reason why it doesn’t make sense to compare ourselves to others: luck. &lt;strong&gt;No one’s success is ever only down to luck, but we can’t ignore the role luck plays in success as an “x” factor — it’s unmanageable and unpredictable.&lt;/strong&gt; The only thing in your control is to continually put yourself in positions to catch lucky breaks. And remember: luck is not distributed evenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Q&amp;amp;A with White House interns, President Obama gave advice on the subject luck has with success and what to focus on instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A lot of times, it’s just happenstance. Or things work out. But being useful? And having a satisfying life? And making a contribution? That is entirely within your control. Orient yourself towards having an impact and making a difference. And you will and you’ll be happy doing it.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Former President Barack Obama, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5IDQDoxXHm0?start=516&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instead-of-comparing-yourself-to-others-or-who-you-were-yesterday-find-your-truepath&quot;&gt;Instead of Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday, Find Your True Path&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity is worthless if you’re on a false path. Your goal and motivation shouldn’t be about just being the best or better than the people in your circles, but creating something useful that can make a difference in peoples’ lives and your community. This is the truest benchmark for success and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People who labor all their lives but have no purpose to direct every thought and impulse toward are wasting their time — even when hard at work.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your true path is doing what you were made for — what you feel you have an inclination and natural ability for. This inclination is a reflection of your unique genetic code, deep underlying preferences for particular activities or forms of expression. When you find your true path, you’ll be less inclined to compare your success with someone else. &lt;strong&gt;You will quickly realize their path isn’t a good fit for you.&lt;/strong&gt; And you won’t be as inclined to envy their money, attention, or whatever, because craving those things is a false path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the end, the money and success that truly last come not to those who focus on such things as goals, but rather to those who focus on mastery and fulfilling their Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Robert Greene, &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need to compare yourself to others is restrained when you’re happy and comfortable with who you are, which comes from being on your true path and working on your Life’s Task. You will no longer envy other peoples’ success and happiness, and you will instead be laser-focused on your own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Don’t aim at success — the more you aim at it and make it a target, the more you are going to miss it. For success, like happiness, cannot be pursued; it must ensue, and it only does so as the unintended side-effect of one’s dedication to a cause greater than oneself…”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Viktor Frankl, Man’s Search for Meaning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can’t be disciplined, happy, and confident all the time. I’ve made journaling a daily habit of mine to give myself the opportunity to reflect on and ground my thoughts. It’s an exercise that has helped me live a more level-headed and purposeful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Inspired by the journal method of Marcus Aurelius.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;stoic journal topics&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ignoring what goes on in other people’s souls — no one ever came to grief that way. But if you won’t keep track of what your own soul’s doing, how you can you not be unhappy?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing yourself to others is a recipe for disaster. Comparing yourself to who you were yesterday is a recipe for passivity. Life is not about being better than other people. It’s not about achieving more than people in our circles. &lt;strong&gt;Life is about being useful to others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">The frequently given advice to not compare yourself with others and only to who you were yesterday never quite satisfied me. It still left a lot of questions unanswered and I recently discovered on Reddit many other people feel the same way.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development" /><published>2019-02-07T06:52:48-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T06:52:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics">&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, often called the philosopher emperor, is a famous stoic philosopher and known as the last good emperor of Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of his journal entries to himself have been recovered and curated into a single book title Meditations, which is widely recognized as one of the most influential pieces of stoic philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of journaling allowed Marcus Aurelius, and can allow us today, to think more clearly and live a more virtuous life. The following stoic journal prompts and topics can help guide your journaling practice toward stoic thought exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-gratitude&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Gratitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a moment to reflect on the value added to your life by the people around you will help you appreciate them and the relationship you have with them, which in turn could spark behavior that strengthens those relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People to consider: significant other, family, friends, coworkers, and people who’ve impacted your life in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value has [person] added to my life? What wisdom, achievements, or fortunate events of mine can I give them some credit for?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value do I (or can I) add to [person’s] life in return?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does [person] affect and influence my life decisions, feelings, and behavior?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What characteristics does [person] have that I admire?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are my best characteristics and who influenced me to develop them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also reflect on your achievements, major events, and material things in your life to establish gratitude for you’ve done and what you have, which will suppress feelings of unhappiness and cravings for new and better things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is an accomplishment I’m very proud of? Why am I proud of it? What can I do to do more things like that?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is one of my most cherished memories and why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of an item in your possession you want to upgrade. Is your current item functioning well enough? What do you appreciate about it? What sustained value will an upgrade add to your life?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at what you have and the things you value most. How much would you crave them if you didn’t have them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-to-suppress-negative-thoughts&quot;&gt;Journal Topics to Suppress Negative Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negative and low value thoughts are fuel for chaos, passivity, and unhappiness. These topics can help control your negative thoughts by thinking through them rationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Like seeing roasted meat and other dishes in front of you and suddenly realizing: This is a dead fish. A dead bird. A dead pig. Or that this noble vintage is grape juice,… Perceptions like that — latching onto things and piercing through them, so we see what they really are. That’s what we need to do all the time… to lay them bare and see how pointless they are…”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of an item you craved to have and eventually purchased. How do you feel about that item now? Was the craving warranted?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you really want to buy right now? What value will that add to your life? What value will be lost if you don’t buy it? Is there a better use for the money you would have to spend to acquire it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of something you‘ve done that you regret. Write an apology to yourself and a response of forgiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-improving-your-character&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Improving Your Character&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his journal, it was apparent that Marcus Aurelius wrote about recurring philosophical tenets in order to continually practice his philosophy. Try doing the same for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel grief, anger, or fear is to try to escape from something decreed by the ruler of all things, now or in the past or in the future. And that ruler is law, which governs what happens to each of us. To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive — a fugitive from justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of a philosophical or ethical tenet that you struggle to live by. Write down the tenet and again in your own words. Try crafting your own analogy. Do this as often as you need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of someone you admire. Write yourself advice you think they would give you from their point-of-view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of 12 year-old you. What “secrets of life” have you acquired that you would want to share with yourself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-daily-reflection--improvement&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Daily Reflection &amp;amp; Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our daily behavior is the best indicator of the type of person we are. Work on improving what you do each day and you will in turn be improving the type of person you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Remember that our own worth is measured by what we devote our energy to.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I lose control of my emotions today? What triggered it? Was that a reasonable response?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I do today that was out of character? What triggered it? Was that a reasonable response?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did you do today that was not a good use of your time?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you miss accomplishing an important habit or step in your routine today? What do you think was the reason for it and how can you prevent it from happening again?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I crave today? Describe what you craved in its most simplistic form. Did it warrant that level of craving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Break Bad Habits for Good&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The best tips from Atomic Habits on breaking your worse habits&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to break bad habits&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done-app-review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Marcus Aurelius, often called the philosopher emperor, is a famous stoic philosopher and known as the last good emperor of Rome.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2019-02-05T22:48:39-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-05T22:48:39-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene">&lt;p&gt;Mastery by Robert Greene is a practical read on helping people find and pursue their Life’s Task (purpose).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally felt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt; was a bit disorganized at times, which was especially apparent looking back at my notes. So below are quotes and thoughts that stuck out to me in the best order I could provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--sml gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mastery.png&quot; alt=&quot;Buy Mastery on Amazon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot;&gt;Buy Mastery on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-mastery-and-why-pursueit&quot;&gt;What is Mastery and Why Pursue It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mastery — the feeling that we have a greater command of reality, other people, and ourselves. Although it might be something we experience for only a short while, for others — Masters of their field — it becomes their way of life, their way of seeing the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pursuit of mastery is the pursuit of purpose, whatever your Life’s Task, as Greene refers to it, may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is not mastery for the purpose of dominating nature or other people, but for determining our fate… You are contributing to the most important cause of all — the survival and prosperity of the human race, in a time of stagnation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because being on the path of mastery requires discipline and a strong work ethic towards a craft you enjoy, you will be working towards something great and something you can be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;James Clear points out your daily habits define who you are in Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;, Greene also says pursuing mastery is important because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…people get the mind and quality of brain that they deserve through their actions in life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road to mastery can be defined by three phases and Mastery goes into depth on each phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apprenticeship — you’re a student learning from others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative-Active — you’re a practitioner, adding your own creativity and style to your craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mastery — you have complete command of the craft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”[Masters] excel by their ability to practice harder and move faster through the process, all of this stemming from the intensity of their desire to learn and from the deep connection they feel to their field of study. And at the core of this intensity of effort is in fact a quality that is genetic and inborn — not talent or brilliance, which is something that must be developed, but rather a deep and powerful inclination toward a particular subject.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masters become masters not because they seek fame, money, or an outcome, but because they’re obsessed with their craft. There are no shortcuts to mastery. It takes time. It takes effort. There will be failures along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-most-people-dont-achieve-mastery-in-their-lives&quot;&gt;Why Most People Don’t Achieve Mastery in Their Lives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A natural response when people feel overwhelmed is to retreat into various forms of passivity… The less we attempt, the less chances of failure. If we can make it look like we are not really responsible for our fate, for what happens to us in life, then our apparent powerlessness is more palatable. For this reason we become attracted to certain narratives: it is genetics that determines much of what we do; we are just products of our times…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are born into a reality that has existed before us with masters already present. We see them online, in TV, we read about them. When we start working toward a particular field, we learn who the masters are already. It’s easy to become envious and to think, “I’ll never be as good, as famous, as well liked by the community. They were born with more natural talent. Why should I try too hard?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the attitude of most people and it can have devastating consequences toward your Life’s Task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This [attitude] can diminish your levels of effort and discipline below the point of effectiveness. Conforming to social norms, you will listen more to others than to your own voice. You may choose a career path based on what peers and parents tell you, or on what seems lucrative. If you lose contact with this inner calling, you can have some success in life, but eventually your lack of true desire catches up with you. Your work becomes mechanical. You come to live for leisure and immediate pleasures. In this way you become increasingly passive, and never move past the first phase. You may grow frustrated and depressed, never realizing that the source of it is your alienation from your own creative potential.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you get past this passive attitude? For one, you must find your Life’s Task — your natural inclination towards a particular field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This intense connection and desire allows them to withstand the pain of the process — the self doubts, the tedious hours of practice and stuffy, the inevitable setbacks, the endless barbs from the envious. They develop a resiliency and confidence that others lack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you know you Life’s Task, you can work through inevitable roadblocks, challenges, and failures. You will find it easier to get back up again, to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discovering-your-calling-the-lifestask&quot;&gt;Discovering Your Calling: The Life’s Task&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a difference between wishing you were a master at something, and wishing you were doing something to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…he didn’t care so much about the finished product; it was the search and process in creating something that had always excited him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to love the work. You have to feel a profound connection to it. You must be obsessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Work is often seen as a means for making money so we can enjoy that second life that we lead.… This is a depressing attitude, because in the end we spend a substantial part of our waking life at work. If we experience this time as something to get through on the way to real pleasure, then our hours at work represent a tragic waste of the short time we have to live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you find work that you love to do, it doesn’t feel like work is something you have to do to live, but an opportunity to create something beyond yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find work you like, Greene recommends trying various fields you’ve always been interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Eventually, you will hit upon a particular field, niche, or opportunity that suits you perfectly. You will recognize it when you find it because it will spark that childlike sense of wonder and excitement; it will feel right. Once found, everything will fall into place. You will learn more quickly and more deeply. Your skill level will reach a point where you will be able to claim your independence from within the group you work for and move out on your own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you grow older as an adult, it’s harder to find these natural inclinations. For years, we’ve already been influenced by the culture we live in, our peers, our family, the influencers we look up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You must dig for signs of such inclinations in your earliest years. Look for its traces in visceral reactions to something simple; a desire to repeat an activity that you never tired of; a subject that stimulated an unusual degree of curiosity; feelings of power attached to particular actions… You have nothing to create; you merely need to dig and refine what has been buried inside of you all along. If you reconnect with this core at any age, some element of that primitive attraction will spark back to life, indicating a path that can ultimately become your Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you find this inclination, practice journaling and reflecting on your feelings toward different types of work and ask yourself why you feel this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Become who you are by learning who you are.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pindar, Ancient Greek poet&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you allow yourself to learn who you really are by paying attention to that voice and force within you, then you can become what you were fated to become — an individual, a Master.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a two pathways you can take for finding your field. First, find a deep narrow niche in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”[once you’ve found a field you like] …look for side paths that particularly attract you… When it is possible, you make a move to this narrower field. You continue this process until you eventually hit upon a totally unoccupied niche, the narrower the better. In some ways, this niche corresponds to your uniqueness…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can combine two entirely different fields into one and create a new category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Once you have mastered your first field, you look for other subjects or skills that you can conquer, on your own time if necessary. You can now combine this added field of knowledge to the original one, perhaps creating a new field, or at least making novel connections between them. You continue this process as long as you wish… Ultimately you create a field that is uniquely your own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know you’re on the path of your Life’s Task, don’t let anything stand in the way — nothing is more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In dealing with your career and its inevitable change, you must think in the following way: You are not tied to a particular position; your loyalty is not to career or a company. You are committed to your Life’s Task, to giving it full expression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t let the field itself to evolve beneath you and leave you behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…it is up to you to foresee the changes going on right now in your profession. You must adapt your Life’s Task to these circumstances. You do not hold on to past ways of doing things. Because that will ensure you will fall behind and suffer for it. You are flexible and always looking to adapt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be lured to other paths that seem easier or more lucrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The road to mastery requires patience. You will have to keep your focus on five or ten years down the road, when you will reap the rewards of your efforts… In the end, the money and success that truly last come not to those who focus on such things as goals, but rather to those who focus on mastery and fulfilling their Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…direct yourself toward the small things you are good at. Do not dream or make grand plans for the future, but instead concentrate on becoming proficient at these simple and immediate skills. This will bring you confidence and become a base from which you can expand to other pursuits. Proceeding in this way, step by step, you will hit upon your Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-i-submit-to-reality-the-ideal-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;Phase I. Submit to Reality: The Ideal Apprenticeship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apprenticeship phase begins when you’ve identified the particular field you have a deep interest and inclination for. You may not have found exactly your Life’s Task, but you’re on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-best-kind-of-apprenticeships&quot;&gt;The Best Kind of Apprenticeships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the goal of an apprenticeship is not money, a good position, a title, or a diploma, but rather the transformation of your mind and character — the first transformation on the way to mastery. You enter a career as an outsider.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start an apprenticeship that offers the best opportunities for learning. Sometimes this means accepting the lowest position at a good company. It would be a mistake to seek out the best pay if it’s at a company that won’t mold you to be an expert in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must value learning above everything else.… opt for the situation that will give you the most opportunities to learn, particularly with hands-on work.… choose a place that has people and mentors who can inspire and teach you. A job with mediocre pay has the added benefit of training you to get by with less — a valuable life skill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentors who you can learn from are essential to your career and skill growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Practical knowledge… is what will pay you dividends for decades to come — far more than the paltry increase in pay you might receive at some seemingly lucrative position that offers fewer learning opportunities. This means that you move toward challenges that will toughen and improve you, where you will get the most objective feedback on your performance and progress. You do not choose apprenticeships that seem easy and comfortable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid of a challenging job with low pay. Your reward in an apprenticeship is not money — it is in skills and character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-you-do-when-you-have-an-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;What You Do When You Have an Apprenticeship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting an apprenticeship, a good attitude is an essential foundation for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You are naïve and full of misconceptions about this new world. Your head is full of dreams and fantasies about the future. Your knowledge of the world is subjective, based on emotions, insecurities, and limited experience. Slowly, you will ground yourself in reality, in the objective world represented by the knowledge and skills that make people successful in it. You will learn how to work with others and handle criticism. In the process you will transform yourself from someone who is impatient and scattered into someone who is disciplined and focused, with a mind that can handle complexity. In the end, you will master yourself and all of your weaknesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep a humble a mind and to not attempt to rise to the top. At some points, you may think you know everything and that you’re ready to go out on your own, but you will see there is a lot to learn before proceeding to the next phase of adding your own style and ideas to the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The greatest mistake you can make in the initial months of your apprenticeship is to imagine that you have to get attention, impress people, and prove yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“These thoughts will dominate your mind and close it off from the reality around you. Any positive attention you receive is deceptive; it is not based on your skills or anything real, and it will turn against you. Instead, you will want to acknowledge the reality and submit to it, muting your colors and keeping in the background as much as possible, remaining passive and giving yourself the space to observe. You will also want to drop any preconceptions you might have about this world you are entering. If you impress people in these first months, it should be because of the seriousness of your desire to learn, not because you are trying to rise to the top before you are ready.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to impress in any way other than through your hard work, determination, and desire to learn. You need to learn your new environment inside and out. How companies in the field work, even at the levels above you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the ability to observe any unfamiliar environment will become a critical lifelong skill. You will develop the habit of stilling your ego and looking outward instead of inward. You will see in any encounter what most people miss because they are thinking of themselves. You will cultivate a keen eye for human psychology, and strengthen your ability to focus… This will be a very important skill for the next, creative phase in life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By being able to critically observe all aspects of your environment, you will be able to make better decisions with your work by seeing the whole picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to accept that apprenticeships will require monotonous and tedious work. This is something you will have to push through and embrace. Even if you don’t think you have anything left to learn, you will learn the power of disciple — the ability to do what you know needs to be done even when your body and mind don’t want you to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discipline-and-the-resistance-practice&quot;&gt;Discipline and the Resistance Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”[The Resistance Practice means] you go in the opposite direction of all of your natural tendencies when it comes to practice. First, you resist the temptation to be nice to yourself. You become your own worst critic; you see your work as if through the eyes of others. You recognize your weaknesses, precisely the elements you are not good at.… Second, you resist the lure of easing up on your focus. You train yourself to concentrate in practice with double the intensity, as if it were the real thing times two. In devising your own routines, you become as creative as possible. You invent exercises that work upon your weaknesses. You give yourself arbitrary deadlines to meet certain standards, constantly pushing yourself past perceived limits. In this way you develop your own standards for excellence, generally higher than those of others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is a super power. If you can develop strong discipline, you can consistently do the work required to be on the path for mastery and success. Set high standards for yourself, even if your friends, peers, or even family think you’re crazy. They most likely won’t have the same levels of expectations for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mistakes and failures are precisely your means of education. They tell you about your own inadequacies. It is hard to find out such things from people, as they are often political with their praise and criticisms. Your failures also permit you to see the flaws of your ideas, which are only revealed in the execution of them. You learn what your audience really wants, the discrepancy between your ideas and how they affect the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one becomes a master with 100% perfect record. It is okay to fail because with patience and time, you will recover and grow even more skillful and stronger due to those learning experiences. Be the own judge of your quality — coworkers and even bosses will not say as much as they think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You want to learn as many skills as possible, following the direction that circumstances lead you to, but only if they are related to your deepest interests. Like a hacker, you value the process of self-discovery and making things that are of the highest quality. You avoid the trap of following one set career path. You are not sure where this will all lead, but you are taking full advantage of the openness of information, all of the knowledge about skills now at our disposal. You see what kind of work suits you and what you want to avoid at all cost. You move by trial and error.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning lots of different skills allows you to combine different skills later in life, and get you closer to discovering your Life’s Task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You are not wandering about because you are afraid of commitment, but because you are expanding your skill base and your possibilities. At a certain point, when you are ready to settle on something, ideas and opportunities will inevitably present themselves to you. When that happens, all of the skills you have accumulated will prove invaluable. You will be the Master at combining them in ways that are unique and suited to your individuality. You may settle on this one place or idea for several years, accumulating in the process even more skills, then move in a slightly different direction when the time is appropriate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching work like this will keep you from finding yourself locked in a boring career and instead provide opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The very desire to find shortcuts makes you eminently unsuited for any kind of mastery.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;absorb-the-masters-power-the-mentordynamic&quot;&gt;Absorb the Master’s Power: The Mentor Dynamic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the apprenticeship phase, it’s critical to find and work under a master as a mentee. With their experience, they can guide you on the right path and help you grow your skills far faster than you could alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best mentor-mentee relationships are with people you work with on a daily basis, such as your manager. If your direct manager isn’t a suitable mentee, then possibly another leader at your company you have the ability to interact with. If no one at your workplace is suitable, find a better company or the next best thing is finding a mentor online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To learn requires a sense of humility. We must admit that there are people out there who know our field much more deeply than we do. Their superiority is not a function of natural talent or privilege, but rather of time and experience. Their authority in the field is not based on politics or trickery. It is very real.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect masters for what they have accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Even if we have teachers in our lives, we tend not to pay full attention to their advice, often preferring to do things our own way. In fact, we come to believe that being critical of Masters or teachers is somehow a sign of our intelligence, and that being a submissive pupil is a sign of weakness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a huge mistake to think you know better than a master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As the relationship progresses you can make this absorption process more conscious and direct, questioning them about the principles underlying their way of doing things. If you are clever,… getting them to analyze their own creativity for you, and mining all kinds of rich ideas in the process. They are often grateful for the opportunity to reveal the inner workings of their power, particularly to someone they do not perceive as a threat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-people-as-they-are-the-social-intelligence&quot;&gt;See People As They Are: The Social Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat the work you do, no matter how small the job and responsibility is as art — as a demonstration of your craft. But don’t do it alone. When appropriate, bring other people in, be open to feedback, and create something together to make not just yourself win, but others with you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…your work is the single greatest means at your disposal for expressing your social intelligence. By being efficient and detail oriented in what you do, you demonstrate that you are thinking of the group at large and advancing its cause. By making what you write or present clear and easy to follow, you show your care for the audience or public at large. By involving other people in your projects and gracefully accepting their feedback, you reveal your comfort with the group dynamic. Work that is solid also protects you from the political conniving and malevolence of others — it is hard to argue with the results you produce. If you are experiencing the pressures of political maneuvering within the group, do not lose your head and become consumed with all of the pettiness. By remaining focused and speaking socially through your work, you will both continue to raise your skill level and stand out among all the others who make a lot of noise but produce nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your work speak for yourself while others around you try to get ahead by playing political games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also keep up a healthy appearance. Even if you don’t think it’s true, people are and will judge you based on your appearance. Use this to your advantage by crafting an appearance that portrays the character you want to be known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…turn this dynamic around by consciously molding these appearances, creating the image that suits you, and controlling people’s judgments. At times you will find it appropriate to stand back and create some mystery around you, heightening your presence. At other times you will want to be more direct and impose a more specific appearance. In general, you never settle on one image or give people the power to completely figure you out. You are always one step ahead of the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t go too far in trying to always persuade and figure out what the people around you are thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In dealing with fools you must adopt the following philosophy: they are simply a part of life, like rocks or furniture. All of us have foolish sides. Moments in which we lose our heads and think more of our ego or short-term goals. It is human nature. Seeing this foolishness within you, you can then accept it in others. This will allow you to smile at their antics, to tolerate their presence as you would a silly child. And to avoid the madness of trying to change them. It is all part of the human comedy, and it is nothing to get upset about or lose sleep over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius’s stoic philosophy also teaches this mindset in dealing with other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-ii-awaken-the-dimensional-mind-the-creative-active&quot;&gt;Phase II. Awaken the Dimensional Mind: The Creative-Active&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Dimensional Mind has two essential requirements: one, a high level of knowledge about a field or subject; and two, the openness and flexibility to use this knowledge in new and original ways.… Once the mind is freed from having to learn these basics, it can focus on higher, more creative matters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dimensional Mind is a concept that combines knowledge and skepticism — having deep knowledge about a particular subject, but not so set in stone in order to be open to new ideas and perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-how-to-obtain-a-dimensional-mind&quot;&gt;Here’s How to Obtain a Dimensional Mind:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…first, choosing the proper Creative Task, the kind of activity that will maximize our skills and knowledge; second, loosening and opening up the mind through certain Creative Strategies; and third, creating the optimal mental conditions for a Breakthrough or Insight. Finally, throughout the process we must also be aware of the Emotional Pitfalls — complacency, boredom, grandiosity, and the like — that continually threaten to derail or block our progress. If we can move through the steps while avoiding these traps, we cannot fail to unleash powerful creative forces from within.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat all your work like art. Hone your craft. Do not think about false goals like money or fame, but focus on creating the best thing you’re capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you go at your work with half a heart, it will show in the lackluster results and in the laggard way in which you reach the end. If you are doing something primarily for money and without a real emotional commitment, it will translate into something that lacks a soul and that has no connection to you. You may not see this, but you can be sure that the public will feel it and that they will receive your work in the same lackluster spirit it was created in. If you are excited and obsessive in the hunt, it will show in the details. If your work comes from a place deep within, its authenticity will be communicated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very difficult to even think about “going down” in your level of lifestyle, but to achieve mastery, you can’t be afraid of that happening. You most likely will have to make some sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must let go of your need for comfort and security. Creative endeavors are by their nature uncertain. You may know your task, but you are never exactly sure where your efforts will lead. If you need everything in your life to be simple and safe, this open-ended nature of the task will fill you with anxiety. If you are worried about what others might think and about how your position in the group might be jeopardized, then you will never really create anything.… your ideas will grow stale and flat. If you are worried about failure or going through a period of mental and financial instability,… your worries will be reflected in the results. Think of yourself as an explorer. You cannot find anything new if you are unwilling to leave the shore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the challenging path of mastery worth it? Because we don’t get anywhere near the same level of satisfaction from exercising our creativity as anything else. It defines who we are. It makes an impact on our community; to the human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Engaged in the creative process we feel more alive than ever, because we are making something and not merely consuming, Masters of the small reality we create. In doing this work, we are in fact creating ourselves. Although it involves much pain, the pleasure that comes from the overall process of creativity is of an intensity that makes us want to repeat it. That is why creative people return again and again to such endeavors, despite all of the anxiety and doubt they stir up. It is nature’s way of rewarding us for the effort; if we had no such rewards, people would not engage in such activity, and mankind would suffer irreparably from this loss. This pleasure will be your reward as well, to whatever degree you pursue the process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With discipline, good work, and time, your skills will grow towards Mastery. And if time is a part of the process, then the more time you have, the more your skills will grow. Time, therefore is an ally. Have patience. By trying to rush to the next level quickly, you’re removing time from the equation and therefore decreasing your skill output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must come to embrace slowness as a virtue in itself. When it comes to creative endeavors, time is always relative. Whether your project takes months or years to complete, you will always experience a sense of impatience and a desire to get to the end. The single greatest action you can take for acquiring creative power is to reverse this natural impatience. You take pleasure in the laborious research process; you enjoy the slow cooking of the idea, the organic growth that naturally takes shape over time. You do not unnaturally draw out the process, which will create its own problems (we all need deadlines), but the longer you can allow the project to absorb your mental energies, the richer it will become. Imagine yourself years in the future looking back at the work you have done. From that future vantage point, the extra months and years you devoted to the process will not seem painful or laborious at all. It is an illusion of the present that will vanish. Time is your greatest ally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fuse-the-intuitive-with-the-rational-mastery&quot;&gt;Fuse the Intuitive With the Rational: Mastery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the path to Mastery, it’s important to lose sight of your goal. Mindset is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must also maintain a sense of destiny, and feel continuously connected to it. You are unique, and there is a purpose to your uniqueness. You must see every setback, failure, or hardship as a trial along the way, as seeds that are being planted for further cultivation, if you know how to grow them. No moment is wasted if you pay attention and learn the lessons contained in every experience. By constantly applying yourself to the subject that suits your inclinations and attacking it from many different angles, you are simply enriching the ground for these seeds to take root. You may not see this process in the present, but it is happening. Never losing your connection to your Life’s Task, you will unconsciously hit upon the right choices in your life. Over time, mastery will come to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerful tool as you face increasing challenges is learning how to manage stress and anxiety — and even better, learn how to use it to your advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We must learn how to quiet the anxiety we feel whenever we are confronted with anything that seems complex or chaotic. In our journey from apprenticeship to mastery we must patiently learn the various parts and skills that are required, never looking too far ahead. In moments of perceived crisis, we must develop the habit of maintaining our cool and never overreacting. If the situation is complex and others are reaching for simple black-and-white answers, or for the usual conventional responses, we must make a point of resisting such a temptation. We maintain our Negative Capability and a degree of detachment. What we are doing is gaining a tolerance and even a taste for chaotic moments, training ourselves to entertain several possibilities or solutions. We are learning to manage our anxiety, a key skill in these chaotic times.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path to mastery is a long road. Temptations to abandon your path will come from all angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The problem is that we humans are deep conformists. Those qualities that separate us are often ridiculed by others, or criticized by teachers.… anything that is peculiar to our makeup is precisely what we must pay the deepest attention to and lean on in our rise to mastery. Mastery is like swimming — it is too difficult to move forward when we are creating our own resistance or swimming against the current. Know your strengths and move with them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing in mastery is to stay true to who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Your false self is the accumulation of all the voices you have internalized from other people — parents and friends who want you to conform to their ideas of what you should be like and what you should do, as well as societal pressures to adhere to certain values that can easily seduce you. It also includes the voice of your own ego, which constantly tries to protect you from unflattering truths.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Greene is my one my favorite writers because the way he likes to weave historical stories into practical advice. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt;, Greene helps people find their purpose in life, which he thinks is better called your Life’s Task. Although long and a little disorganized, Mastery was a fun read that revealed a desire for creativity and craft within me for my work. I still think I’m young in my career (apprenticeship phase) and Mastery provided some practical advice on how to make best use of my position and time to move closer to mastery. I wanted a bit more detail with the practical advice, but I still found it quite useful. I rate Mastery an 8/10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Mastery by Robert Greene is a practical read on helping people find and pursue their Life’s Task (purpose).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mastery-book-summary.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mastery-book-summary.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My Google Sheets Budget Template - Simple &amp;amp; Beautiful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Google Sheets Budget Template - Simple &amp; Beautiful" /><published>2019-02-01T15:51:34-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T15:51:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template">&lt;p&gt;I received an inheritance of $30k. &lt;strong&gt;One year later, I had blown it all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the money to move out, get a new car, eat out constantly — all while telling myself I’m going to be making $10k a month before I know it as freelance marketer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every month I knew I was spending more than I was making, but I was too scared to look at my bank account or my credit card statement. *Just click pay*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t until I could only afford one more month’s rent that I accepted I needed a full-time job and a budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been five years since then and I’ve learned a few tricks along the way. The most important thing is to &lt;strong&gt;understand the difference between a good budget system and a bad one.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A bad budget system only shows you where your money is going. A good budget system will create a change in your behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-my-google-sheets-budget-template-can-improve-your-spending-habits&quot;&gt;How My Google Sheets Budget Template Can Improve Your Spending Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it forces you to enter your expenses &lt;strong&gt;manually&lt;/strong&gt;. Although this seems crazy with today’s tools that can link to your accounts and do this automatically, &lt;strong&gt;doing it manually is crucial to improving spending habits.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Manually recording your expenses every week will force you to review every transaction, to feel the pain of every dollar spent, and make you think “was that really necessary?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason to manually record expenses is you can fine-tune the expense category for each transaction, or even split a transaction into two categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives you way more options for using and tailoring categories exactly to your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here’s one of my favorite charts where you can see how you’ve been spending vs your budget by each category over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Graphs for each budget category.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Graphs for each budget category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;view-and-start-using-my-google-sheets-budgettemplate&quot;&gt;View and Start Using My Google Sheets Budget Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the link below and click ‘make a copy’ to start using it in your Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VRczmKEyg96fFixxz4LtR-1Yh2_V4xILIGVrpRqN38w/copy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Download: My Google Sheets Budget Template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend reading on to learn how to set the budget template up for your finances and learn how to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the initial set up and ongoing expense recording, &lt;strong&gt;everything is automated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instructions-how-to-use-the-budget-template&quot;&gt;Instructions: How to Use The Budget Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I included easy-to-follow prompts to make it simple and quick to get set up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--middle gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/budget1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Prompts make it super easy to use this Google Sheets template.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Prompts make it super easy to use this Google Sheets template.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can learn how to use the template in this video tutorial, or by reading the below guide if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FAEg7BBGOuo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-enter-your-income&quot;&gt;I. Enter your income&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the top left box on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab, enter your income. Follow the orange colored cells as cues for which part to fill out. If you don’t have a &lt;strong&gt;401k&lt;/strong&gt; or a &lt;strong&gt;Recurring Income #2&lt;/strong&gt; (additional income), you can leave those sections blank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your income data in the Income box on the Dashbord tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your income data in the Income box on the Dashbord tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any income entered here will be added to your available budget. If you do receive any kind of extra income, you may either be putting it all in savings, part of it in savings, or you need all of it for your expenses. Unless you’re comfortable with Google Sheets and spreadsheet formulas, this budget template is only made for two sources of income. If you have more than one additional income source, you can sum them and enter the total as one number in the &lt;strong&gt;Recurring Income #2&lt;/strong&gt; cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need all or a portion of that extra income, you need to add it to the &lt;strong&gt;Recurring Income #2&lt;/strong&gt; cell. If you save all of it, you can still add it if you wish (and offset it later by increasing how much of your income is sent to savings) or you can omit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this section is completed, you’ll get your &lt;strong&gt;Net Total Income&lt;/strong&gt;, which is how much net income you have left over to spend, put in savings etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ii-enter-monthly-recurring-expenses&quot;&gt;II. Enter Monthly Recurring Expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below the &lt;strong&gt;Income&lt;/strong&gt; box is the &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Recurring&lt;/strong&gt; box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your monthly recurring expenses on the Dashbord tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your monthly recurring expenses on the Dashbord tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first item is &lt;strong&gt;Savings&lt;/strong&gt; to help you prioritize setting money aside for savings to help you “pay yourself first”, a very effecitve wealth building strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The goal [of pay yourself first] is to make sure that enough income is first saved or invested before monthly expenses or discretionary purchases are made.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/payyourselffirst.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Investopedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you can start adding recurring monthly expenses. These are monthly expenditures that are typically the same amount every month. Examples include rent and utilities, car payment and insurance, phone bills, gym memberships, Netflix/Spotify, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this, you’ll be left with your &lt;strong&gt;Net Spendable Income&lt;/strong&gt;, which tells you how much you have left for discretionary spending for food, shopping, going out, and other expenses. But first, there’s one more step before we get to creating our actual budget: annual expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iii-enter-annual-expenses&quot;&gt;III. Enter Annual Expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy behind including annual expenses is to set aside a monthly amount of money to prepare for when these big expenses come up. Start by adding in things you pay once a year for in the &lt;strong&gt;Annual Recurring&lt;/strong&gt; box. Some examples are car registration, vacations, gifts, car maintenance, credit card annualy fees, Amazon Prime, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your annually recurring expenses on the Dashbord tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your annually recurring expenses on the Dashbord tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you entered in all the annual expenses you can think of, the budget template will divide the total into a monthly amount as a line item back in the &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Recurring&lt;/strong&gt; box. Now you have your final &lt;strong&gt;Net Spendable Income&lt;/strong&gt; amount you can use to start budgeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-create-your-budget&quot;&gt;IV. Create Your Budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you know how much money you can comfortably spend after savings, monthly recurring expenses, and planning for future annual expenses, you can create your budget. In the &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box, enter categories of expenses and an allotted amount. Some examples include eating out, groceries, going out, shopping, coffee, alcohol, personal care, gas, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter the spending categories you want to track and their budget on the Dashbord tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter the spending categories you want to track and their budget on the Dashbord tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to some clever conditional formatting in Google Sheets, the budget template will sum your &lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; monthly expenses. If the &lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; is green, your expenses are under your &lt;strong&gt;Net Spendable Income&lt;/strong&gt;. It will be red if it’s over and you will need to readjust your &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Budget&lt;/strong&gt; or consider eliminating or reducing some of your monthly or annual recurring expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: Before we can get into the &lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spent vs Budget&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Expenses Last 7 Months&lt;/strong&gt; boxes, we need to run through the other tabs in the Google Sheet budget template first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-recording-expenses&quot;&gt;V. Recording Expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the presumably biggest downsides of a doing your personal budget in Google Sheets is that you have to enter your expenses in manually, but this is a blessing in disguise. Entering your expenses manually will have a big psychological effect on you to spend less. It forces you to “feel the pain” of every dollar you spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; tab you’ll enter each of your expenses - one row per one expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll see some instructions in red at the top for more information. Across the blue row heading, the budget template auto populates your &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; categories from the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab. When you enter an expense, start with the date in &lt;strong&gt;Column A&lt;/strong&gt;, the name of the place you spend the money in &lt;strong&gt;Column B&lt;/strong&gt;, and then tab over to the column with the expense category that best matches how this expense should be categorized. If it’s an annual expense, it’s the same exact process - just make sure you’re in the right annual expense column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget17.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Expenses tab with sample data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Expenses tab with sample data&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: It’s important you don’t change the order of your items in the &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; box on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab because the column you entered the expense under isn’t locked to the expense category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are the expense categories in different columns instead of writing in/choosing the expense category in a single category column? For two reasons. One, it’s much faster to just ‘tab’ over to the right expense category column than writing it in or switching from keyboard to mouse to choose the right category from a dropdown. Second, it allows for less process-heavy formulas making the spreadsheet more smooth to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget16.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Example of how fast you can enter expenses by using the tab and enter keys&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of how fast you can enter expenses by using the tab and enter keys&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: When choosing the date, it doesn’t matter whether you choose the transaction date or the posted date (if pulling from a credit card), but you should stick to one or the other. I prefer posted date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vi-tallying-up-assets-and-liabilities-in-the-balance-sheet&quot;&gt;VI. Tallying Up Assets and Liabilities in the Balance Sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now onto the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tab of the budget template. This is where you will add up all the money you have and owe in your accounts. This will ultimately tell you if your wealth/net worth is increasing or decreasing. Make sure you’ve filled out the preliminary &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; steps first (see points 1-4 above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: Because this is counting the actual numbers in your account, you don’t necessarily have to record every expense. Sometimes there are expenses that don’t quite make sense to include that could throw off measuring your spending. But don’t worry, as long as the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; is accurate, measuring your cash balance and net worth over time will still be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, name the accounts in &lt;strong&gt;Column A&lt;/strong&gt; (mostly the savings accounts and assets). Examples of savings accounts can include primary, emergency fund, and vacation fund. Assets can be your car, credit card miles, 401k, IRA, stocks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Choose the accounts you want to include as assets on the Balance Sheet tab and give them a nickname&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Choose the accounts you want to include as assets on the Balance Sheet tab and give them a nickname&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: Unless your comfortable with Google Sheets formulas, this spreadsheet doesn’t support changing the purpose of the accounts that are listed there. It’s okay to not use any of them, but not okay to add or change the purpose of an account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve named your accounts, follow the below steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter your starting date in cell &lt;strong&gt;B1&lt;/strong&gt;. Dates are entered in the format of &lt;strong&gt;1/1/2018&lt;/strong&gt; (the formatting will display the month’s name and year). In cell &lt;strong&gt;B1&lt;/strong&gt;, enter the date of the oldest month you want to start your budget. In most cases, you’ll enter the 1st of the current month or the 1st of last month. You can start further back if you wish, but it will take extra work to calculate historical balances of your accounts. Then in cell &lt;strong&gt;C1&lt;/strong&gt;, enter the 1st of the following month. Then continue adding the 1st of every subsequent month until you reach the end of &lt;strong&gt;row 1&lt;/strong&gt;. Once completed, the orange instructions in cell &lt;strong&gt;A1&lt;/strong&gt; should disappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget11.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your starting date on the Balance Sheet tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your starting date on the Balance Sheet tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now you’ll have a header row in &lt;strong&gt;row 1&lt;/strong&gt; with the month and year. The numbers you will fill out in the column beneath a month must be the balances at the end of that month. So forget that you used the first of the month in the heading - the reason for that was just to get the month and year to display and to make some formulas work. Just remember, the numbers under a month’s column in the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; represent where those accounts stand at the end of that month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: If you’re starting your budget this month, you don’t need to fill out the numbers in the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; yet. It’s easiest to do this soon after the month ends, either one the 1st of the following month or at least within a few days of it ending. Then all you need to do is pull up your online banking and fill out the balances for all your accounts, credit cards, loans, retirement accounts, etc. &lt;strong&gt;Remember, the numbers in these columns represent how you stand at the end of the month&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any row that has a &lt;strong&gt;-&lt;/strong&gt; in the cell means these numbers are auto calculated with Google Sheets formulas. Grey shaded cells are intentionally left blank due to the nature of what it’s calculating (for example you need 3 months of data before it can calculate a 3 month rolling average). Here’s what the &lt;strong&gt;Assets &amp;amp; Income&lt;/strong&gt; section will look like once you have some data in there:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Assets &amp;amp; Income section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Assets &amp;amp; Income section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;Rent Due&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;row 30&lt;/strong&gt;, I always set to $0. Rent should be paid on the 1st and I don’t like to include it as money owed. If I’m filling out the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; for a month where rent hasn’t yet been deducted from my checking account, I’ll subtract it from my current checking balance for a more accurate representation of my month’s finances. I do the same thing for credit card payments when it applies - pay my credit card and if it hasn’t been reflected in my credit card or checking balance, I manually subtract the amount from my credit card balance and the amount I paid from my checking account. Here’s what the &lt;strong&gt;Liabilities&lt;/strong&gt; section looks like with sample date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Liabilities secion with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Liabilities secion with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The categories under &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; starting in &lt;strong&gt;row 36&lt;/strong&gt; are auto populated from the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab. The sums of each category are then auto calculated from the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; tab so you don’t need to do anything here. The same is true for &lt;strong&gt;Annual Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; starting at &lt;strong&gt;row 50&lt;/strong&gt;. If you spend in an annual expense category, it won’t count towards your monthly budget and instead will pull from the future “pool” of money set aside for annual expenses you decllare in the &lt;strong&gt;Annual Reccuring&lt;/strong&gt; box on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Monthly and Annual Expenses secions with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Monthly and Annual Expenses secions with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last section is the &lt;strong&gt;Totals&lt;/strong&gt; section that brings everything together to calculate your net checking balance (money in checking minus current credit card balances) and your net worth. In &lt;strong&gt;row 72&lt;/strong&gt; you can leave notes for yourself if something unusual occurred in a given month. The word “Notes” will auto populate in each month, but to leave a note, right-click the cell and select “Insert note.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget15.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Totals section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Totals section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all you do the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; at the end of each month. As you use this Google Sheets budget template each month, more data on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab will start to populate and be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vii-net-worth-summary&quot;&gt;VII. Net Worth Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab, the &lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt; box will show an overview of the most recent balances you entered on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tab compared to the previous completed month. Then it also compares your &lt;strong&gt;Latest&lt;/strong&gt; with the previous &lt;strong&gt;3 Month Average&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes it easy to see if your money is increasing or decreasing. You’ll need at least 4 months of completed data for the &lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt; box to completely work. Don’t worry or change any of the formulas here if it throws an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget7.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Summary box on the Dashbord tab shows whether your net worth is growing or shrinking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Summary box on the Dashbord tab shows whether your net worth is growing or shrinking&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;viii-spent-vs-budget&quot;&gt;VIII. Spent vs Budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further down the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab, you’ll see the &lt;strong&gt;Spent vs Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box. This is a graph that compares your spending in each category to the budget you set for that category in the &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box. Use the dropdown selector in cell &lt;strong&gt;P30&lt;/strong&gt; to change the category or choose ‘Total.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget8.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Spent vs Budget box on the Dashbord tab visualizes your spending per category in a graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Spent vs Budget box on the Dashbord tab visualizes your spending per category in a graph&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: This graph shows the previous seven months of data so it won’t be fully complete until you have at least seven months of complete data. And it won’t show any data at all until you have data from at least one previous month in your &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tabs (It doesn’t show current month). Again, don’t change any formulas or the chart as it will still work fine if you don’t have all seven months yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ix-expenses-last-seven-months&quot;&gt;IX. Expenses Last Seven Months&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below the &lt;strong&gt;Spent vs Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box is the same data but in a table format in the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses Last 7 Months&lt;/strong&gt; box. This is another way to compare your spending vs budget by category. Amounts will be red where you overspent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/budget9.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Expenses Last 7 Months box on the Dashbord tab shows a table of your spending vs budget per each category&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Expenses Last 7 Months box on the Dashbord tab shows a table of your spending vs budget per each category&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-budgeting-tips&quot;&gt;Bonus Budgeting Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A budget is only good if you update it consistently, keep it accurate, and spend time analyzing your spending. That’s why I made it a point to make this budget template in Google Sheets look nice, be easy to use, and be rewarding to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes that’s still not enough. &lt;strong&gt;There’s definitely been times where I don’t do it for a few weeks at a time and the more you wait, the more work you’ll have to do, and the more you won’t look forward to doing it&lt;/strong&gt;. I‘ve made it a habit to log my expenses every Sunday vs once every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe a budget will help you get control of your spending, read this guide on how to stick to new habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tip is to use a credit card for all transactions when possible. Using a credit card makes it much easier to keep track of your spending and at the same time protects your bank account from fraud, builds your credit, and you can earn points and rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think of the spreadsheet. If you found some places where I messed up or have ideas for new functionality, let me know on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/regpaq&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/i-made-317-per-month-from-two-amazon-niche-sites-last-year-and-heres-how-i-did-it&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;I Made $317 / Mo. From Two Amazon Niche Sites Last Year&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;And here’s how I did it.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/niche-site-amazon-affiliate.png&quot; alt=&quot;niche site amazon affiliate&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">I received an inheritance of $30k. One year later, I had blown it all.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2018 Year Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018-year-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2018 Year Review" /><published>2019-01-25T09:46:11-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-25T09:46:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018-year-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018-year-review">&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-100kyr-by30&quot;&gt;Make $100k/yr by 30&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an arbitrary “goal,” but nonetheless one I wrote down at the beginning of the year. In fact it’s something I always had as a goal in the back of mind since I started working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some hard work and definitely some luck mixed in, I was able to make it. What’s funny is earlier in the year, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/marketing/comments/6kg6kv/who_here_makes_100k/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;asked the r/marketing subreddit who made $100k&lt;/a&gt; and what was their path and advice. It ended up getting way more comments than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comments were pretty inspiring and kind of pointed out I was a little underpaid at where I was at the time. So I used that to make some moves and did two things: 1) turned a lucrative job offer into a raise and 2) got a high paying freelancing client doing paid Facebook Ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was awesome to go back to the community at r/marketing and do an update post and an ask me anything: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/marketing/comments/9qsktw/i_made_130k_with_year_as_a_b2b_marketer_in_saas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“I made $130k this year as a B2B Marketer in SaaS. AMA”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-1-book-amonth&quot;&gt;Read 1 Book a Month&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t quite make this one. I read 7 books and listened to 8 on Audible. I decided I’m not the biggest fan of audiobooks — while entertaining during drives, at the gym, or doing whatever, I just don’t retain as much information. Since I wanted to read a book a month to learn practical knowledge, audiobooks therefore just can’t count towards this goal. So from now on, Audiobooks will be reserved for just fun books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kindle (7): 48 Laws of Power, Meditations, Mastery, Man’s Search for Meaning, The Boron Letters, Atomic Habits, Pre-Suasion,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audible (8): Rome’s Last Citizen (2x), Conspiracy, The Obstacle is The Way (2x), Washington: A Life, Thomas Jefferson: The Art of Power, Ego Is The Enemy, First Break All The Rules, and Way of the Wolf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The essential book to help you find your purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mastery-book-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;mastery book summary&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;start-trackinghabits&quot;&gt;Start Tracking Habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the year off strong using a pen and planner method, but after a couple months I started to miss a few days tracking, which eventually led me to stop completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of 2018, I started using a &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;habit tracking app called Done&lt;/a&gt;, which was a huge improvement over pen and paper. Reading &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; also helped me tremendously to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;stick with my new habits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I have to mark this goal as a fail, but I’ve made big improvements here that I don’t feel bad about it. I’m pretty confident I’ll stick to my habits and tracking them everyday in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done-app-review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;doing-habits&quot;&gt;Doing Habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/meditate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/journal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/floss.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/gym.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;Habit progress recorded in Done.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only habit I kept up from the beginning of the year was going to the gym. My goal at first was to go 3x a week and then it went to 4x. Due to some injuries, illness, and a vacation to Europe, I didn’t quite meet my goal. I averaged 2.85x per week. Not bad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journaling was tough. I was fired up in the beginning of the year, but then I couldn’t keep it up. Again thanks to Atomic Habits, I was able to find a way to integrate journaling into my routine that stuck (December I went to Europe and got sick hence the lower number).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditating was something I first tried in 2018. I liked it for a while, but began to feel it wasn’t really doing much for me practically. I picked it back up again, but still have some doubt about how much it helps me in my day-to-day thoughts and feelings. I’m going to test switching from Headspace to Sam Harris’s Waking Up app and see if I can get more value from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hardly ever flossed in my life, but after being told how disgusting I was every night by my girlfriend, I decided to give it a go. Surprisingly, it wasn’t that hard to keep up after I got used to doing it. It was also great to hear a dentist tell me that I’ve been doing a good job flossing — a life first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-things-thathappened&quot;&gt;Other Things That Happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moved-into-a-new-apartment&quot;&gt;Moved Into a New Apartment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Deanna (my girlfriend) and I moved out of our studios and into a one bedroom apartment together. We had to renew our lease in 2018 or leave the building and we decided to stay, but upgrade to a better unit with an awesome and balcony and view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/apartment.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facebook-ads-for-musclepharm&quot;&gt;Facebook Ads for MusclePharm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a six month freelance project for my most high-profile company yet—&lt;a href=&quot;https://musclepharm.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MusclePharm&lt;/a&gt;. I learned a lot doing paid Facebook ads at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ServiceTitan&lt;/a&gt; (the company I worked for at the time) after spending over $1.5 million in FB ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from this project. For one, I don’t think I’ll freelance again while at a full-time job. While the extra income is very nice, the opportunity cost is very high — most notably less free time and a hit to my performance at my main job. The latter is important because I was in a great position at ST and I could have done better during my time there. I believe freelancing was one of the major factors of my decrease in performance there, which led to me not going as high and far as I could have gone there — earning me more money long term than the freelance project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;turned-30&quot;&gt;Turned 30&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hit the big 3–0 last year. Deanna took me out to a delicious steak dinner, and other than that I didn’t really celebrate too much. She did get me some amazing gifts though — a new Louis Vuitton wallet and some nice Clark Dessert Boots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bought-a-newcar&quot;&gt;Bought a New Car&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love cars. Over the years I’ve had two Honda S2000s, a super clean ’96 BMW E36 328is coupe in manual, and an ’09 BMW e92 328i coupe. Then the unthinkable happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got rear ended hard and the ’09 Bimmer was totaled. To make it worse, it was right after I was laid off so I didn’t want to spend a lot of money while my income was uncertain. That’s how I ended up driving a VW Passat for two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in 2018 I finally got myself a new-to-me car: a ’14 BMW F32 435i coupe in manual with 25k miles. I’ve modded the car a lot so far (with more to come). Finally, I have a car I love getting into and driving again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/435.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;went-toseattle&quot;&gt;Went to Seattle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a quick vacation in Seattle, the first time I’ve ever been there. It’s the most beautiful city I’ve ever visited in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/seattle.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-experience-managing-a-directreport&quot;&gt;First Experience Managing a Direct Report&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my career, a big highlight in 2018 was beginning my management experience after being given the responsibility to manage someone. Although it was only for 9 months or so, it was a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sole contributor, your core focus is to do your job and help the company achieve goals. As a team contributor and manager, it’s still your job to help achieve company goals, but it’s also a big part to help another person achieve &lt;strong&gt;their&lt;/strong&gt; goals. And in many ways, that’s more rewarding. I’m excited for more opportunities to grow in a leadership role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;servicetitan-to-chilipiper&quot;&gt;ServiceTitan to Chili Piper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest change in 2018 was my job change from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ServiceTitan&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chilipiper.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chili Piper&lt;/a&gt;. I spent 2.5 years at ServiceTitan and have grown tremendously during that time. During my time there, the company went through two major rounds of funding, a valuation from $300 million to $1.6 billion right after I left, and from 115 employees to nearly 600.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the company grew and our marketing department ballooned in size, the skills asked of each team member in our team changed narrowed dramatically. When I joined, the marketing team was 6 people and when I left it was close to 30. In the beginning, we were asked to wear a lot of hats — be really good at and do many different things. As the team grew, the company was able to afford to place specialists in more siloed roles. This didn’t really fit my skill set and how I wanted to progress in my career, so the company and I agreed to part ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now thrilled to join Chili Piper, a small start up with around a dozen people who make a suite of tools for marketing and sales people — a demographic I know well since I’m a marketer myself who works closely with sales. This is a welcomed change, because having empathy for your buyers is a huge advantage to success as a marketer and job fulfillment — something I struggled with at ServiceTitan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;went-to-paris-and-amsterdam&quot;&gt;Went to Paris and Amsterdam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out I was going to Paris two weeks before my departure date. I joined Chili Piper in November during a contest they were running where if we break the most revenue generated in a single month, our founders were taking all of us to Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw the number we were at and the one we needed to hit, and I actually didn’t expect us to make it. But we have some absolute monsters on our team and they hit the number. Next thing I knew, I was going to the US Passport Agency in downtown LA one week before departure to rush order a new passport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/paris.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been to Paris, and it instantly became my favorite city in Europe. The architecture was beautiful and the food everywhere I went was delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I extended my Paris trip to visit my friend in Amsterdam. I’ve been once before so long ago I don’t even remember anything — it felt like I was visiting for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/amsterdam.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amsterdam was also a beautiful place. While it felt much smaller than Paris and it was definitely a touristy place, I still really enjoyed this unique city and my time there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-a-yearlyreview&quot;&gt;Why Do a Yearly Review?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this yearly review more as a personal exercise of reflection and gratitude. If I don’t take the time to reflect on what I’ve done and memories created, it becomes easy for me to forget and think time is flying by. Before this reflection, I would have said I didn’t do much in 2018 and maybe even ask myself “what am I doing with my life?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the reflection, it’s much more clear to see what I’ve done, experiences had, and memories created. It makes me think, “Hey my life isn’t that boring after all,” a mindset easy to give in to with social media. Finally, it’s an exercise in gratitude in appreciating the people in your life, the things in your life, and even the very flow of time itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Goals:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2018-year-review.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2018-year-review.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Break Bad Habits for Good</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-break-bad-habits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Break Bad Habits for Good" /><published>2019-01-24T15:45:09-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-24T15:45:09-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-break-bad-habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-break-bad-habits">&lt;p&gt;Stopping a bad habit is usually much more difficult than starting a new habit, especially if it’s a bad habit you’ve had for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason bad habits get started in the first place is throughout our day we experience a wide range of feelings and sensations, which can unconsciously trigger an action to fulfill or solve such feeling—all without a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the best action is found to deal with that feeling, it becomes ingrained in us and we tend come back to it whenever we experience that feeling again. Typically these solutions are short term solutions that can provide instant gratification, but can harm us in the long run— physically and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the following examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smoking cigarettes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long video game sessions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alcoholic drinks after each work night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Picking up and checking your phone constantly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Browsing Instagram constantly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying a coffee and donut every morning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They provide instant gratification to solve some kind of feeling (the trigger). Typically, solutions that provide instant gratification have a long term consequences. But because that instant gratification is so fulfilling and rewarding, it makes it extremely difficult to give up that instant gratification and remove it from your routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your current habits are not necessarily the best way to solve the problem you face, they are just the methods you learned to use. Once you associate a solution with the problem you need to solve, you keep coming back to it — an explanation for why habits are hard to break.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are six tips from &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; that helped me be break my worse habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-write-down-the-bad-habits-you-want-to-quit-andwhy&quot;&gt;1. Write Down the Bad Habits You Want to Quit and Why&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help make your promise to yourself more concrete, almost like a contract between your conscious and unconscious self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as important, write down why you want to stop each one. Usually this turns into crafting a new desired identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: I don’t want to eat a donut for breakfast every morning. Why? Because I don’t want a sugar rush in the morning with a crash in the afternoon. I don’t want to eat all those calories and it will help me lose some weight. New identity: I live a healthy lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ultimate form of intrinsic motivation is when a habit becomes part of your identity. You might start a habit because of motivation, but the only reason you’ll stick with one is that it becomes part of your identity. True behavior change is identity change.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this seems like you’re just playing a trick on yourself at first, once it becomes ingrained in you, it’s a powerful resistance to temptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-remove-the-cues-that-trigger-your-badhabits&quot;&gt;2. Remove the Cues That Trigger Your Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may be difficult to pin down exactly what causes you to suddenly desire your bad habit, once you’re able to stop the cue (or limit it as much as possible), you’re much more likely to not desire and therefore do your bad habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you have a desire to do the bad habit in question, think about why you want to do it. Did something you see caused it? Something you felt? Something in your environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you’re constantly picking up and checking your phone, maybe it was a notification that caused it? Once you’ve identified the cue, you can remove it as best you can. In this case, you can turn on do not disturb mode and stop the notifications from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-increase-friction-between-you-and-badhabits&quot;&gt;3. Increase Friction Between You and Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For extremely ingrained habits, sometimes removing the cue is not enough so you can go a step further by adding friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only can you turn off notifications, you can also put your phone in another room out of reach. Then if you felt the urge to pick it up, you’d have to get up from where you are and go get it, all the while remembering that you put it in that room for a purpose — a promise you made to yourself that you don’t want to break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples: throw out the alcohol you have in your home to stop drinking at home after work. Store your video game consoles in the closet so you’d have to take it out each time and set it up just to play. Delete Instagram from your phone so every time you want to check it you have to download the app again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-replace-a-bad-habit-with-a-goodhabit&quot;&gt;4. Replace a Bad Habit with a Good Habit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believing the why, removing the cue, and increasing friction is likely to help you stop most of your habits. But there could still be unfulfilled feelings that leave you feeling empty or deprived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the case, you may be using too much willpower to stop your bad habits—and that can only last so long before you give in. Perhaps it’s best to find a different and better solution to solve that feeling, rather than trying to ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, replace the donut in the morning with a fruit smoothie. Replace the drink after work with a decaf latte. Replace the video games with &lt;a href=&quot;/booknotes&quot;&gt;a great book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-record-your-progress-in-a-habittracker&quot;&gt;5. Record Your Progress in a Habit Tracker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing your progress and how far you’ve come can also be a great long term source of motivation. With a good system for tracking your habits, you’ll be able to see the number of days (or weeks) in a row you refrained from a bad habit. As that number increases, you’ll want to break it less and less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can track habits using pen and paper, a Google Sheet, or an app. After trying a few of these methods, I settled on an app being the easiest to use and because it was the easiest and fastest way to track habits, it was the system I could actually stick to using every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app I use is called Done. &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;Check out my review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done-app-review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-reward-yourself-for-resisting-your-badhabits&quot;&gt;6. Reward Yourself for Resisting Your Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, give yourself a reward for refraining from a bad habit. If you don’t have a donut in the morning for a week, treat yourself to a nice breakfast on Sunday mornings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t drink at home after work for a week, reward yourself with a drink out on Saturday night. If you don’t play video games for a week, reward yourself with a long session just on Sundays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using these strategies, I was able to completely break, or significantly reduce, some bad habits of mine, and even replace some of them with positive habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s your best to tip to break a bad habit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Stopping a bad habit is usually much more difficult than starting a new habit, especially if it’s a bad habit you’ve had for a long time.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>