<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/all.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-15T12:30:29-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed/all.xml</id><title type="html">regpaq | All</title><subtitle>B2B Marketer. Avid reader &amp; writer.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;regpaq&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Why I Became Vegan</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vegan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Became Vegan" /><published>2023-01-14T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-14T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vegan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vegan">&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost three years since I stopped eating or buying anything made from animals because I became convinced it’s unethical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t a conclusion I reached on a whim. It took many years for my mind to change. Most people think being vegan is a diet, but I learned veganism is really a philosophy. This is my first time writing about it, so for now I only want to cover the definition of veganism and why I find its core argument so convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-veganism&quot;&gt;What is veganism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s true that someone who doesn’t eat or drink anything made wholly or partly from animals is vegan, it doesn’t capture the complete picture of veganism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a definition for veganism I’ve slightly modified from The Vegan Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Veganism is a philosophy and way of living which seeks to avoid the exploitation and use of animals-as far as is possible and practicable-for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; purpose, including food, clothing, furniture, entertainment, makeup, personal products, and any other items that use materials or ingredients derived from animals.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophical part of veganism is really about ethics. Like humans, non-human animals are conscious and sentient beings. They have individual personalities, desires, experience pleasures, and feel pain. &lt;strong&gt;Despite being a different species from humans, their preferences for seeking pleasures and avoiding pain should be respected and protected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Veganism is about taking the most basic and fundamental natural right that we believe all humans have, the right to life, and extending it to animals.&lt;/strong&gt; We shouldn’t treat sentient beings like objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most people think being vegan is a more ethical choice than not, but also that it’s not &lt;em&gt;unethical&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be vegan. The difference is veganism says &lt;em&gt;it is&lt;/em&gt; unethical to not be vegan. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;core-argument-for-veganism&quot;&gt;Core argument for veganism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animals suffer in the production of animal products, and since we have access to sufficient alternatives that don’t require the use of animals to be made, that means products made from animals are unnecessary and the animal suffering is unnecessary. It is unethical to cause unnecessary suffering, therefore it is unethical to consume, purchase, or create products made from animals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to believe it’s &lt;em&gt;not unethical&lt;/em&gt; to take and use the bodies of animals for food and other materials, then we must have a truly legitimate &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; for them that is &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt; to be satisfied in any other &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most obvious &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; of animal products would be for food. We need to eat to survive, right? And generally, meat, eggs, milk, etc. contains the important nutrients we need to survive. &lt;strong&gt;However, because it’s &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; to get these nutrients from a plant-based diet, then we don’t need animal products to survive. Yes, we need food to survive, but that food doesn’t need to come from animals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it was not possible to eat a plant-based diet and live a healthy life (or in other words that didn’t cause illness or premature death), then eating food made from animals would be necessary, and the suffering animals would go through to produce that food would generally not be unethical to inflict. However, there already has been more than sufficient research done to show that people can not only survive on a plant-based diet, but is often correlated with reduced risk of cancer and longer life spans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But is it &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; to switch to a healthy plant-based diet? Well, I admit it’s not easy and there are some costs.&lt;/strong&gt; You will have to learn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what you need to eat to be healthy on a plant-based diet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to shop at grocery stores and read ingredients labels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what and how to order at restaurants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to deal with social events that revolve around food&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people think it would be too difficult for them to switch to a vegan diet, but after a few months most of these become non issues. The only thing I still find somewhat of a challenge after being vegan for nearly three years is the social aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However, none of these obstacles make switching to a vegan diet impractical enough for us to say we have a legitamte need for animal products. The far majority of people living in first world countries have access to modern grocery stores that have everything one would need to eat a healthy plant-based diet. This means it’s both possible and practical to not consume animal products. Therefore the production of animal products is unecessary and animal suffering is unecessary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality is however, that most people just don’t care about the well-being of animals. Most people love the way they taste more than they think their life is worth.&lt;/strong&gt; So how did I start caring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-changed-my-mind&quot;&gt;What changed my mind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started in 2007 when I attended a bullfight in Spain and it was the first time I can remember giving serious thought to the well-being of animals. Just imagine being the bull for a minute in this scenario…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/vegan-bull-crowd.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-crowd.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-crowd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The beginning of a bullfight in Spain&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The beginning of a bullfight in Spain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re forced into a stadium and paraded around to entertain the spectators. Then you start getting stabbed with spears repeatedly. With each piercing comes tremendous pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/vegan-bull-stab.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-stab.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-stab.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The bull is repeatedly stabbed by spears with red, decorative hilts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The bull is repeatedly stabbed by spears with red, decorative hilts&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several spears are sticking out of your body, you lose the strength to run. It’s at this moment a sword is thrust into your neck and you’re killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/vegan-bull-death.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-death.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-death.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Once the bull is too weak to offer the matador a challenge, a final, fatal blow is delivered&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Once the bull is too weak to offer the matador a challenge, a final, fatal blow is delivered&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As I was watching this bull writhe in pain, I was struck emotionally. What was the point? For our entertainment? Because it’s culture? It was barbaric.&lt;/strong&gt; It was this experience, and many others throughout the years (from books, movies and TV, YouTube videos, conversations), that sparked an uneasiness inside me about our relationship with animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But it was in 2020, when I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/C1vW9iSpLLk&quot;&gt;Alex O’Connor’s video “The Meat Eater’s Case for Veganism”&lt;/a&gt; that flipped me from being somewhat interested in the ethics of how we treat animals to all of a sudden trying to find the best arguments against veganism to refute Alex’s points. I didn’t find any then and I have yet to find any now. I knew at that moment I had to become vegan, because I was convinced it was immoral to eat animals and I had no excuse not be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C1vW9iSpLLk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-you-should-care&quot;&gt;Why you should care&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the other side of your carnitas bowl is a sentient being who was enslaved, abused, and ultimately had their life taken away from them without their consent. They didn’t want to die, and there is no way to kill someone humanely who doesn’t want to die.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you eat animals, you owe it to your conscience, your desire to be a good person, to fully understand how your meat is made and what these sentient beings go through before arriving on your dinner plate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/vegan-inside-animal-farms.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.dominionmovement.com/watch&quot;&gt;What the lives of animals are like in a factory farm, where 99% of American meat comes from.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most people would say veganism is extreme. But I think believing it’s not immoral for us to enslave, abuse, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://animalclock.org/&quot;&gt;kill billions of animals per year&lt;/a&gt; is the extreme position, and to abstain from that to be the sane position.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is how humans are: We question all our beliefs, except for the ones that we really believe in, and those we never think to question.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Orson Scott Card, Speaker for the Dead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;counter-arguments&quot;&gt;Counter arguments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is just my introduction to the vegan argument, I didn’t want to go deeper than I already have. However, it can’t be ignored that there are plenty of good and interesting counterpoints to the argument that we have a moral obligation to be vegan, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“It’s a personal choice what we eat.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Animals are inferior and don’t have the same moral worth as humans so killing them for food is not immoral.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We’ve been eating animals for thousands of years. It’s the natural food chain.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“It’s not immoral if they’re killed humanely, which is more painless than how they would probably be killed in nature.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We’re biologically made to eat meat and we need meat in a balanced diet to live a healthy life.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to address some of these and others in upcoming writings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">It’s been almost three years since I stopped eating or buying anything made from animals because I became convinced it’s unethical.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/vegan.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/vegan.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2021 Year Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021-year-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021 Year Review" /><published>2022-07-22T04:00:11-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T04:00:11-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021-year-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021-year-review">&lt;p&gt;2021 has been one of the hardest years of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In June, I hurt my back from incorrectly massaging a knot out of my back with a foam roller&lt;/strong&gt;, as silly as it sounds. I believe I pinched a nerve (I never did an MRI to confirm).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The pain was incredible. No matter what position I was in - laying on my back, laying on my stomach, standing, or sitting, it was extremely painful.&lt;/strong&gt; The pain expanded to my chest and I went to the hospital to get some tests done. Luckily, nothing life-threatening, and I was prescribed pain medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the pain medicine wasn’t enough. I did several doctor office visits to try and understand what had happened and what exact treatment I needed. But no one could tell me what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The pain was so great and constant I could hardly do anything.&lt;/strong&gt; I couldn’t stay in any one position for long. I couldn’t go on car rides for very long. I couldn’t sit in a chair to work (or even play video games). I couldn’t sleep without tossing and turning every 30 minutes. I had to sleep on the couch for months to not affect Deanna’s sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point I had nearly given up hope that I would never get better and I would be in pain for the rest of my life. I would’ve rather died than live like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luckily, I found a physical therapist who was able to eliminate about 80% of the pain&lt;/strong&gt; through deep massaging, cupping, chiropractic spine adjustments, stretching, and using a machine that stretched my neck as if it was going to rip my head off my body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even with most of the pain gone, I still feel it every day.&lt;/strong&gt; Even as I write this in July 2022, I am in pain. I thought the pain was slowly going away, but it has never fully went away and now I need to reschedule a series of physical therapy appointments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this injury has given me perspective. There are so many people in the world that have it far worse than I did, yet they have the strength to carry on. It’s interesting that on the scale of the worst injuries or losses one could incur, mine was pretty low on that scale. I’ve always had a fortunate and comfortable life, and I think the gap between someone’s normal and their injury is an important consideration when determining one’s resolve. While I think this logic has some merit and is interesting to think about, I can also think of several scenarios that show some people can endure incredible difficulties when many can’t perceive themselves capable of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of my injury, I didn’t do a whole lot this year, but there were some other things that happened I’d like to remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-job-at-codecademy&quot;&gt;New job at Codecademy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after I hurt my back, I started the interview process. This was before I was able to get any relief from physical therapy. &lt;strong&gt;I remember having to do my video interview calls on my knees because it hurt to sit in my chair and in between rounds I was icing my back on the floor.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite that, I was given an offer to join their B2B as a &lt;a href=&quot;/resume&quot;&gt;Senior Paid Marketing Manager&lt;/a&gt; and I accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codecademy.com/&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; ages ago to start learning html and css. I love to build websites with code and I’ve been enjoying learning JavaScript, so it’s really cool to work for a company whose product I’ve used and like, and is in the education space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2021-year-review-codecademy.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-codecademy.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-codecademy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My new coworkers and I&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My new coworkers and I&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m writing this in July 2022 so I’ve been working for Codecademy for a year now and so far it’s been great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;went-to-new-york-city&quot;&gt;Went to New York City&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right as I was joining, Codecademy was celebrating their 10 year anniversary and wanted to fly everyone out to their HQ in NYC. This was my second time in NYC and loved it just as much as last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2021-year-review-trade-center.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-trade-center.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-trade-center.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New York City's One World Trade Center, the tallest building in the United States&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New York City's One World Trade Center, the tallest building in the United States&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I was able to visit the world trade center 9/11 memorial. It was a somber experience, and it was surprising how small the area was of each buildings footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2021-year-review-memorial.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-memorial.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-memorial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The original World Trade Center 9/11 memorial&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The original World Trade Center 9/11 memorial&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;espresso&quot;&gt;Espresso&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in the year, I bought a rocket appartamento espresso machine, a niche coffee grinder and some accessories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2021-year-review-espresso.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-espresso.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-espresso.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My new Rocket Appartamento and Niche coffee grinder&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My new Rocket Appartamento and Niche coffee grinder&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table-2nd-col-right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rocket Appartamento Espresso Machine&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,750.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Niche Coffee Grinder&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$735.77&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Acaia Lunar Smart Espresso Scale&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$242.44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;notNeutral 6 Piece Glassware Set&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$141.10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$2,869.31&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been one of the best purchases, or rather investments, I’ve ever made. No, it doesn’t make or save me money, but I get a lot of enjoyment from making and drinking high quality espresso-based drinks every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;computer&quot;&gt;Computer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big purchase I made this year was getting a gaming pc. I thought about building my own, but I knew nothing about pc components so I went with a top of the line pre-built from Corsair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2021-year-review-pc.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-pc.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2021-year-review-pc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My new Corsair pre-built gaming pc&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My new Corsair pre-built gaming pc&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;PC Build Specs&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MSI Z490-A Pro Motherboard&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Intel Core i9-10850k CPU&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;NVIDIA GeForce RTX 3090 GPU&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4x 16GB Corsair DDR4 3200MHz Memory&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2x 2TB M.2 NVME SSD Storage&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Corsair 1000W PSU&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table-2nd-col-right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Corsair i7200 Vengeance Pre-Built PC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$4,740.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Glorious GMMK Pro Mechanical Keyboard&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$314.93&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alienware 24.5” 240Hz IPS Monitor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$360.55&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monitor Arm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$31.30&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Logitech MX Vertical Wireless Mouse&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$103.43&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$5,551.20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I’m still gaming and really enjoying it. Here’s what I’ve been playing in 2021:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Call of Duty Warzone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Civilization VI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humankind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m playing Warzone the most by far. The difference in performance and experience from an XBOX Series X is incredible - to the point where it feels like I’m even playing a whole new game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also helped me get way better at the game. I set up OBS, a screen recording program, to capture my gameplay. For a bit, I made some gameplay videos I uploaded to YouTube, but kind of lost interest in that as hardly anyone watched most of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting everything set up, I started to use the pc as my main computer. I’m starting to like windows 11, and don’t really miss using mac os at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don’t really care about the goals I had set in 2020, or rather I don’t really care about hitting the goals. I’m just trying to do enough to get by financially and spend the rest of my time on things I enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime that is reading. Sometimes it’s writing or coding. And sometimes it’s gaming and watching tv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean I’ve stopped working on improving myself, I still am. What I’m starting to ask myself is to what end will  I achieve by always working on improving, growing, and getting better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More money to have what? I feel fine with how much money I’m making. I don’t think making more will add anything to my happiness or tranquility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As said in one of my favorite quotes, the desire to always want more is what makes one poor. Obviously there is a floor of minimum needs for this quote to be true, but I’m well above that floor. I’m happy with that I have and the less I crave more things, the longer I can hold on to that happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">2021 has been one of the hardest years of my life.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2021-year-review.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2021-year-review.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2020 Year Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-year-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2020 Year Review" /><published>2021-02-09T03:00:11-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-09T03:00:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020-year-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-year-review">&lt;p&gt;I don’t even know where to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I only posted five articles. I stopped working out. I stopped reading. The world had gone mad. I’d spent 99% of time in my apartment and a lot of that was spent playing video games again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ve been dreading writing this update, but I have to do it to move on and get back into the flow of things. Back to feeling normal.&lt;/strong&gt; So much has happened in 2020 and at the same time so little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year started off great. We just moved from Glendale, the city we’ve spent the past few years in, and moved to West Hollywood. It was a very different environment than Glendale, the city and the apartment itself, which took a bit to get used to. But I loved that I had a great selection of restaurants that I could walk to and I found a lovely coffee shop I could skateboard to where I’d have a latte and read or work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the first time in my life I felt like I lived in a city and a pretty famous one at that. It was fun to feel a part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-hollywood-sign.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-hollywood-sign.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-hollywood-sign.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My apartment with the Hollywood sign in the background&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My apartment with the Hollywood sign in the background&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was bummed we couldn’t get a unit in our building that would give us a view of the Hollywood sign, let alone a view at all. It was expensive to live there and we could only get a unit that faced inside. It was dark for the most part and felt like I lived in a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-apartment.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-apartment.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-apartment.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Inside the West Hollywood apartment&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Inside the West Hollywood apartment&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And soon after we moved in, Covid-19 started worrying everyone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We heard rumors of government issued stay-at-home orders and I was doubtful it was going to come to that. I still remember the day when we were watching the Newsom or Garcetti press conference where the lockdown order was confirmed. I remember being kind of excited actually because something big was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stock market went into a free fall and I remember trying to wake up at 6:00 AM every morning to catch the opening bell and I would watch the market move all day and listen to every Covid press conference. I learned about options from Reddit’s Wall Street Bets subreddit (&lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt;) and wrote an article about it to help me understand them better. &lt;strong&gt;This was the first thing that got in the way of my normal routine.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/trading-stock-options-101-beginners&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Options Trading 101: Options Explained in Plain English&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;An introduction to stock options trading for beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-trading-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-trading-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stock Options Trading 101&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It was surreal going to Target and seeing everyone inside wearing a mask. All the food, toilet paper, and sanitizer were gone from the shelves.&lt;/strong&gt; Then waiting in a 30 minute line to go to the grocery store became the new normal. Then it hit me - this wasn’t exciting and it is going to suck for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a long time later, the protests for the death of Geroge Floyd began to happen all over the country and being in LA, there was one just down the block from us. I wasn’t on one of the main streets where it happened, but it was crazy to see all the stores and restaurants boarded up. One day police mobilized on our street in preparation of protestors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-police.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-police.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-police.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Police preparing for a nearby BLM protest on my street&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Police preparing for a nearby BLM protest on my street&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, discourse on politics and current events became insufferable and inescapable. It only continued further in this direction as Trump did more Trump things, the impeachment, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, enough about the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we were staying home and not seeing anyone, we needed a distraction and something fun to do at home. I bought Animal Crossing for the Switch and it was a lot of fun transforming our island and upgrading our clothes and houses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-animal-crossing.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-animal-crossing.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-animal-crossing.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We spent a lot of time playing Animal Crossing&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-animal-crossing2.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-animal-crossing2.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-animal-crossing2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We spent a lot of time playing Animal Crossing&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We spent a lot of time playing Animal Crossing&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Animal Crossing didn’t keep my attention as long as it did hers, so I ended up buying a PS4 again (for the third time) only to play Call of Duty Modern Warfare and Warzone. With this game, I fell in love with Call of Duty again and to this day I still spend the majority of my free time playing it. Another reason my normal routine was affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Around the beginning of May, I decided to try eating vegan and since then I’ve stuck with it. And now I can’t imagine going back.&lt;/strong&gt; Why? Well that would take a while to explain and I plan to write an article about why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, we decided to end our lease in West Hollywood early and move to Orange County. We were able to afford a bigger, nicer apartment for a little less than we were paying before in an area much cleaner and safer. Oh yeah, it has a better view, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-laguna-niguel.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-laguna-niguel.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2020-year-review-laguna-niguel.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;View from our new apartment in Orange County&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;View from our new apartment in Orange County&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I’m not a big music person and wouldn’t normally mention what I’m listening to, I feel I have to make an exception. I came across Charli XCX and I’ve listened to these albums so much this year, especially the album &lt;em&gt;How I’m Feeling Now&lt;/em&gt;, that they will forever define and bring me back to 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-how-im-feeling-now.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-how-im-feeling-now.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-how-im-feeling-now.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;ONE: How I'm Feeling Now. TWO: Charli. THREE: Pop 2&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-charli.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-charli.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-charli.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;ONE: How I'm Feeling Now. TWO: Charli. THREE: Pop 2&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-pop2.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-pop2.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-pop2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ONE: How I'm Feeling Now. TWO: Charli. THREE: Pop 2&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;ONE: How I'm Feeling Now. TWO: Charli. THREE: Pop 2&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consistency’s sake, I should talk about my goals from 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals-from-2019&quot;&gt;Goals From 2019&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-one-book-a-month&quot;&gt;Read one book a month&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only read two books completely last year, &lt;em&gt;I Will Teach You to Be Rich&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The War on Normal People&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a notes article is coming soon for &lt;em&gt;The War on Normal People&lt;/em&gt;, I did manage to write one for &lt;em&gt;I Will Teach You to Be Rich&lt;/em&gt; by Ramit Sethi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The best introduction to personal finance and how to enjoy spending your money.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ramit Sethi I Will Teach You to Be Rich&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tweeted it out and tagged Ramit and he ended up making his own tweet for it, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;The best introduction to personal finance and how to enjoy spending your money...&amp;quot;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;quot;A stark contrast from the dry, guilt-inducing material [in personal finance]...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/regpaq?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@regpaq&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/GHBTmKpwag&quot;&gt;https://t.co/GHBTmKpwag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ramit Sethi (@ramit) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ramit/status/1222196945348894725?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It drove quite a bit of traffic to the site and was definitely one of the coolest things to happen to my writing, ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest reason why I didn’t read more was because I started reading &lt;em&gt;The History of Western Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; and it’s a very long, dense book. It’s very interesting, but it takes a lot of time for me to read it because I need to look up philosophical concepts to attempt to understand everything. It’s quite exhausting to read it, but I do enjoy it. I’m about two-thirds of the way done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;write-one-article-a-week&quot;&gt;Write one article a week&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I barely wrote anything new in 2020 unfortunately. I’m always super proud and fulfilled when I publish something new, but it’s hard for me to get into a rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite articles I’ve ever written was heavily updated in 2020, and that’s my &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;Google Sheets Budget Template article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the spreadsheet budget I made to make budgeting fun.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;google sheets budget template&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the work for the article was really the spreadsheet template behind it, which I completely revamped to look way better and be even easier to use. I’m really proud of it and I’ve received a lot of Twitter DMs from random people thanking me for it and letting me know how much it’s helped them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;daily-habits&quot;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-read.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-read.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-read.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in DONE&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-journal.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-journal.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-journal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in DONE&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-published.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-published.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-published.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in DONE&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2020-year-review-finances.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-finances.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020-year-review-finances.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in DONE&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;Habit progress recorded in DONE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just really fell off with everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flossing has become such a stronghold in my routine, I don’t need to post about it anymore since I haven’t missed a day since I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also didn’t update coding or the gym, which I did four and zero times respectively in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels bad to look at this and see that I have regressed in all of my habits, except doing finances. My new goal is to &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;update my finances&lt;/a&gt; every morning and while I haven’t made it a habit, I did do it more often than I did in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals-for-2021&quot;&gt;Goals for 2021?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t really have any goals I’d like to commit to (at least these types of goals) other than getting back into the above four habits than mean the most to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m ready to get back to normal and getting back into my daily routines will help me get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, that’s it for the 2020 update. No traveling. Nothing else exciting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">I don’t even know where to begin.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2020-year-review.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2020-year-review.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Options Trading 101: Options Explained in Plain English</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/trading-stock-options-101-beginners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Options Trading 101: Options Explained in Plain English" /><published>2020-04-12T05:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-12T05:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/trading-stock-options-101-beginners</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/trading-stock-options-101-beginners">&lt;p&gt;Stock options are just like coupons. And if you know how to use a coupon, you’ll know how trading stock options work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stock-options-101-how-options-work&quot;&gt;Stock Options 101: How Options Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain how options work, let’s start with looking at something you’re already familiar with - a coupon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take this one for example - get ten-piece nuggets for $1.99 before March 15, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-tendies.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-tendies.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-tendies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coupons are exactly like stock options&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Coupons are exactly like stock options&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although coupons are free, options are not. You have to buy them. I’ll cover more on this later so for now, just assume you bought this coupon for $0.50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with this coupon, you have the choice to buy ten-piece nuggets at a guaranteed price of $1.99 before March 15th, but you don’t have to use it if you don’t want to. You have the &lt;em&gt;option&lt;/em&gt; to, but not the obligation. This coupon has essentially the same makeup as a stock option:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ten-piece nuggets are the &lt;strong&gt;underlying asset&lt;/strong&gt;, the thing which you have an option to buy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$1.99 is what’s called the &lt;strong&gt;strike price&lt;/strong&gt;, the price you and the seller &lt;em&gt;struck&lt;/em&gt; a deal on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;March 15, 2020 is the &lt;strong&gt;expiration date&lt;/strong&gt;, the last day you have the option available to use it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The $0.50 you paid for the coupon is called the &lt;strong&gt;premium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investor would buy this coupon if they think the price of chicken will go up before the expiration date so they can buy ten-piece nuggets at a guaranteed price of $1.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say there’s been a global chicken shortage and now the cost for ten-piece nuggets went up from $1.99 ($2 for simplicity’s sake) to $6. Now the investor can &lt;strong&gt;exercise&lt;/strong&gt; their option to use the coupon and buy ten-piece nuggets for the $2 price and resell them on the open market for $6. After factoring in the premium paid of the coupon ($0.50), the investor profited $3.50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if instead veganism has taken over and now ten-piece nuggets only cost $1? Since the investor could now buy ten-piece nuggets for $1 on the open market, they have no reason to use the coupon to buy them for $2. This makes the coupon worthless. In this scenario, the investor wouldn’t exercise their option to use the coupon and their loss is only the $0.50 premium they paid for the coupon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Options, at their core, are really this simple. Although they can get more complex when it comes to buying, selling, and using them in various investment strategies, they aren’t impossible to understand. Let’s leave behind the coupon analogy and now look at the two different types of option contracts and their makeup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-an-options-contract&quot;&gt;What is an Options Contract?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An options contract is an agreement that gives the purchaser an option to buy or sell a stock at a later date at a predetermined price. The agreement is always between two parties, a buyer (a.k.a. the holder or owner) and a seller (a.k.a. the writer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expiration date is when the option expires. When you’re the buyer, you can exercise an option on or before the expiration date. When you’re the seller, you can be &lt;strong&gt;assigned&lt;/strong&gt; to fulfill your obligation of the contract on or before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only two main types of option contracts, call options and put options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call options&lt;/strong&gt;, or “calls” for short, give the buyer the right to &lt;em&gt;call&lt;/em&gt; the underlying asset away from the option seller and buy it at a predetermined price up to a predetermined date. An investor purchases a call option contract when they think the price of the underlying asset will &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; in value beyond the agreed upon strike price before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put options&lt;/strong&gt;, or “puts” for short, give the buyer the right to &lt;em&gt;put&lt;/em&gt; the underlying asset up for sale and sell it to the option seller at a predetermined price up to a predetermined date. An investor purchases a put option contract when they think the price of the underlying asset will &lt;em&gt;decrease&lt;/em&gt; in value beyond the the agreed upon strike price before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both call and put options are contracts that give the buyer &lt;em&gt;the right&lt;/em&gt; to buy or sell the underlying asset, and not &lt;em&gt;the obligation&lt;/em&gt; to do so. Therefore, the seller of the contract is giving up &lt;em&gt;their right&lt;/em&gt; and control. So what’s in it for the seller? Since the option contract has value, the buyer has to pay the seller for it. This payment is called the &lt;strong&gt;premium&lt;/strong&gt;. The price for the underlying asset that the two parties agreed upon is called the &lt;strong&gt;strike price&lt;/strong&gt; because that’s the price they “struck” a deal on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ways-to-exit-an-options-trade&quot;&gt;Ways to exit an options trade&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the underlying asset’s value moves &lt;em&gt;in favor&lt;/em&gt; of the option buyer before the expiration date, they can sell the option contract itself to another buyer at a higher premium for a profit. At expiration, if the price of the underlying asset has moved beyond the strike price (this is called &lt;strong&gt;in the money&lt;/strong&gt;), they can exercise their option of the contract to buy the underlying asset at the strike price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the underlying asset’s value moves &lt;em&gt;out of favor&lt;/em&gt; of the buyer before expiration, they can sell the option at a lower premium for a loss or continue to hold it to see if the underlying asset’s value changes to be in their favor in time for expiration. If at expiration the value of the underlying asset is still below the strike price (this is called &lt;strong&gt;out of the money&lt;/strong&gt;), the buyer can let the option contract expire worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The option seller (the contract writer) can also sell the contract to another investor to close their position before expiration. At expiration, if the option is in the money, they will still be able to keep the premium but they will be assigned to buy or sell (depends on the option they wrote) the underlying asset. If the option is out of the money, their position is automatically closed and their capital is no longer at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are three ways to close out an options trade:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prior to expiration, you can buy or sell the contract itself to close your position (for profit or loss)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prior to or at expiration, the buyer can exercise their option in which the seller would get assigned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at expiration, the buyer can let the contract expire worthless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll discuss closing an options trade in more detail in a future article about option contract pricing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-read-an-options-contract&quot;&gt;How to Read an Options Contract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you know how option contracts work and their makeup, you can now learn to “read” an option. Here’s an example of an options contract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SPY MARCH 15 ’20 $260 CALL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPY&lt;/strong&gt; is the ticker for the underlying asset, in this case the S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MARCH 15 ’20&lt;/strong&gt; is the expiration date&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$260&lt;/strong&gt; is the strike price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call&lt;/strong&gt; is the type of option, in this case a call&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every broker is different and may display the elements of an options contract in different orders and formats, but they are all generally the same. Sometimes you will see an option in shorthand that can look confusing, but it’s all the same information, just more compact. For example, this is the same option as above but for a put instead of a call:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SPY051520P220&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPY&lt;/strong&gt; is the ticker, &lt;strong&gt;051520&lt;/strong&gt; is the expiration date (5/15/2020), &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; is the option type (in this case a put, or could be &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; for call), and &lt;strong&gt;220&lt;/strong&gt; is the strike price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-trade-option-contracts-instead-of-stocks-directly&quot;&gt;Why Trade Option Contracts Instead of Stocks Directly?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With trading stocks (or any equity), you have limited leverage and flexibility. For the most part, you can only &lt;em&gt;buy&lt;/em&gt; a stock or &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; a stock. With trading options, you have much more leverage and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look first at how an option provides more leverage. &lt;strong&gt;A single options contract (almost) always controls 100 shares of the underlying asset.&lt;/strong&gt; So in other words, you can control 100 shares for the price of the option’s premium without having to buy 100 shares of the stock outright. For example, SPY is currently trading at $240. You could buy 100 shares outright for $24,000 or you could buy one call option contract for a fraction of the price, which could be anywhere from, say, $400 to upwards of $1,000 depending on the strike price and expiration. Or, you can invest $24,000 to buy 40 call option contracts with a $6 premium ($600 total per contract) to instead control 4,000 shares of SPY worth $960,000. This is how options provide more leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of flexibility, trading stocks is one directional, up or down, and your profit and loss is directly tied 1:1 with the stock. Here is the profit and loss payoff chart for going long on a stock and shorting a stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/buy-stock-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/buy-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/buy-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and shorting a stock&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/short-stock-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/short-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/short-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and shorting a stock&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Payoff diagrams for buying and shorting a stock&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you buy a stock (a.k.a. go “long”), you profit when the stock’s price increases and incur a loss when the stock’s price decreases. When you short a stock, you profit when the stock’s price decreases and incur a loss when the stock’s price increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are the payoff charts for buying and selling a call option contract and buying and selling a put option contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/buy-call-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/buy-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/buy-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/buy-put-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/buy-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/buy-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/sell-call-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/sell-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sell-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/sell-put-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/sell-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sell-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice immediately the differences. Each of the above option strategies either have a limit to how much loss you can incur or a limit to how much profit you can gain. Behind the scenes, they each have their own levels of risk and probability of making a profit to tolerate with these limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying and selling call or put option contracts are just scratching the surface, too. By combining different types of options with different strike prices, you can create unique option strategies to profit in any kind of market movement. Here’s some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/bull-call-spread-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/bull-call-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/bull-call-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/bear-put-spread-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/bear-put-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/bear-put-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/long-butterfly-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/long-butterfly-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/long-butterfly-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/long-straddle-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/long-straddle-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/long-straddle-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about these for now. Just understand that with options, you have the ability to limit both profit and loss in a single trade, profit if there is little movement in an equity, or profit if there is a lot of movement regardless if it’s up or down. This is how options provide more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-read-the-options-chain&quot;&gt;How to Read the Options Chain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pull up a stock or ETF and you should see a link for “options.” Clicking this will take you to what’s called the &lt;strong&gt;options chain&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a scary looking table full of numbers you won’t understand. But don’t worry, here’s how to read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each broker will display their options chain differently, but they will all have the same essential information, and some will offer more. Here’s an example of options chain from E*Trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-option-chain.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-option-chain.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-option-chain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of a simple options chain (from E*Trade)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of a simple options chain (from E*Trade)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled up the options chain for the symbol &lt;strong&gt;SPY&lt;/strong&gt; as indicated in the top left and the type of options chain we’re looking at is the default &lt;strong&gt;Calls &amp;amp; Puts&lt;/strong&gt; chain (don’t worry about the others for now). In the next section is some standard quote information and immediately below that is where the information for the options chain begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The option chains are divided into different sections by the various &lt;strong&gt;expiration dates&lt;/strong&gt; shown as tabs. You’ll see I have &lt;em&gt;April 9 ’20&lt;/em&gt; selected. Clicking on the various expiration dates will change the data in the table beneath it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each row in this table is an individual options contract you can buy or sell. Splitting the table down the middle is the &lt;strong&gt;strike price&lt;/strong&gt; column. By default, option chains will show a certain number of available contracts with a strike price below and above the current price of the underlying asset (again, SPY in this case). The current price of SPY at the time of this screenshot is $272 as seen in the quote section. You can change which strike prices are shown by entering a desired strike price at the top in the “Near” box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left side of the strike price column in the table are &lt;strong&gt;call option contracts&lt;/strong&gt; and to the right of the strike price are &lt;strong&gt;put option contracts&lt;/strong&gt;. Since the current price of SPY is $272, all the call option contracts with a strike price below $272 are shaded blue because they are &lt;strong&gt;in the money&lt;/strong&gt; (often abbreviated as ITM). You can see the same thing on the right side for put option contracts with strike prices above $272. Contracts that are not shaded blue are considered &lt;strong&gt;out of the money&lt;/strong&gt; (OTM). When an option contract’s strike price is the same as the underlying asset’s current price (or within a few cents), it’s considered an &lt;strong&gt;at the money&lt;/strong&gt; option (ATM). ITM, ATM, and OTM are the three types of &lt;strong&gt;option moneyness&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the table you’ll see lots of numbers. Here’s the breakdown of each column:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Interest&lt;/strong&gt; is the total number of these contracts that are currently active and open&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vol&lt;/strong&gt;, short for volume, is the number of these contracts that were opened just today&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change&lt;/strong&gt; is today’s price (premium) movement of that contract since the closing price of the previous trading day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last&lt;/strong&gt; is the price (also called the &lt;strong&gt;mark&lt;/strong&gt;) of the contract’s last completed transaction, whether opened or closed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bid&lt;/strong&gt; is the current maximum price buyers are willing to pay for that contract&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask&lt;/strong&gt; is the current minimum price sellers are willing sell that contract for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a more advanced options chain table from Power E*Trade, their more advanced options trading platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-advanced-options-chain.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-advanced-options-chain.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-advanced-options-chain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the options chain from a more advanced broker (from Power E*Trade)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the options chain from a more advanced broker (from Power E*Trade)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first point out these options chains are &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; looking at call option contracts - notice the strike price column is not in the middle anymore but all the way to the right. That’s because with more advanced option trading platforms, you can hide one side or the other to see more columns of information for a contract all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these options chains look completely different on the surface, it’s still mostly the same information. Take a minute to compare this screenshot to the previous one and try to spot what’s the same and what’s new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first difference you might notice is I’ve selected multiple expiration dates, &lt;em&gt;Apr-09-20&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Apr-15-20&lt;/em&gt; and you can see both option chains displayed below at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a breakdown of the data in the new columns in the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bid Size&lt;/strong&gt; is the number of contracts buyers have placed buy orders for that are waiting to be filled at the current bid price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask Size&lt;/strong&gt; is the number of contracts sellers have placed sell orders for that are waiting to be filled at the current ask price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delta&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Gamma&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Theta&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Vega&lt;/strong&gt; (along with &lt;strong&gt;Rho&lt;/strong&gt; which isn’t shown) are referred to as the &lt;strong&gt;Greeks&lt;/strong&gt; and I’m going to cover this in another article - don’t worry about them for now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implied Volatility&lt;/strong&gt; or IV is a measurement of how volatile the price of that contract is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prob ITM Exp ATM IV&lt;/strong&gt; is the probability that contract will be ITM at it’s expiration date (this is calculated using the IV from the same expiration date contract that’s currently ATM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intrinsic Value&lt;/strong&gt; is the dollar value worth per contract if it expired right now. Only contracts ITM have an intrinsic value greater than 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extrinsic Value&lt;/strong&gt; is the dollar value worth per contract investors give an option based on its profit potential at expiration that has not yet been realized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-buy-to-open-an-option-trade&quot;&gt;How to Buy to Open an Option Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you can buy to open an options contract, you will need to get option approval from your brokerage. How to accomplish this is different with each broker, but should be easy to figure out. There are typically four levels of option access, with each level permitting different types of option strategies. Apply for at least level two. Your broker will tell you what each level grants access to. Once you submit your request, it may take a few trading days to be approved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various ways for each broker to &lt;em&gt;open a new position&lt;/em&gt; for an options contract, but you can most likely click a contract’s ask price to buy it or the bid price to write (sell) it. Here’s what it looks like in Power E*Trade to buy the April 15th $268 contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-order.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-order.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-order.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of an option order window (from Power E*Trade)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of an option order window (from Power E*Trade)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at the very top, confirm you have the right account selected&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;below that, confirm the symbol is correct, in this case SPY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confirm whether you want to buy or write the option using the &lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; toggle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;select the number of contracts you want to buy under &lt;strong&gt;Qty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confirm your &lt;strong&gt;Expiration&lt;/strong&gt; date is correct&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confirm your &lt;strong&gt;Strike&lt;/strong&gt; price is correct&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price Type&lt;/strong&gt; let’s you choose how you want your order executed, I recommend to always use limit to secure your desired price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set your desired price under &lt;strong&gt;Limit Price&lt;/strong&gt;. To the right, you can see the bid and ask price for the contract change in real time as you’re placing your order&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set how long you want your order to stay open under &lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set whether you want your order to process only if it can buy or write all the contracts at your limit price under &lt;strong&gt;Special Handling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After everything looks correct, clicking the &lt;strong&gt;Preview&lt;/strong&gt; button will allow you to do one final confirmation of your trade before placing an order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-sell-to-close-an-option-trade&quot;&gt;How to Sell to Close an Option Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close an open position, go to your open positions list in your broker and find the position you want to close. There should be a &lt;em&gt;close&lt;/em&gt; button or link when you hover over it or select it. This is the best way, at least for me, to ensure you’re closing a position, instead of &lt;em&gt;selling to open&lt;/em&gt; a new position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s an overview of what options are, how they work, why options can be a useful instrument for investors, and how to open and close an option trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next article, I’ll cover what affects a contract’s price, dive deeper into the definitions of some of the items in this article (e.g. IV, Prob ITM, etc), and explain what each of the Greeks mean.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Stock options are just like coupons. And if you know how to use a coupon, you’ll know how trading stock options work.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)" /><published>2020-02-07T00:51:34-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:51:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template">&lt;p&gt;I have a strange love for spreadsheets and I want to share the budget template I made on Google Sheets that I’ve been using and building for over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make your own copy by clicking the link below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1FyZvG4UI11Kd-kaVPpUiV5mRjgPz4OERfxak_KXCsgU/copy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; id=&quot;budget_download&quot;&gt;Make a copy: My Google Sheets Budget Template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The template is based off the principles and concepts from Ramit Sethi’s personal finance book, &lt;em&gt;“I Will Teach You to Be Rich.”&lt;/em&gt; I’ll cover everything you need to know in this post, but if you want to learn more about it, you can read my summary of the book below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The best introduction to personal finance and how to enjoy spending your money.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ramit Sethi I Will Teach You to Be Rich&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-this-google-sheets-budget-template-better-than-the-others-out-there&quot;&gt;What Makes This Google Sheets Budget Template Better Than The Others Out There&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;all-the-setup-is-on-one-page&quot;&gt;All the setup is on one page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just one configuration tab, you’ll fill out all your info: income, account names, budget, etc. All the other tabs pull data from this &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab so you never have to enter in any information twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-one-page-settings.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-one-page-settings.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-one-page-settings.png&quot; alt=&quot;Once you set up this Config tab, just enter expenses and account balances. That's it!&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Once you set up this Config tab, just enter expenses and account balances. That's it!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;built-in-guided-setup&quot;&gt;Built-in guided setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening up a new Google Sheets budget template with all these numbers and tabs can be daunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I wanted to create a guided setup to make it super simple for anyone to get started. When you open up the template, you’ll be greeted with easy-to-follow prompts so you know exactly what you need to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/guided-tour.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Bright orange prompts make this the easiest Google Sheets budget template to get set up on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setup-checklist&quot;&gt;Setup checklist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing the configuration settings, the checklist shows you where to go next in the template to enter your expenses and account balances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-setup-checklist.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-setup-checklist.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-setup-checklist.png&quot; alt=&quot;The setup checklist will automatically mark things complete as you finish each step.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The setup checklist will automatically mark things complete as you finish each step.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-dashboard-to-rule-them-all&quot;&gt;One dashboard to rule them all&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Google Sheets budget template has four tabs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; - the main tab where you can see your spending vs budget for the current month and analyze previous months’ spending. All the data is pulled from the other tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; - where you enter all your expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; - to record your bank account, retirement account, credit card and loan balances, etc. This data is used to help measure whether your net worth is increasing or shrinking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; - as explained above, this is where you fill out your income, name your accounts, and set your budgets, which is used in all the other tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll spend most of your time in the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;The dashboard is the clearest way to see where you're spending your money.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The dashboard is the clearest way to see where you're spending your money.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;always-know-how-much-of-your-monthly-budget-you-have-left&quot;&gt;Always know how much of your monthly budget you have left&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you fill out your expenses, there’s a “module” where you can see exactly how much of a budget category you’ve used so far in the current month and know exactly how much you have left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve overspent in one budget category, the template will let you take remaining budget from another category to cover it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/budget-module.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This makes it fun to fill out your expenses everyday and it's easy to temporarily take budget from another category to cover one you've overspent in.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budget-and-keep-track-of-annual-irregular-expenses&quot;&gt;Budget and keep track of annual, irregular expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The template is also built to accommodate irregular expenses that you might only spend money on or have to pay for a few times a year. Once you enter a list of the things you want to create an annual budget for, the template will calculate how much you need to save per month to cover it. And that amount is deducted before you set up your monthly budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; alt=&quot;This template helps you plan for irregular or annual expenses.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This template helps you plan for irregular or annual expenses.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spend-your-money-without-feeling-guilty&quot;&gt;Spend your money without feeling guilty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call the monthly budget the &lt;em&gt;“guilt-free budget,”&lt;/em&gt; which is a concept taken from the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://regpaq.com/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I Will Teach You to Be Rich.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Since the budget template is built to help you put aside money for savings before creating your monthly budget, it means you don’t ever have to feel guilty about spending the money you do have left over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a fundamental shift in my perspective about personal finance Ramit calls &lt;em&gt;paying yourself first.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;built-to-drive-behavioral-change&quot;&gt;Built to drive behavioral change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my friends use a budgeting app like Mint and I’ve tried them, too. But these apps don’t really help me spend less money - they just tell me where I spend my money and try to guess (poorly) the category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I love budgets built on spreadsheets. I can customize it exactly the way I need to actually help me spend my money more thoughtfully. On less of things I care little about, and more on the things I care a lot about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A bad budget system only shows you where your money is going. A good budget system will create a change in your behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1FyZvG4UI11Kd-kaVPpUiV5mRjgPz4OERfxak_KXCsgU/copy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; id=&quot;budget_download&quot;&gt;try my Google Sheets budget template&lt;/a&gt;, make a copy of it and try it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are simple and clear instructions with extra notes on cells that have an asterisk(*) - just hover over those cells to the see note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re stuck and need more info to get going, read on to get the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-my-google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;How to Use My Google Sheets Budget Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, cells with an asterisk(*) mean there is a note on that cell with more information. Hover over it to see what it says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-enter-your-income&quot;&gt;I. Enter your income&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the top left box on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab, enter your income. Follow the orange colored cells as cues for which part to fill out next. If you don’t &lt;strong&gt;contribute to a 401k&lt;/strong&gt; or typically receive any &lt;strong&gt;extra monthly income&lt;/strong&gt;, enter $0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-income.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-income.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-income.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your income data in the Income Breakdown box on the Dashbord tab&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your income data in the Income Breakdown box on the Dashbord tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This budget template is only made for two sources of income. If you have more than one additional source of income, you can count them together and enter the total as one number for your &lt;strong&gt;extra monthly income&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All income entered here will be available for your budget. Before leaving the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab, you’ll be able to choose how much of it will go into savings, additional retirement accounts, loans, etc, but first you have to name your accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ii-name-your-accounts&quot;&gt;II. Name your accounts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to give a &lt;strong&gt;nickname&lt;/strong&gt; for every type of bank account, asset, and liability you have. The &lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt; is very important to formulas in in the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tabs and cannot be changed. If you don’t have an account with the listed &lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt;, leave it blank and skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-bank-account-names.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-bank-account-names.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-bank-account-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-asset-names.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-asset-names.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-asset-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-liability-names.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-liability-names.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-liability-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have more accounts than what the &lt;strong&gt;types&lt;/strong&gt; have you can count them together as one. For example, if you have four credit cards, you can count two of them together and give &lt;strong&gt;credit card #3&lt;/strong&gt; the nickname &lt;strong&gt;Amex &amp;amp; Citi cards&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iii-create-your-annual-budget&quot;&gt;III. Create your annual budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why you create your budget for annual expenses before monthly expenses is so that you’re encouraged to set aside money to be better prepared for irregular expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by adding things you pay for once a year or irregularly in the &lt;strong&gt;Annual Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box. You can find examples and suggestions by hovering over the &lt;strong&gt;budget category*&lt;/strong&gt; cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your annual and irregular expenses to prepare for the future.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your annual and irregular expenses to prepare for the future.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you enter in all the annual and irregular expenses you can think of, the budget template will divide the &lt;strong&gt;total&lt;/strong&gt; into a monthly amount inside the &lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-enter-your-fixed-monthly-costs&quot;&gt;IV. Enter your fixed monthly costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; are recurring monthly expenses that you don’t expect to change month-to-month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the list is the monthly amount to set aside for your &lt;strong&gt;annual budget&lt;/strong&gt; and the second item is your &lt;strong&gt;after tax retirement&lt;/strong&gt; account. If you have one and gave it a nickname in the &lt;strong&gt;Asset Names&lt;/strong&gt; box, the nickname will be used for this line item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have one or don’t plan on contributing to the one you do have, enter $0 for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-fixed-monthly-costs.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-fixed-monthly-costs.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-fixed-monthly-costs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your fixed monthly costs.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your fixed monthly costs.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is room for eight additional fixed monthly costs. There are suggestions in the note on the &lt;strong&gt;budget category*&lt;/strong&gt; cell. Along with budgeting for annual expenses and retirement, I highly recommend setting more money aside for extra savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;pay yourself first&lt;/em&gt; concept described in &lt;em&gt;“I Will Teach You to Be Rich.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The goal [of pay yourself first] is to make sure that enough income is first saved or invested before monthly expenses or discretionary purchases are made.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/payyourselffirst.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Investopedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you’re left with your &lt;strong&gt;total for guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt;, which is how much you have left for discretionary spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-create-your-guilt-free-monthly-budget&quot;&gt;IV. Create your guilt-free, monthly budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained earlier, it’s called your guilt-free budget because this is what is left over after setting money aside for savings, retiremenet, and future annual expenses. This is your money to spend however you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Guilt-Free Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box, enter categories of expenses and an allotted amount. Again, there are suggestions in the note on the &lt;strong&gt;budget category*&lt;/strong&gt; cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve budgeted over what you have available in your &lt;strong&gt;total for guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt; from the &lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; box, this &lt;strong&gt;total&lt;/strong&gt; number will turn red and. The number below the &lt;strong&gt;total&lt;/strong&gt; number is how much you have left from your &lt;strong&gt;guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your monthly and annual budget is now set up! The next step is setting up the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-setting-up-the-balance-sheet&quot;&gt;V. Setting up the balance sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going deep into the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;, you just need to enter your start date in the orange cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start date is the first of a month, current or in the past, written as &lt;em&gt;“1/1/2020”&lt;/em&gt;. Once you enter your start date, it will reformat to &lt;em&gt;“Jan ‘20”&lt;/em&gt; and fill the rest of the range for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/dates-on-balance-sheet.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Write the start date in the format of 1/1/2020.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do here, but it makes sense to first record your expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-how-to-record-expenses&quot;&gt;V. How to record expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; tab you’ll record your monthly and annual expenses - one row per one expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest presumable downsides of doing your budget in Google Sheets is you have to enter in your expenses manually, but this is a blessing in disguise. Entering your expenses manually has a big and positive psychological effect on your spending behavior. It makes you “feel the pain” of every dollar you spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Manually recording your expenses every week will force you to review every transaction, to feel the pain of every dollar spent, and make you think “was that really necessary?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit is you can easily split an expense into two different budget categories, which I’ve found helpful many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/entering-expenses.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of how fast you can enter expenses by using the 'tab' and 'enter' keys&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the heading, you’ll see your &lt;strong&gt;guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;annual budget&lt;/strong&gt; categories from the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab. When you enter an expense, start with the date in &lt;strong&gt;column a&lt;/strong&gt;, the name of the place you spend the money in &lt;strong&gt;column b&lt;/strong&gt;, and then tab over to the column with the right budget category for that expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and enter all your expenses beginning from the start date you entered on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t enter expenses or transfers you already accounted for in the &lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; box on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vi-filling-out-the-balance-sheet&quot;&gt;VI. Filling out the balance sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the beginning of every month you’ll fill out the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tab for the previous month. This is where you will add up all the money you have and owe in your accounts so you can see if your wealth and net worth are increasing or shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before moving on, make sure the first three items are marked complete in the &lt;strong&gt;Setup&lt;/strong&gt; checklist on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet’s&lt;/strong&gt; sidebar, you’ll see the accounts you’ve named on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab. At the beginning of the month when you fill this out, you’ll enter the balances of each account in the previous month’s column. For example, if I was filling this out today on February 7th, I’d enter the balances under the &lt;strong&gt;Jan ‘20&lt;/strong&gt; column. So if you’re starting date is the first of this month, you don’t have to fill out anything until the month is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You only need to enter balances in the white rows. You can skip the greyed out columns (don’t delete them) and don’t overwrite anything with a &lt;strong&gt;-&lt;/strong&gt; in the cell. The dashes indicate a placeholder for a formula and will populate if and when it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter the previous months' ending balances in each row for the indicated month.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter the previous months' ending balances in each row for the indicated month.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Liabilities&lt;/strong&gt; section, you’ll do the same thing as you do with your bank accounts but for your rent/mortgage, loans, and credit cards. If you don’t have a mortgage, enter $0 for the &lt;strong&gt;rent&lt;/strong&gt;. Rent is paid on the 1st of the month so by the end of the month, which these totals are representing, you don’t owe anymore rent. So actually, &lt;strong&gt;rent&lt;/strong&gt; should be $0 for every month in the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pay a mortgage, then you can enter the mortgage payoff amount in the &lt;strong&gt;mortgage&lt;/strong&gt; row. I do the same with my &lt;strong&gt;car loan&lt;/strong&gt;. When filling out your credit card balances, make sure any pending credit card payments are already reflected in your bank account balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-liabilities.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-liabilities.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-liabilities.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Liabilities section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Liabilities section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Annual Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; sections automatically sum your expenses for that month for each budget category. You can analyze this easier in the the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-expenses.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-expenses.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-expenses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Monthly and Annual Expenses secions with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Monthly and Annual Expenses secions with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last section is the &lt;strong&gt;Totals&lt;/strong&gt; section, which brings everything together to calculate your &lt;strong&gt;net checking balance&lt;/strong&gt; (money in checking minus current credit card balances) and your &lt;strong&gt;net worth&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last row you can leave notes for yourself if something noteworthy occurred that you might want to come back to. The word “Notes” will auto populate in each month, but to leave an actual note, right-click the &lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt; cell and select “Insert note.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-totals.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-totals.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-totals.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Totals section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Totals section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all you need to do on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tab. As you use this Google Sheets budget template each month, more data on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab will start to populate and be more useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vii-using-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;VII. Using the dashboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the best part - the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;. This is where you can see the most useful insights for your budget. Except for a small part that I’ll explain below, everything on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; is automated and you shouldn’t have to change anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top is an &lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt; box with just a few pieces of information to get your overall personal finance health. It’s updated every time a month is filled out on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; so if your start date is the first of the current month, you won’t see anything here yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-overview.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-overview.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-overview.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Overview box on the Dashbord tab shows your personal finance health from a bird's eye view.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Overview box on the Dashbord tab shows your personal finance health from a bird's eye view.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the right of your &lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt; box is a graph of your &lt;strong&gt;Net Worth&lt;/strong&gt; growth. This is pulling the last seven months of data from the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-net-worth.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-net-worth.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-net-worth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualize the grow of your net worth over time.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Visualize the grow of your net worth over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is my favorite part of the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;, the &lt;strong&gt;This Month’s Budget Spent So Far*&lt;/strong&gt; box. This shows how your spending is doing for the current month compared to your budget for each category. Since I update my &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; tab every morning, I can see my updated budget here every day so I know exactly how much of my budget I have left for each category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/budget-module.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This makes it fun to fill out your expenses everyday and it's easy to temporarily take budget from another category to cover one you overspent in.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you overspent in one category, you can subtract &lt;strong&gt;Remaining&lt;/strong&gt; budget from another budget category by subtracting an amount from it in the &lt;strong&gt;Cut Remaining*&lt;/strong&gt; column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the same module for annual expenses below the monthly one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; alt=&quot;Always know exactly how much of your budget you have left of your annual budget for each category.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Always know exactly how much of your budget you have left of your annual budget for each category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the monthly and the annual &lt;strong&gt;Budget Spent So Far&lt;/strong&gt; boxes will update automatically every month and year respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is the &lt;strong&gt;Spent vs Budget Previous 7 Months*&lt;/strong&gt; box. This is a dynamic graph that compares your spending to your budget for each category. Use the dropdown selector in the top right of the box to look at a specific budget category or look at the total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/spent-vs-budget.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Spent vs Budget box on the Dashbord tab visualizes your spending for each category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this graph is only looking at the previous seven completed months. It doesn’t take into account the current months’s spending because it’s not over yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab is the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses Table Previous 7 Months*&lt;/strong&gt; box. This provides the same data as the graph above, but in a table format. Amounts will turn red if you overspent your budget in that category that month. This is a great way to quickly see how you’re doing staying under budget at a glance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-expense-table.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-expense-table.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-expense-table.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Expenses Last 7 Months box shows a table of your spending vs your budget for each category.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Expenses Last 7 Months box shows a table of your spending vs your budget for each category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-budgeting-tips&quot;&gt;Bonus Budgeting Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A budget is only good if you update it consistently, keep it accurate, and spend time analyzing your spending. That’s why I made it a point to make this budget template in Google Sheets look nice, be easy to use, and be rewarding to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes that’s still not enough. &lt;strong&gt;There’s definitely been times where I don’t do it for a few weeks at a time and the more you wait, the more work you’ll have to do, and the more you won’t look forward to doing it&lt;/strong&gt;. I‘ve made it a habit to enter my expenses every morning instead of once a week or month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe a budget will help you get control of your spending, read this guide on how to stick to new habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tip is to use a credit card for all transactions when possible. Using a credit card makes it much easier to keep track of your spending and at the same time protects your bank account from fraud, builds your credit, and you can earn points and rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think of the spreadsheet. If you found some places where I messed up or have ideas for new functionality, let me know on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/regpaq&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">I have a strange love for spreadsheets and I want to share the budget template I made on Google Sheets that I’ve been using and building for over five years.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fathom Analytics Review (From a Marketer)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fathom-analytics-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fathom Analytics Review (From a Marketer)" /><published>2020-01-27T17:02:48-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-27T17:02:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fathom-analytics-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fathom-analytics-review">&lt;p&gt;Fathom Analytics is a cookie-less analytics platform that values user privacy above all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most marketers default to using Google Analytics for every website. It’s free, powerful, and the industry standard. Why try anything else, &lt;em&gt;right?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-wanted-an-alternative-to-google-analytics&quot;&gt;Why I Wanted an Alternative to Google Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s three reasons I wanted something different than Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It adds load time to a website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It uses cookies and requires a GDPR notice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It tracks users for Google’s own data gain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When rebuilding this site from scratch, one of my big focuses was on speed.&lt;/strong&gt; Since I was using Netlify to host and deploy my site from GitHub, I first tried their server-side analytics called &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netlify Analytics is cool because it tracks users on the server side vs the client side. That means it adds zero weight and load time to a website, doesn’t use cookies, and doesn’t track users. &lt;em&gt;Great!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the product isn’t nearly detailed enough to offer any actionable insights, especially at $9/month as I explained in my review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics Review (From a Marketer)&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Is it everything the industry has been waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/netlify-analytics-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/netlify-analytics-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/netlify-analytics-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;netlify analytics review from a marketer&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So still interested in other analytics platforms, I heard about Fathom through Twitter. Although it’s not server-side analytics, it is cookie-less and doesn’t add much more load time than Google Analytics does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of Fathom started in 2018 from a tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pjrvs/&quot;&gt;Paul Jarvis&lt;/a&gt; who asked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What if website analytics software didn’t take your users data to line their pockets for advertising?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul Jarvis&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I love the idea behind this.&lt;/strong&gt; But a problem I couldn’t deal with when switching to Netlify Analytics was, as a marketer, not being able to take away enough actionable insights to improve my content and website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would Fathom Analytics be any different? &lt;strong&gt;Because I don’t want to pay for vanity metrics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is Fathom Analytics more expensive than Netlify Analytics, but it will add to my website’s load time. If I’m going to have to pay more and deal with the load time, it will have to be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So far, I’ve been using and paying for Fathom for seven months now and here’s what I think of it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-review-of-fathom-analytics-can-it-replace-google-analytics-for-marketers&quot;&gt;My Review of Fathom Analytics: Can it Replace Google Analytics for Marketers?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fathom analytics has two types of customers: personal blogs (like this website), and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For personal blogs, the message is simple: Google is kind of a bully and you don’t want to give them data on all your users. And their analytics is complicated to use. So here’s an analytics platform that just gives you the data you need and keeps your user data private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For businesses (and marketers), it’s a different story. We actually know how to use Google Analytics and rely on that data to help drive our SEO, content, and website strategy. &lt;strong&gt;Do most marketers care about their user privacy? Aren’t marketers the ones who are always trying to identify their users?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a much tougher sell. In my opinion, the only companies who are going to ditch Google Analytics for privacy-focused analytics like Fathom are ones with founders who already value data privacy. If they don’t, no chance in hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t think Paul Jarvis or his co-founder &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackellis/&quot;&gt;Jack Ellis&lt;/a&gt; care. They don’t want those types of customers anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The way we run our business is ridiculously simple (not the norm in tech): we charge a fair amount of money for our product, use that money to keep the business running indefinitely, and remain small so that we don’t need a lot of money to be profitable and sustainable.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/about&quot;&gt;Fathom Analytics About Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you, as a marketer, don’t value data-privacy for your users, you’re probably not going to like Fathom Analytics. If you do, it’s then it’s the best privacy-focused analytics solution available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t decide whether you value data-privacy or tracking users more, then read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/ethical-marketing-dilemma.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/ethical-marketing-dilemma.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/ethical-marketing-dilemma.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The ethical marketer's dilemma.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The ethical marketer's dilemma.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-data-can-you-see-from-fathom-analytics&quot;&gt;What Data Can You See from Fathom Analytics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of what you get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;live, real-time data that doesn’t expire like Netlify Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;custom date range picker to filter data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;total unique visits (equivalent to sessions in Google Analytics, I think), page views, average time on site, and bounce rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list of your site’s URLs with the percent of total and number of unique visits and page views&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/support/goals&quot;&gt;unlimited goal creation&lt;/a&gt; by link click, page load, or form submission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list of referrers (actual page referring URL) with the percent of total and number of unique visits and page views (also shows the individual tweets sending you traffic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;device type, browser, and country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all sounds good, but when I dug in, I found some shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-want-from-fathom-analytics&quot;&gt;What I Want From Fathom Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a few things I’d like to see built in future releases. I’m not sure if it’s possible based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/news/anonymization&quot;&gt;their way of measuring traffic&lt;/a&gt;, but if it is, I would be so happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Fathom Analytics, you can’t:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;filter traffic by referrer to see what pages are being viewed by that referring traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or filter traffic by device type, browser, or country (no equivalent to Google Analytics’ dimensions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;filter metrics by looking at a one page URL at a time to see the referrers, device type, country, and goals for any given page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;see bounce rate, average time spent on site, or goal completions by page URL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or see the above by the first page URL of a unique visit (equivalent to Google Analytics’ Landing Page dimension)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these were added, this would give me about 90% of what I use Google Analytics for as a marketer and would be sufficient for a personal blog, but still don’t think it could suffice for a growth-focused company’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they can’t add these features without sacrificing user privacy, Fathom is the type of company to stand its ground and say &lt;em&gt;no.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/usefathom/fathom/issues/283&quot;&gt;Paul Jarvis already denied my request to work with AMP.&lt;/a&gt; I get it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-cool-things-you-can-do-with-fathom-analytics&quot;&gt;Other Cool Things You Can Do With Fathom Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can choose to make your analytics public if you want to have a transparent website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do have an affiliate program where you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;get 25% lifetime commissions and people you refer will get $10 off their first month&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They’re working on an API - I’m going to use it to display page view counts on articles for social proof&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can set up weekly and monthly reports and also set up client reports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can use it on unlimited domains and &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;their pricing is based on total page views&lt;/a&gt; not by domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can get a &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;7-day free trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-fathom-analytics-worth-it&quot;&gt;Is Fathom Analytics Worth It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fathom Analytics costs $14/month and right now, I do feel like I’m paying for vanity metrics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/fathom-analytics-pricing.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/fathom-analytics-pricing.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/fathom-analytics-pricing.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fathom Analytics starts at $14/month with unlimited domains.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Fathom Analytics starts at $14/month with unlimited domains.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I enjoy paying for it and using it on this site. It’s rare to come across a company that sticks to its mission which radiates in everything they do - their roadmap, design, content, and podcast. And they’re upfront about charging more than the industry standard so they can afford to stick to their principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I just love it when companies do that. And I’m a sucker for it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So should you make the switch? Well it comes down to whether you can get behind the mission of the company:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Our goal is huge but simple: to make as many websites as possible black holes for data to Google.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul Jarvis&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you vibe with that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;give it a shot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-april-2020&quot;&gt;Update April 2020&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the decision to switch back to Google Analytics. Because my site isn’t big enough and I don’t write as much as I’d like to, I don’t get enough value from premium analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I enjoy what Fathom is doing, I’m going to pause for now and come back soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the fun of it, I tested the difference in my site speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Requests&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Data over network&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Resources on page&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Load time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fathom&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;233 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;312 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;623 ms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;277 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;430 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;384 ms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, Google Analytics added more weight to the page, but was quicker to load. And since I don’t have any third party embeds or sending this data to any third party websites, I still don’t need a cookie consent notice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Fathom Analytics is a cookie-less analytics platform that values user privacy above all.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/fathom-analytics-review.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/fathom-analytics-review.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2019 Year Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019-year-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2019 Year Review" /><published>2020-01-21T03:00:11-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-21T03:00:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019-year-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019-year-review">&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals-from-2018&quot;&gt;Goals From 2018&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-one-book-a-month&quot;&gt;Read one book a month&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like last year in 2018, I had a goal to read one book a month. Also like last year, I didn’t do it. In fact, &lt;em&gt;I did worse&lt;/em&gt;. Here’s what I did read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kindle (3): &lt;em&gt;The Effective Executive&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Laws of Human Nature&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Blitzscaling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audible (4): &lt;em&gt;Benjamin Franklin: An American Life&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The 50th Law&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trust Me, I’m Lying&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Creative Calling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;The Effective Executive—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The essential handbook to learn leadership and effectiveness at work.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/peter-drucker-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/peter-drucker-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/peter-drucker-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/peter-drucker-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/peter-drucker.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Peter Drucker author of The Effective Executive&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only enjoyed &lt;em&gt;The Effective Executive&lt;/em&gt; so it’s the only book I published notes on. On the other hand, I enjoyed listening to all the audio books, especially Ryan Holiday’s &lt;em&gt;Trust Me, I’m Lying&lt;/em&gt; and Chase Jarvis’s &lt;em&gt;Creative Calling&lt;/em&gt;. Because it’s difficult to take notes on an audio book here’s my personal takeaway from each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trust Me, I’m Lying:&lt;/em&gt; The media can be unknowingly manipulated by marketers to create stories about what they want, and then the people are unknowingly manipulated to think and believe what marketers and the media want us to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creative Calling:&lt;/em&gt; Everyone has creativity and it makes us happy to use our creativity to make things. Strive to create more in your life and you will live a more satisfying life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I ended up spending a lot of time learning more HTML, CSS, and JS (more on this later), I didn’t read as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;write-one-article-a-week&quot;&gt;Write one article a week&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t publish as much as I wanted to, but I did write more than last year. In total, I published eleven articles - a far cry from the goal of 52.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, I did do some of my best writing and started &lt;a href=&quot;/philosophy&quot;&gt;writing about philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my two favorite articles I wrote in 2019:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Virtue is a Better Goal Than Legacy&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The Stoics saw virtue as life&amp;#39;s highest objective. I&amp;#39;m starting to see why.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/moral-virtue-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/moral-virtue-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/moral-virtue-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/moral-virtue-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Virtue is its own reward&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Stop Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why these comparisons don&amp;#39;t make sense and how it improved my mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others.png&quot; alt=&quot;stop comparing yourself to others&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The articles I’m really proud of and enjoy writing are the ones that take the longest. With the time I allot to writing, it’s not sustainable to write these types of articles every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for 2020 is to keep the same goal, but plan out my topics in advance and mix in shorter ones with longer ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;daily-habits&quot;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-meditating.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-meditating.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-meditating.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-journaling.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-journaling.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-journaling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-flossing.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-flossing.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-flossing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-working-out.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-working-out.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-working-out.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;Habit progress recorded in Done.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last year I was considering quitting meditation and I did end up quitting it.&lt;/strong&gt; It was a drag to do in the mornings and I don’t really think it made enough of an impact in my day-to-day thoughts to warrant the will power it took to do every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of meditating, I think I get more value from journaling. It’s not supposed to help in the same exact way, but &lt;strong&gt;journaling has helped me think more clearly and carefully about meaningful things in my life - goals, relationships, work, ideas, politics, and philosophy&lt;/strong&gt;. I did much better last year than in 2018 and I’m still going strong into 2020. Here’s a guide I wrote this year about journaling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;23 Stoic Journal Prompts for Self-Development&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Inspired by the journal method of Marcus Aurelius, these journal prompts will help you improve your character, acquire tranquility, and be more of a Stoic.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stoic-journal-topics-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stoic-journal-topics-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics-250.jpeg 250w,
                                /assets/images/stoic-journal-topics-572.jpeg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;stoic journal topics&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disappointingly, I stopped going to the gym.&lt;/strong&gt; I was doing really well last year but then I tapered off. It all started from quitting Equinox, which saved me a lot of money. I tried to substitute it with my apartment’s gym, but the equipment is nowhere near expansive enough to continue my routine. I had to significantly adjust my exercises and they just weren’t as effective or enjoyable so I lost interest. I do plan to start again in 2020, but it’s not as high of a priority as it was in 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some good news is I didn’t miss a single day of flossing.&lt;/strong&gt; This may not seem like much to some, but it’s a big deal for me because I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; used to floss. And doing it every single day now? That’s a big change. It’s great to go to the dentist and not have to have the “flossing talk.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-coding.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-coding.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-coding.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-reading.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-reading.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-reading.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-publishing.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-publishing.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-publishing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-finances.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-finances.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-finances.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Habit progress recorded in Done.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;Habit progress recorded in Done.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I started tracking some new habits: learning how to code, reading, writing, and and staying on top of my finances.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m setting a goal for 2020 to code at least a little bit every day,&lt;/strong&gt; whether it’s actually writing code or doing tutorials. I just want to make sure it stays fresh and relevant in my mind each day. The end goal is to build a few of my own web apps. I plan to write more about coding, and specifically the build process of this website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A big priority for me in 2020 is to stay on top of my personal finances and how I’m spending my money.&lt;/strong&gt; Since I no longer have to stress about paying rent or my credit card bill (and I’m grateful for that), it’s led me to be much more careless about how I’m spending my money. I want to be more conscious of how I’m spending and I want to save more aggressively. Here’s the spreadsheet I’m using to manage my budget and a guide on how to use it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the spreadsheet budget I made to make budgeting fun.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;google sheets budget template&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-things-that-happened&quot;&gt;Other Things That Happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fired-from-chili-piper&quot;&gt;Fired from Chili Piper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As excited as I was to join the Chili Piper team, it had an abrupt ending last year. After eight months, the CEO and Co-Founder let me go despite &lt;a href=&quot;/resume&quot;&gt;accomplishing a lot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I wanted to join Chili Piper in the first place was for the opportunity to work under &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/emilshour&quot;&gt;Emil Shour&lt;/a&gt;, a marketer I respect and wanted to learn from. Only a few months after I joined, he decided to leave for another company. That left me to take over all of marketing and report directly to the CEO. At the time, it was a welcomed change to take on more responsibility, but it’s where things went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The founder had a strong take on what good marketing is and it’s very different than what I believe it to be. &lt;strong&gt;He had a specific vision for what the company’s brand should be, which I believe reflected more the desires of a pet project than something our customers could best connect with.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, however, it was my job to scale the brand around the founder’s vision. But because of our different marketing philosophies, we butted heads in just about every strategic discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In short, I failed to be the brand advocate the company needed. I failed to persuasively make my case for a better way. I failed to admit I took on more responsibility that I could handle. I failed to keep my head down and my foot on the gas.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an important learning experience for my career and it had some great moments I’ll cherish. Lingering bitterness aside, I sincerely wish the founder, the team, and the company the best of luck and success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-chili-piper.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-chili-piper.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-chili-piper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coincidentally, writing this now while wearing my Chili Piper sweatshirt&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Coincidentally, writing this now while wearing my Chili Piper sweatshirt&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-a-better-idea-of-what-i-want-out-of-work&quot;&gt;Getting a better idea of what I want out of work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After suddenly exiting Chili Piper and the job I had before at ServiceTitan, I took a pause to think how my career was going. I used to be obsessed with my career and not in a &lt;em&gt;positive obsessed&lt;/em&gt; kind of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At ServiceTitan, I tried to analyze the political power structure of the office so I could cozy up to the right people who had influence. I craved recognition and would resent the people who got it. I was fixated on the next promotion, becoming a manager, and how much money I made &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;compared to my coworkers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I convinced myself I was better than them because I thought about work to this level, but it inevitably led to misery. To losing a game I had made up in my head.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is hard to write.&lt;/em&gt; It’s shocking I was like this and unaware of it at the time. I cringe when I imagine what my coworkers who saw through the charade thought of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But sometimes we need to get knocked out before we can be reborn.&lt;/strong&gt; The first punch was ServiceTitan’s CEO suggesting I move on to another company. The knockout blow was getting fired from Chili Piper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before applying to jobs, I took two months off to reflect on my behavior, what I did wrong, and what I’ll do differently next time. I thought about what I wanted out of life and how my career is not my everything, but just a piece of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I thought about all my previous coworkers. How much more I could have done to help them succeed.&lt;/strong&gt; How I seethed with resentment when they got praise instead of genuinely being happy for them when they completely deserved it. How I spent more of my time in envy, than being grateful for the opportunity I had and doing the actual good work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m still navigating through my redemption arc, but I’m already in a more tranquil state, trying to remember I’m in a good place instead of always wishing for the next thing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote has been on the background of my phone for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It is not the man who has too little, but the man who craves more, that is poor.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seneca&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keeping-busy-in-my-time-off&quot;&gt;Keeping busy in my time off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my break from work, I spent a lot of time brushing up on my HTML, CSS, and JS skills as a creative outlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I moved my blog off Medium to a static site&lt;/strong&gt; - essentially just hardcoded HTML and CSS files. I originally moved my blog from WordPress to Medium because I wanted to force myself to stop fiddling with the design. Now I went full on custom. &lt;em&gt;Hey, I had the time!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why I stopped blogging on Medium and moved to a static, self hosted blog.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;medium vs self hosted blog&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been taking &lt;a href=&quot;http://referrals.trhou.se/reggiepaquette&quot;&gt;online web development courses from Treehouse&lt;/a&gt; and completed their front end web development track. For 2020, I’m going to tackle their full stack javascript track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I “completed” a somewhat broken to-do app&lt;/strong&gt; that I started making two years ago. It works good enough for me to move on to the next project, but it’s special to me because it marks the completion of my first JS project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-to-do.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-to-do.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-to-do.png&quot; alt=&quot;A simple to-do app using Google’s Inbox design&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/regpaq/todo-material&quot;&gt;A simple to-do app using Google’s Inbox design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also &lt;a href=&quot;/resume&quot;&gt;wrote several case studies of work I’ve done&lt;/a&gt; at ServiceTitan and Chili Piper to build a portfolio. I’m not sure how effective it was at helping me land an interview or secure an offer, but it helped me get me some confidence back by remembering the good work I’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-job&quot;&gt;New job&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I had to start applying to jobs (because money). I had a better idea in mind of the type of company I wanted to work for and the people I wanted to work with so I took my time and was selective with the companies I applied to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a company called &lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/&quot;&gt;Revealbot&lt;/a&gt; on the remote job board &lt;a href=&quot;https://weworkremotely.com/&quot;&gt;WeWorkRemotely&lt;/a&gt; that stuck out to me for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They’re a B2B SaaS company offering a product for Facebook advertisers, a type of customer I know well because I spent around &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/resume&quot;&gt;$1.2MM in Facebook ads at ServiceTitan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Their website and product has a fantastic design which means the company values good design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I applied and did a preliminary project for them. &lt;strong&gt;I used part of my interviews with the co-founders to ask about their approach and philosophy to marketing and business, their values, and vision for the company to make sure it aligned with how I see things.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned they have a full-time designer in house and that’s how they’re able to make every design detail on the website and app consistent, look fantastic, and provide a good user experience. &lt;strong&gt;As a marketer, a good designer makes everything I do look 10x better, so this was a huge plus to have one in house.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part was the feedback I got from the project I did for them. They were impressed with how much I did in the time I had and the direction of my approach and strategy. &lt;strong&gt;For me, this solidified this was the right place for me, so I accepted their offer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now been 5 months and so far I’m really enjoying it. Recently, I was able to meet the team for the first time in person in Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;barcelona&quot;&gt;Barcelona&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new work held their annual retreat in Barcelona and I got to go. This marks my second year in a row going to Europe and I hope to go again in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-1.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-1.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A group of us went to Camp Nou&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A group of us went to Camp Nou&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What made this trip special was my girlfriend got to meet me there after spending a week with my coworkers.&lt;/strong&gt; It was her first time ever in Europe and we got to spend ten days in Barcelona together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-2.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-2.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The places we went in Barcelona, including the Picasso museum&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-3.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-3.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The places we went in Barcelona, including the Picasso museum&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-4.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-4.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The places we went in Barcelona, including the Picasso museum&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-9.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-9.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The places we went in Barcelona, including the Picasso museum&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The places we went in Barcelona, including the Picasso museum&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my second time going to Barcelona, but this was definitely my favorite time. &lt;strong&gt;The food was spectacular, but most of all, I’ll miss the beautiful architecture in the Gothic Quarter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-5.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-5.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The food we ate in Barcelona&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-6.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-6.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The food we ate in Barcelona&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-8.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-8.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The food we ate in Barcelona&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-barcelona-7.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-7.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2019-year-review-barcelona-7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The food we ate in Barcelona&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The food we ate in Barcelona&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;utah&quot;&gt;Utah&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My entire family has now moved to Utah, including my parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was the first time I went to visit them there. &lt;strong&gt;And as I get older, I recognize how important the relationships we have with family are, so it was great to spend a lot of time together and I’m planning to go again in 2020.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-utah.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-utah.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-utah.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;With my sister and her kids&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;With my sister and her kids&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-utah-2.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-utah-2.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-utah-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Love how everything is so green in Utah&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Love how everything is so green in Utah&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;san-francisco&quot;&gt;San Francisco&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Christmas, I went to visit my girlfriend’s family in the bay area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We went into the city one night for dinner in China town. It was my first time in San Francisco.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-san-francisco.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-san-francisco.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-san-francisco.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;San Francisco's China town at night&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;San Francisco's China town at night&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mexico&quot;&gt;Mexico&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My cousin got married this year and he invited me on a weekend trip to Mexico for his bachelor’s party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed in an Airbnb on the beach in Rosarito.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-mexico.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-mexico.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-mexico.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset in Rosarito, Mexico&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Sunset in Rosarito, Mexico&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t get to see or talk with him often, so it was a great opportunity to spend time with him and catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-mexico-2.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-mexico-2.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-mexico-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The tacos were delicious&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-mexico-3.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-mexico-3.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-mexico-3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The tacos were delicious&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The tacos were delicious&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bought-new-wheels&quot;&gt;Bought new wheels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I couldn’t end my yearly review without an update to my car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in my life, I bought my own set of aftermarket wheels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/2019-year-review-wheels.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-wheels.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/2019-year-review-wheels.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;19” BBS CHRs&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;19” BBS CHRs&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals-for-2020&quot;&gt;Goals for 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have thought about this more, but here are the main things I want to achieve in 2020:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;read one book a month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publish one article a week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complete the full stack javascript course from treehouse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create a new blog for all my marketing content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build my first complete web app people can reliably use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you made it this far, thank you for reading! I wish you a happy 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Goals From 2018</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2019-year-review.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2019-year-review.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2020-01-14T06:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T06:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes">&lt;p&gt;It’s unfortunate I Will Teach You To Be Rich has an off-putting title because it’s a fantastic introduction to personal finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi’s goal is to make personal finance exciting and rewarding, a stark contrast from the dry, guilt-inducing material you typically would associate to the personal finance space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He won’t blame you for spending lots of money on the things you enjoy; the same things most people would tell you is irresponsible to spend so much money on. Instead he encourages you to keep doing it unapologetically.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catch? Cut spending harder in other areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Spend extravagantly on the things you love, and cut costs mercilessly on the things you don’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--sml gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-cover.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-cover.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Buy I Will Teach You to be Rich on Amazon&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Will-Teach-You-Rich-Second-ebook/dp/B07GNXPP4P/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=e52afa785fde06ed59be0365987f513d&amp;amp;language=en_US&quot;&gt;Buy I Will Teach You to be Rich on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His refreshing approach to money comes from the idea that money shouldn’t rule our lives, and instead be a tool to help us enjoy life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he’ll encourage financial responsibility. Yes, he’ll advocate &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;using a budget&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, he’ll try to persuade you to start saving for retirement immediately. &lt;strong&gt;But what makes Ramit different is he shows you how to get this important stuff done and out of the way by automating it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes room to think about the fun stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you want to be rich?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does being rich mean to you?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you love to spend money on?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-this-summary-of-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich&quot;&gt;In This Summary of I Will Teach You to Be Rich&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to make credit cards work for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to set up the right bank accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to set up the right retirement accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;how to manage spending and enjoy it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to automate it all to be hands off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to invest intelligently with little work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to briefly cover his main recommendations from each topic, but because of his innovative approach to spending and budgeting and how practical it is, I’m going to spend a bit more time covering them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everybody teaches you how to save. Nobody talks about how to spend.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-make-credit-cards-work-for-you&quot;&gt;How to Make Credit Cards Work for You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section covers a lot about what a credit score is, how it’s calculated, and how credit cards work - all great for beginners. These are the notes I took for myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;always use a credit card over a debit card - builds credit, protects your bank account, accrue rewards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;always pay off credit cards in full each month - treat it like a debit card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up automatic payments so you never miss a payment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;keep old credit cards active by charging a small monthly cost to keep credit history&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;switch credit cards to a no annual fee card when it’s no longer your primary card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;request credit limit increases to improve your credit utilization rate (a factor of your credit score)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be aware of and use your rewards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can negotiate lower APRs and get late fees waived if you call and ask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The section ends with strategies to pay off credit card debt. It can be summarized by paying off debt with the highest intrest rate, but it’s more nuanced than that. If you do have credit card debt, this section is worth reading in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-set-up-the-right-bank-accounts&quot;&gt;How to Set Up The Right Bank Accounts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always surprised when I learn friends use traditional big banks for their accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They typically have the worse benefits, have minimum balance requirements for checking accounts, and a poor online banking experience. Ramit does a good job exposing these pitfalls by explaining how banks make money and the tactics they use to lure you in and make it hard to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a couple, but important takeaways on banks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;switch to an online bank (I recommend Capital One)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open a high-yield savings accounts (Capital One has them for free)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-set-up-the-right-retirement-accounts&quot;&gt;How to Set Up The Right Retirement Accounts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most important section so far, Ramit makes it simple to understand all the different types of retirement accounts and persuasively lays out why it’s so important to start saving for retirement now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He created five systematic steps for investing he calls “The Ladder of Personal Finance.”&lt;/strong&gt; When you finish the first step, or if it’s not an option, you proceed to the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;contribute 100% of what your employer matches in a company 401k&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pay off credit card or other debt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open a Roth IRA and contribute up to the annual maximum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;max out your 401k beyond or regardless of a company match&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;put the rest in a non retirement brokerage account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this section goes deep into each step of the ladder, explaining everything very clearly. I was finally able to understand the tax advantages of each different kind of retirement account and also why it was valuable to start now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-manage-spending-and-enjoy-it&quot;&gt;How to Manage Spending and Enjoy It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can learn to how to better manage your money he says you need to understand where you’re spending it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, he doesn’t recommend creating a budget where you track your finances down to the penny, but instead do what he calls a “Conscious Spending Plan,” which still sounds an awful lot like a budget, just a little more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious Spending is Ramit’s method of allowing yourself to spend money on the things that bring you joy, even if they seem frivolous to other people, or even frivolous to you. In exchange, you cut the spending elsewhere. This is how Ramit defines frugality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Frugality isn’t about cutting your spending on everything. That approach wouldn’t last two days. Frugality, quite simply, is about choosing the things you love enough to spend extravagantly on - and then cutting costs mercilessly on the things you don’t love.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-make-a-conscious-spending-plan&quot;&gt;How to make a conscious spending plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divide up where your take home pay goes into four major buckets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Money Buckets&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Percent of take home pay to allocate&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;I. Fixed Costs - Rent, utilities, debt, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50-60%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;II. Investments - 401(k), Rotha IRA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;III. Savings - Vacations, gifts, house down payment, unexpected expenses&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5-10%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IV. Guilt-free spending money - Dining out, drinking, movies, clothes, shoes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20-35%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed costs are expenses you have to pay every month no matter what. Once you total them up, subtract that amount from your take-home pay.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figure out how much you want to save for retirement in a 401k and or IRA and then deduct that amount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about what you want to save for in the short and long term. Calculate how much you need to save per month to reach that goal and then deduct that amount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After allocating money for fixed costs, retirement and investments, and savings, the rest is for guilt-free spending.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;I made a budget template on Google Sheets&lt;/a&gt; based on Ramit’s Conscious Spending Plan that can you help do all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the spreadsheet budget I made to make budgeting fun.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;google sheets budget template&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tips-to-optimize-your-conscious-spending-plan&quot;&gt;Tips to optimize your Conscious Spending Plan:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;always try to cut fixed costs and guilt-free spending before cutting how much you allocate to investing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;focus on big wins to cut spending, not small ones like buying generic brands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you’re more likely to stick to a new budget by making a gradual change than a dramatic one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;actually write out tangible savings goals to increase motivation to achieve them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-envelope-system-to-target-big-wins&quot;&gt;Use the “envelope system” to target big wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The envelope system is essentially a second bucket system for your guilt-free spending. You allocate a certain amount of your guilt-free spending to certain categories (envelopes) and once you spend all the money in that envelope, that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s much easier to figure out how much money you should put into each envelope by looking at your last three months of spending in each category, averaging them out, and then setting an achievable goal for each one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good objective to try and meet your spending goal for each category, but you can dip into other envelopes if you need to. The most important thing is keeping your total spending below what you have for guilt-free spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;activity-based-envelopes&quot;&gt;Activity based envelopes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One trick Ramit mentions that I’ve used in the past is instead of using the general categories that credit card companies and banks typically use, create categories more personal to you and &lt;em&gt;around events&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I have used these categories in the past:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;eating out alone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coffee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alcohol for home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;going out with friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this requires a manual categorization of each expense, it will highglight the driving activities behind your spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to keep track of spending is to always use a credit card (as long as your responsible) so you can just pull up your account to enter expenses into your budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The best part about setting up a strategic budget is that it guides your decisions, letting you say no much more easily - ‘Sorry, it’s not in my plan this month.’ - and freeing you up to enjoy what you do spend on. This is guilt-free spending at its best.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-automate-it-all-to-be-hands-off&quot;&gt;How to Automate It All to be Hands Off&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re contributing to a 401k, that’s probably already automated by your employer before even receiving your paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then your paycheck gets deposited into your checking account and from there you set up a monthly automatic transfer to your other retirement and savings accounts. &lt;strong&gt;By transferring the money automatically right after you get paid, you’re paying yourself first, not spending first and saving what’s left over.&lt;/strong&gt; That’s why the money left over to spend is guilt-free spending money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what the flow looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/always-pay-yourself-first-ramit-sethi-teach-you-to-be-rich.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/always-pay-yourself-first-ramit-sethi-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/always-pay-yourself-first-ramit-sethi-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;How to automate your finances. Automatically transfer to savings first. Your percentage allocation may differ.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;How to automate your finances. Automatically transfer to savings first. Your percentage allocation may differ.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“By setting up an automatic payment plan you actually make it difficult to stop the contributions to your retirement account! Not because you can’t - you can adjust your system any time - but because you’re lazy and you won’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More automation tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up all bills to be paid by credit card automatically&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if a bill (like rent) can’t be paid by card, set up auto bill pay to have your bank automtically send a check on your behalf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up your credit card bill to be paid automatically from your checking account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set a reminder in the middle of the month to check how you much you’ve spent compared to what you’ve allocated for guilt-free spending&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-invest-intelligently-with-little-work&quot;&gt;How to Invest Intelligently with Little Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section of &lt;em&gt;I Will Teach You to be Rich&lt;/em&gt;, Ramit walks us through how to invest the money in your 401ks and IRAs. It’s a good introduction to the foundational topics of investing that can be summed up in a few points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be less risk averse when you’re younger, more risk averse when older&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hardly anyone beats the market, even full-time investors so it’s not worth trying to pick the right stocks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t invest in any funds with high fees, like mutual funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;it’s better long term to invest in low-fee index funds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some diversification is good, just remember to rebalance your ratios annually&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;invest in lifecycle funds to be completely hands off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramit goes into more details on each one of these here and explains why he gives the advice he does. It’s solid financial advice and worth reading more into if you’re fresh to personal finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-personal-finance-tips&quot;&gt;Final Personal Finance Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;try and invest as much as you can, as early as you can&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;if your income increases, look to increase how much you allocate to savings first&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ignore the noise of the financial industry, it can cause you to get emotional and make bad decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t worry about tricks to avoid taxes or seeing a financial advisor until your investments total $100k+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;create an emergency fund to protect against job loss or unexpected, expensive bills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Unlike other people, who worry about money (because they never learned how it works), you get to focus on the things you love.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">It’s unfortunate I Will Teach You To Be Rich has an off-putting title because it’s a fantastic introduction to personal finance.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Free Will Doesn’t Exist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/free-will-doesnt-exist" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Will Doesn’t Exist" /><published>2020-01-06T06:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-06T06:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/free-will-doesnt-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/free-will-doesnt-exist">&lt;p&gt;It seems we have control of our actions. It seems we make our own choices. It seems we choose our beliefs. It seems we can think about what we want, when we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems everything we do is of our own free will and this all seems quite obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there does exist the opposite belief that we don’t have free will to choose all those things ourselves and rather our thoughts, beliefs, choices, and actions are determined only by a result of previous causes that could not have resulted in any other outcome. &lt;strong&gt;This philosophical belief is called determinism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about determinism from Sam Harris and my first reaction was &lt;em&gt;no way that’s even close to being right, of course we have free will&lt;/em&gt;. But after listening to his arguments and doing my own research on determinism, I can’t help but be convinced it’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This realization had such a profound effect on me it has fundamentally changed the way I think about myself, other people, and the world around me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is an examination into determinism versus free will, thought exercises to illustrate the lack of free will in our thoughts, beliefs, choices, and actions, and finally the implications of it in our daily lives and society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;free-will-vs-determinism&quot;&gt;Free Will vs Determinism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Determinism#History&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Determinism&lt;/a&gt; is the philosophical belief that any thought you have, belief you uphold, choice you make, and action you take is determined by a chain of previous causes that could not be otherwise because of those causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_will&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Free will&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, is the belief we have the unimpeded ability to control our thoughts, choose our beliefs, make choices, and take actions between different possible options. &lt;strong&gt;The key question that differentiates determinism and free will is &lt;em&gt;are you capable to have done otherwise?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/w8Q6CWv7IXo?t=8106&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;great thought exercise on the Joe Rogan Experience&lt;/a&gt; to illustrate the difference. It goes like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of a city - any city in the world. &lt;em&gt;Now say it out loud.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have chosen any of the hundreds of cities you know the name of, &lt;em&gt;but you chose that one.&lt;/em&gt; Some other cities might have run through your head right before you answered, but there were hundreds that didn’t even occur to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the hundreds of possible options, this seems like an example of one of the freest choices you can make. But if we go back in time right to the moment where I first asked you to say the city out loud, &lt;em&gt;could you have chosen a different city?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you examine your thought process leading to your city of choice, you’ll find reasons that caused you to choose that city - fond memories, something you saw today, or simply how you were feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a universe with free will, you’d be capable of using those inputs to choose one city and you could have easily chosen a different city. But in a deterministic universe, we could go back 1,000 times right to the start of this thought exercise and you’d go through that same exact thought process and you’d choose that same city every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s the difference between free will and determinism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arguments-for-determinism&quot;&gt;Arguments for Determinism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are thought exercises to reveal how much of who we are, our thoughts, beliefs, choices, and actions are the product of causes rather than choices from our own free will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-didnt-choose-our-genetics-or-upbringing&quot;&gt;We didn’t choose our genetics or upbringing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, we’re alive. And it wasn’t by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t get to choose the country or city we were born and raised in. We didn’t choose the culture. We didn’t choose the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t get to choose our genetic code, how tall we’d become, how attractive or unattractive we are, the sound of our voice, the color of our skin, the language we speak, our natural talents, our gender or sex, or the diseases we’re susceptible to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t get to choose our parents, how much or how little money they had to raise us with, their relationship between each other, the religion, values, and politics they ingrained in us, or how much or how little they pushed us in sports, music, or academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How our parents raised us (or the people who did), heavily influence our identity, character, values, beliefs, and future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you’re a parent, you already know this is true or you wouldn’t have read all those books or watched all those videos on how to become a great parent. You wouldn’t have tried as hard as you did to create the best possible life for your children if you knew it wouldn’t make a difference.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to think about your upbringing. How much has it made you who you are today? How much of that was your choice? How much of that was determined and out of your control?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-choose-our-own-thoughts&quot;&gt;We don’t choose our own thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the part of us that feels closest to our sense of free will, our thoughts seem to be the element we have complete control of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we are in complete control of our thoughts, &lt;strong&gt;why do we struggle with staying focused and distractions? It’s not that we choose to be distracted. It happens “against our will” because we don’t have the control to choose what we think about.&lt;/strong&gt; If you’ve ever practiced meditation, you already know how frequently random thoughts surface themselves, completely outside of our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only do we not choose what and when we think about things, we don’t choose our opinion of things either. &lt;strong&gt;If we did have free will and complete control of choosing our opinions, marketing and advertising wouldn’t be a multi billion dollar industry fighting for our attention,&lt;/strong&gt; we wouldn’t be the average of the five people we surround ourselves with, &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;social media wouldn’t affect our mental health&lt;/a&gt;, and good and bad influences wouldn’t make a difference to our character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few of the many things that influence every thought and opinion we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we don’t choose the things we think about, when we think about them, and our opinions of them, how can we possibly ever have a thought or opinion formed purely from our choice alone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-choose-our-own-beliefs&quot;&gt;We don’t choose our own beliefs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to think of a strong belief you have, such as a religious belief or political position. What is your best reason for believing your belief or position is right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever your best reason was, it wasn’t &lt;em&gt;because I chose to believe it,&lt;/em&gt; was it? &lt;strong&gt;That’s because we don’t choose our beliefs. We’re convinced of them. It’s only until we’re convinced of a belief that we can uphold that belief with conviction.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate this is true, see if you’re capable of choosing to believe the opposite view of the belief or position you were just thinking of. Could you do it? If you believe the Earth is a sphere, can you choose to believe right now, with complete conviction, that it’s flat? The reason why you can’t is because you’ve already been presented with good reasons why it’s a sphere and good reasons why it’s not flat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need good reasons to believe something, and making a choice to believe something is never a good enough reason for a strong belief to form.&lt;/strong&gt; So what is a good enough reason?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To our detriment, a good enough reason is anything that sounds more convincing to us than what we knew before and it’s here wherein lies the problem. We can be convinced to uphold false beliefs for objectively bad reasons. These bad, but convincing, reasons are often &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourlogicalfallacyis.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;logical fallacies&lt;/a&gt; strengthened through &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourbias.is/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt;. And it’s why some people do believe the Earth is flat with complete conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And consider for a moment why we even have the beliefs we do in the first place. Beliefs are pushed onto us from every angle since birth from our parents, teachers and textbooks, church and church leaders, community and culture, the news media, and on and on. &lt;strong&gt;Then we have social media that exacerbates the problem by isolating us into echo chambers that feed into our confirmation bias.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, because we don’t choose which beliefs are up for consideration in the first place and we can’t choose which to uphold, it’s clear our beliefs are determined, not chosen by our own free will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-make-our-own-choices&quot;&gt;We don’t make our own choices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris’s ‘pick a city’ thought exercise is a demonstration of how we use previous causes to make a choice. Although this is an example of one of the freest choices you can make, it is an inconsequential choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely life’s more consequential choices where we spend weeks reflecting and deliberating over the pros and cons of that choice has to be an example of using free will to make a choice, right? Let’s explore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you’re deciding which college to go to for your bachelor’s degree. The pros and cons you might be deliberating over are the schools’ prestiges, quality of major programs, how much fun you’ll have, and where your parents want you to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your genetics, upbringing, thoughts, opinions, and beliefs will determine your final assessment for each of these considerations. &lt;strong&gt;These are the tools we use to make decisions and if our decision making tools are determined, then the choices we end up making from them are determined.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, neither the time it takes to make a choice or the level of consequence in a choice’s outcome changes the fact that our choices are determined. We’re still capable of making choices in a deterministic universe, but we are never capable of choosing something else than what we do end up choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Virtue is a Better Goal Than Legacy&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The Stoics saw virtue as life&amp;#39;s highest objective. I&amp;#39;m starting to see why.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/moral-virtue-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/moral-virtue-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/moral-virtue-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/moral-virtue-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Virtue is its own reward&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-control-our-own-actions&quot;&gt;We don’t control our own actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions can occur either unconsciously or consciously. Unconscious actions like scratching an itch, sighing, or bouncing your leg up and down while sitting are actions that occur, without a doubt, from a cause, not by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conscious actions require a choice to act. And if choices are determined, then actions are determined.&lt;/strong&gt; We can even make a choice to act and still fail to complete that act because causes are more powerful than our choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we don’t have complete control of our actions or body. If we did, we wouldn’t choose to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;break a bad habit&lt;/a&gt; and fail. We wouldn’t choose to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;start a good habit&lt;/a&gt; and fail. We wouldn’t need to read a &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;book on habits&lt;/a&gt; at all. If we had free will and control of our actions, we could simply choose to do something and do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we don’t have control of our actions because we don’t have control of our choices. We don’t have control of our choices because we don’t have control of our beliefs. We don’t have control of our beliefs because we don’t have control of our thoughts, opinions, genetics, or how we were raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/atomic-habits-summary-review-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/atomic-habits-summary-review-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-the-lack-of-free-will-matter&quot;&gt;Does the Lack of Free Will Matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining whether we have free will or not matters because if we do have free will, that means we should have full, moral responsibility for our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t have free will, how much moral responsibility should we bear for actions we could not have done otherwise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Admitting that free will is an illusion actually does have some important consequences. They’re not the kind of consequences that people worry about. It’s not that you have no basis to be a better person or to change your life or to make efforts to improve yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“That all remains intact, but it does change our ethical views of good and evil in some important ways.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sam Harris, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/w8Q6CWv7IXo?t=8319&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joe Rogan Experience #543 2:18:39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let’s look at what the lack of free will means for our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-be-too-hard-on-yourself&quot;&gt;Don’t be too hard on yourself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be disappointed with the way you look, how much money you make, or how many followers you have. You might &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;compare yourself to others&lt;/a&gt; and be disappointed with how ordinary or inadequate you are compared to them. I’ve been there and I think we’ve all been there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By understanding that we don’t have control over the causes that determine our looks, income, popularity, or status, it becomes possible to accept who we are and be grateful for what we have.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Stop Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why these comparisons don&amp;#39;t make sense and how it improved my mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others.png&quot; alt=&quot;stop comparing yourself to others&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most empowering tenets of Stoicism and why I’ve fully embraced its philosophy into my life is about identifying and separating the things that are up to us from what’s not. If something is not up to us and is out of our control, then we shouldn’t get angry, scared, or grieve about it because there’s nothing we could have done to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When a slave runs away from his master, we call him a fugitive slave. But the law of nature is a master too, and to break it is to become a fugitive.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“To feel grief, anger, or fear is to try to escape from something decreed by the ruler of all things, now or in the past or in the future. And that ruler is law [fate], which governs what happens to each of us. To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive — a fugitive from justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 10.25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infusing determinism and Stoicism into my perspective has shown me that getting angry, sad, and frustrated with who and where I am today would be denying that my previous causes could not have been anything else than what they were.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, these negative emotions are unnecessary. All they do is bring extra harm for no rational reason. Identifying the things that are outside of my control has &lt;a href=&quot;/virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;ultimately brought tranquility into my life.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-good-to-other-people&quot;&gt;Be good to other people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just as you recognize the things you can’t control about yourself, it’s just as powerful to recognize other people are the way they are and do the things they do because of causes outside of their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So think about that the next time your significant other, a family member, friend, or coworker does something you find weird or wrong. It doesn’t seem weird or wrong to them because of their previous causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel affection for people even when they make mistakes is uniquely human. You can do it, if you simply recognize: that they’re human too, that they act out of ignorance, against their will, and that you’ll both be dead before long. And, above all, that they haven’t really hurt you. They haven’t diminished your ability to choose [how to react].”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you have objectively good reasons for thinking whatever they’re doing is weird or wrong, they may just not know better and that’s okay. If you’re able to, try and steer them in the right direction. &lt;strong&gt;The worst thing you can do for your relationship and your own well-being, is pass blame.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If it’s in your control, why do you do it? If it’s in someone else’s, then who are you blaming? Atoms? The gods? Stupid either way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Blame no one. Set people straight, if you can. If not, just repair the damage. And suppose you can’t do that either. Then where does blaming people get you?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 8.17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeing the universe, yourself, and other people through a lens of determinism and Stoicism adds a priceless attribute to your character: empathy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2.png&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-more-aware-of-what-influences-you&quot;&gt;Be more aware of what influences you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally everything and everyone around us is influencing our thoughts, beliefs, and behavior in every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pay attention to your thoughts and emotions throughout the day. Try to understand what made you think and feel that way.&lt;/em&gt; By being able to identify the cause, we can cut out the negative influences and increase the positive ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius often draws a comparison between being unaware of your influences to “being jerked like a puppet by our own impulses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s time you realized that you have something in you more powerful and miraculous than the things that affect you and make you dance like a puppet.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“What’s in my thoughts at this moment? Fear? Jealousy? Desire? Feelings like that?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 12.19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “power” he’s referring to is our ability to be aware of these influences and how we choose to react to them. This is a skill that takes practice. Meditation is the most popular method to get better at it, but I’ve found &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;daily journaling&lt;/a&gt; to work better for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly realized social media and video games were some of my biggest negative influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the expense of losing touch with some friends, I deleted Snapchat and Instagram because it made me &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;care too much about what other people think of me&lt;/a&gt;, envy the lives other people live and the things they have, and lose gratitude for who I am and what I have in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sold my Playstation because all I wanted to do was game when I got off work. I realized it was an unproductive use of time and losing online games would leave me annoyed and frustrated (FIFA players understand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;23 Stoic Journal Prompts for Self-Development&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Inspired by the journal method of Marcus Aurelius, these journal prompts will help you improve your character, acquire tranquility, and be more of a Stoic.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stoic-journal-topics-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stoic-journal-topics-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics-250.jpeg 250w,
                                /assets/images/stoic-journal-topics-572.jpeg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;stoic journal topics&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-on-politics-and-society&quot;&gt;Impact on politics and society&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This perspective of empathy through determinism and Stoicism can be extended to people who live on the opposite side of the globe, who we don’t understand, and who society deems bad. Through practicing this perspective, it’s possible to develop empathy for these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, people in jail for committing crimes have previous causes that led them to do so, whether those crimes are theft, drug related, or assault. While determinism doesn’t mean our society must rid all fault and responsibility from those who commit crimes, but maybe we should emphasize an approach of rehabilitation more than punishment in our criminal justice system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe we should be more empathetic to people who were born in a third world country through no choice of their own. Maybe we should be more empathetic to people who have different religious beliefs and political positions due to causes outside of their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although some critics say there isn’t much of a practical difference between free will and the illusion of it, there are clear implications to the understanding of ourselves, other people, and the world around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge yourself to be aware of the influences on your thoughts, beliefs, and behavior. Challenge yourself to accept and be grateful for who you are, what you have, and what you’ve accomplished. Challenge yourself to feel affection for other people even when they make mistakes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">It seems we have control of our actions. It seems we make our own choices. It seems we choose our beliefs. It seems we can think about what we want, when we want.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/sam-harris-free-will.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/sam-harris-free-will.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtue is a Better Goal Than Legacy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/virtue-is-its-own-reward" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtue is a Better Goal Than Legacy" /><published>2019-11-29T06:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-11-29T06:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/virtue-is-its-own-reward</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/virtue-is-its-own-reward">&lt;p&gt;Before I got &lt;a href=&quot;/philosophy&quot;&gt;interested in philosophy&lt;/a&gt;, I used to believe the amount of impact one has on the world was the highest objective we should aim to achieve in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or in other words, build the biggest legacy. &lt;strong&gt;And if my life ended without a legacy, if there wasn’t a large subset of people who remembered me or knew who I was even just 50 years after I died, my life was… well meaningless.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a demoralizing point-of-view, but I couldn’t reason or justify a better measurement for meaning. I’d rather accept a harsh reality as true than keep my head in the sand and believe a false reality to feel better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I was conflicted when reading how strong &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt; and the Stoics believed accepting fate and doing good as the highest objective he strived to achieve in life. This is one of my favorite Aurelius quotes about this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No matter what anyone says or does, my task is to be good. Like gold or emerald or purple repeating to itself, “No matter what anyone says or does, my task is to be emerald, my color undiminished.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this quote because he says his task is to be good, like an emerald’s task is to be emerald in color. An emerald can’t be anything but emerald. And Aurelius strives to be good to his core so he couldn’t do anything but good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I didn’t understand how striving to achieve virtue could lead to a meaningful life. But then I understood Aurelius didn’t seek to achieve meaning. &lt;strong&gt;Rather, he sought to achieve goodness.&lt;/strong&gt; So what did Aurelius know about meaning to disregard it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;according-to-marcus-aurelius-life-and-legacy-are-trivial-and-meaningless&quot;&gt;According to Marcus Aurelius, Life and Legacy are Trivial and Meaningless&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s my understanding that Aurelius never believed in a “meaningful” life. In one meditation, he equated the entirety of life to a rock being thrown in the air and coming back down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A rock thrown in the air. It loses nothing by coming down, gained nothing by going up.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another, he wrote about exercising awareness in the moment, not to appreciate it, but to realize it’s not much to miss out on when he dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Stop whatever you’re doing for a moment and ask yourself: Am I afraid of death because I won’t be able to do this anymore?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 10.29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have the impression Aurelius believed life was something that had to be done and put up with as fate demanded. Why? Because death scared him and he wanted to believe he wouldn’t be missing out on anything when he died to better cope with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Human lives are brief and trivial. Yesterday a blob of semen; tomorrow embalming fluid, ash.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“To pass through this brief life as nature demands. To give it up without complaint.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 4.48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-aurelius-had-to-say-about-legacy-and-fame&quot;&gt;What Aurelius had to say about legacy and fame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacies are born out of fame and Aurelius had a disdain for it for two reasons. If you’re working towards achieving fame, it means you care too much about what other people think of you. And second, fame doesn’t last long so it’s pointless to pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…look at how soon we’re all forgotten. The abyss of endless time that swallows it all. The emptiness of all those applauding hands. The people who praise us - how capricious they are, how arbitrary. And the tiny region in which it all takes place. The whole earth a point in space…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 4.3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter if people remember you 50 years after death or 200, you will still be forgotten. Think about how many people you know the names of who were alive 200 years ago in 1819. There was a billion people alive in the world then. Can you name more than five?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“So many who were remembered already forgotten, and those who remembered them long gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2.png&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-criticisms-of-marcus-aureliuss-point-of-view&quot;&gt;My Criticisms of Marcus Aurelius’s Point-of-View&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my interpretation of Aurelius’s beliefs, legacy, fame, and being remembered is meaningless. And life itself is void of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only criticism is you can take two people, and objectively determine which had more impact, and thus more meaning. For example, taken to the extreme, it’s easy to identify who had more impact and meant more to society: Steve Jobs vs the average joe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to point out that impact could be positive or negative. For example, Martin Luther King Jr vs Osama Bin Laden. Both had great impact on society, but in opposite directions. If, for sake of argument, we quantified their impact as equal would their meaning be equal? Does meaning take into account positive vs negative impact? I think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius and the Stoics believed being virtuous and doing good as the highest objective. &lt;strong&gt;Then, according to Stoicism, wouldn’t someone who does more good than another have both more impact and more meaning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stoics argued that the only thing in our control is our mind. And it’s rare for people to make an impact at the level of Jobs or MLK. If all it took to make a high impact was desire and tenacity, there would be a lot more people making that high of an impact. But there are lot of factors outside of our control, which makes the highest level of achievement impossible for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Therefore, while there may be objective measures to determine if a life is more impactful or meaningful than another, it’s fruitless to pursue it and make it your highest objective. Instead, the Stoics argue it’s best to make virtue and doing good the highest objective, which is entirely within our control. I’m beginning to understand why.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Stop Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why these comparisons don&amp;#39;t make sense and how it improved my mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others.png&quot; alt=&quot;stop comparing yourself to others&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-how-virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;Understanding How Virtue is Its Own Reward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://dailystoic.com/4-stoic-virtues/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ryan Holiday puts it&lt;/a&gt;, “A Stoic believes they don’t control the world around them, only how they respond — and that they must always respond with courage, temperance, wisdom, and justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the four core virtues of Stoicism. Aurelius believed &lt;strong&gt;justice&lt;/strong&gt; was the most important, because acting with justice is doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“And a commitment to justice in your own acts. Which means: thought and action resulting in the common good. What you were born to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I completed &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt; for the first time two years ago. Since then, I’ve been adopting a Stoic mindset and I’ve seen myself undergo a dramatic transformation. Acting with justice and virtue has given me a new level of patience and resilience, improved my relationships, and fostered an affection for all people. It has redirected my ambition from building a legacy and longing for recognition to a mission of doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started writing out how acting with justice has helped me in all these ways, but I can’t explain it better than Marcus Aurelius himself. Here are some of my favorite meditations on doing good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel affection for people even when they make mistakes is uniquely human. You can do it, if you simply recognize: that they’re human too, that they act out of ignorance, against their will, and that you’ll both be dead before long. And, above all, that they haven’t really hurt you. They haven’t diminished your ability to choose.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When people injure you, ask yourself what good or harm they thought would come of it. If you understand that, you’ll feel sympathy rather than outrage or anger. Your sense of good and evil may be the same as theirs, or near it, in which case you have to excuse them. Or your sense of good and evil may differ from theirs. In which case they’re misguided and deserve your compassion. Is that so hard?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To do harm is to do yourself harm. To do an injustice is to do yourself an injustice - it degrades you.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When faced with people’s bad behavior, turn around ask when &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; have acted like that. When you saw money as good, or pleasure, or social position. Your anger will subside as soon as you recognize that they acted under compulsion (what else could they do?)…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 10.30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“That you don’t know for sure it &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; a mistake. A lot of things are means to some other end. You have to know an awful lot before you can judge other people’s actions with real understanding.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 11.18.v&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you believe doing good as the highest objective, you feel good when you do it. &lt;strong&gt;Acting with justice and virtue is its own reward because acting virtuously is synonymous with doing good to others and preserving your integrity. With self fulfillment and happiness as a bonus.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What is the goal of virtue, after all, except a life that flows smoothly?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Epictetus, Book I, 108&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with one last meditation that sums up Aurelius’s and the Stoics point-of-view and reason for doing good as the highest objective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…And how does it injure you anyway? You’ll find that none of the people you’re upset about has done anything that could do damage to your mind. But that’s all that “harm” or “injury” could mean. Yes, boorish people do boorish things. What’s strange or unheard of about that? Isn’t it yourself you should reproach - for not anticipating that they’d act this way? The logos gave you the means to see it - that a person would act a given way - but you paid no attention. And now you’re astonished that he’s gone and done it. So when you call someone “untrustworthy” or “ungrateful,” turn the reproach on yourself. It was you who did wrong. By assuming that someone with those traits deserved your trust. Or by doing them a favor and expecting something in return, instead of looking to the action itself for your reward. What else did you expect from helping someone out? Isn’t it enough that you’ve done what your nature demands? You want a salary for it, too? As if your eyes expected a reward for seeing, or your feet for walking. That’s what they were made for. By doing what they were designed to do, they’re performing their function. Whereas humans were made to help others. And when we do help others - or help them to do something - we’re doing what we were designed for. We perform our function.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 9.42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Before I got interested in philosophy, I used to believe the amount of impact one has on the world was the highest objective we should aim to achieve in life.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>