<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-23T07:36:53-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">regpaq</title><subtitle>B2B Marketer. Avid reader &amp; writer.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stop Comparing Yourself to Others — Use This Benchmark Instead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop Comparing Yourself to Others — Use This Benchmark Instead" /><published>2019-02-13T12:11:11-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T12:11:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others">&lt;p&gt;The frequently given advice to not compare yourself with others and only to who you were yesterday never quite satisfied me. It still left a lot of questions unanswered and I recently discovered on Reddit many other people feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/productivity/comments/ao04vn/stop_comparing_yourself_to_others_and_start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent post on r/productivity&lt;/a&gt;, there were some top comments refuting this advice with how they actually like to use jealousy, greed, and wanting to be better than other people as motivation to achieve “greatness.” Not only is comparing yourself to others the wrong way to achieve true greatness, so is comparing yourself to who you were yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being better than who you were yesterday should be the bare minimum you strive for, because it doesn’t allow you to achieve what you’re fully capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it doesn’t confirm you’re on the right path to begin with. On its own, “compare yourself to who you were yesterday” is only feel-good advice that has very little practical usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why there’s some rationality behind why we tend to compare ourselves to others. You can see in your physical or digital circle who the low achievers are and who the high achievers are — giving you the missing benchmark of effort and success. But in the end, it’s a terrible benchmark that will have devastating effects on your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparing-yourself-to-others-leads-you-to-falsepaths&quot;&gt;Comparing Yourself to Others Leads You to False Paths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, I was introduced to and befriended a very successful guy who day traded for a living. I didn’t know anything about the world of finance, but seeing the success he had and hearing how much he would make in any given day was exhilarating. &lt;strong&gt;As time went on, my benchmark for effort and success expanded to include his. I began to compare what I had achieved to him. “Success” now meant nothing short of what he had achieved.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told myself I needed to do everything I could to achieve that level of success. I decided to learn how to be a day trader and I went so far as to sell my dream car to get the cash to do it. With studying and his mentorship, I started to make a few hundred dollars per week. As my confidence and greed grew, I became less risk-averse. &lt;strong&gt;Half a year later, my losses totaled close to $10k.&lt;/strong&gt; I closed my account and threw my dreams of riches and day trading out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started to compare myself to him, and what I had to what he had, it led me to abandon my path and join the path that made him successful. I never had any prior interest in stocks or studied the financial markets. I was just chasing the money and that led to disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Using others as a benchmark for success can lead to conformity — it can take you away from what you’re happy and good at doing and put you on a false path — chasing money, status, or attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a never ending trap. There will always be someone to compare yourself to with more money, more status, and more fame that will lead you off your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everyone gets one life. Yours is almost used up, and instead of treating yourself with respect, you have entrusted your own happiness to the souls of others.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius, Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-fate-and-luck-always-play-a-significant-role-in-someones-success&quot;&gt;Understand Fate and Luck Always Play a Significant Role in Someone’s Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us is a completely unique individual with a unique genetic makeup. We’re all raised by different people, with different values, and in different environments — all of which significantly impact our character and what we do in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will shout, “you can do anything you set your mind to” or “you just need to work harder” or “you’re not sacrificing enough.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/u/65e0b0f45be5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nat Eliason&lt;/a&gt; made some noise when he called out Gary Vaynerchuk as an example of someone who does this in a piece he wrote titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@nateliason/no-more-struggle-porn-202153a01108&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;No More “Struggle Porn.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While we do need to have ruthless discipline to reach our greatest potential, we cannot ignore the limits imposed on us by the cards we’re dealt or we will forever be dissatisfied with who we are and what we’ve accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another reason why it doesn’t make sense to compare ourselves to others: luck. &lt;strong&gt;No one’s success is ever only down to luck, but we can’t ignore the role luck plays in success as an “x” factor — it’s unmanageable and unpredictable.&lt;/strong&gt; The only thing in your control is to continually put yourself in positions to catch lucky breaks. And remember: luck is not distributed evenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Q&amp;amp;A with White House interns, President Obama gave advice on the subject luck has with success and what to focus on instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A lot of times, it’s just happenstance. Or things work out. But being useful? And having a satisfying life? And making a contribution? That is entirely within your control. Orient yourself towards having an impact and making a difference. And you will and you’ll be happy doing it.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— President Barack Obama&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instead-of-comparing-yourself-to-others-or-who-you-were-yesterday-find-your-truepath&quot;&gt;Instead of Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday, Find Your True Path&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity is worthless if you’re on a false path. Your goal and motivation shouldn’t be about just being the best or better than the people in your circles, but creating something useful that can make a difference in peoples’ lives and your community. This is the truest benchmark for success and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People who labor all their lives but have no purpose to direct every thought and impulse toward are wasting their time — even when hard at work.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius, Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your true path is doing what you were made for — what you feel you have an inclination and natural ability for. This inclination is a reflection of your unique genetic code, deep underlying preferences for particular activities or forms of expression. When you find your true path, you’ll be less inclined to compare your success with someone else. &lt;strong&gt;You will quickly realize their path isn’t a good fit for you.&lt;/strong&gt; And you won’t be as inclined to envy their money, attention, or whatever, because craving those things is a false path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the end, the money and success that truly last come not to those who focus on such things as goals, but rather to those who focus on mastery and fulfilling their Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;Robert Greene, Mastery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need to compare yourself to others is restrained when you’re happy and comfortable with who you are, which comes from being on your true path and working on your Life’s Task. You will no longer envy other peoples’ success and happiness, and you will instead be laser-focused on your own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Don’t aim at success — the more you aim at it and make it a target, the more you are going to miss it. For success, like happiness, cannot be pursued; it must ensue, and it only does so as the unintended side-effect of one’s dedication to a cause greater than oneself…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— Viktor Frankl, Man’s Search for Meaning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can’t be disciplined, happy, and confident all the time. I’ve made journaling a daily habit of mine to give myself the opportunity to reflect on and ground my thoughts. It’s an exercise that has helped me live a more level-headed and purposeful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Inspired by the journal method of Marcus Aurelius.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;stoic journal topics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ignoring what goes on in other people’s souls — no one ever came to grief that way. But if you won’t keep track of what your own soul’s doing, how you can you not be unhappy?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius, Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing yourself to others is a recipe for disaster. Comparing yourself to who you were yesterday is a recipe for passivity. Life is not about being better than other people. It’s not about achieving more than people in our circles. &lt;strong&gt;Life is about being useful to others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">The frequently given advice to not compare yourself with others and only to who you were yesterday never quite satisfied me. It still left a lot of questions unanswered and I recently discovered on Reddit many other people feel the same way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development" /><published>2019-02-07T06:52:48-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T06:52:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics">&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, often called the philosopher emperor, is a famous stoic philosopher and known as the last good emperor of Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of his journal entries to himself have been recovered and curated into a single book title Meditations, which is widely recognized as one of the most influential pieces of stoic philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of journaling allowed Marcus Aurelius, and can allow us today, to think more clearly and live a more virtuous life. The following journal topics can help guide your journaling practice toward stoic thought exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-gratitude&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Gratitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a moment to reflect on the value added to your life by the people around you will help you appreciate them and the relationship you have with them, which in turn could spark behavior that strengthens those relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People to consider: significant other, family, friends, coworkers, and people who’ve impacted your life in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value has [person] added to my life? What wisdom, achievements, or fortunate events of mine can I give them some credit for?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value do I (or can I) add to [person’s] life in return?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does [person] affect and influence my life decisions, feelings, and behavior?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What characteristics does [person] have that I admire?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are my best characteristics who influenced me to develop them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also reflect on your achievements, major events, and material things in your life to establish gratitude for you’ve done and what you have, which will suppress feelings of unhappiness and cravings for new and better things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is an accomplishment I’m very proud of? Why am I proud of it? What can I do to do more things like that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is one of my most cherished memories and why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of an item in your possession you want to upgrade. Is your current item functioning well enough? What do you appreciate about it? What sustained value will an upgrade add to your life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at what you have and the things you value most. How much would you crave them if you didn’t have them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-to-suppress-negative-thoughts&quot;&gt;Journal Topics to Suppress Negative Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negative and low value thoughts are fuel for chaos, passivity, and unhappiness. These topics can help control your negative thoughts by thinking through them rationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Like seeing roasted meat and other dishes in front of you and suddenly realizing: This is a dead fish. A dead bird. A dead pig. Or that this noble vintage is grape juice,… Perceptions like that — latching onto things and piercing through them, so we see what they really are. That’s what we need to do all the time… to lay them bare and see how pointless they are…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius, Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of an item you craved to have and eventually purchased. How do you feel about that item now? Was the craving warranted?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you really want to buy right now? What value will that add to your life? What value will be lost if you don’t buy it? Is there a better use for the money you would have to spend to acquire it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of something you‘ve done that you regret. Write an apology to yourself and a response of forgiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-improving-your-character&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Improving Your Character&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his journal, it was apparent that Marcus Aurelius wrote about recurring philosophical tenets in order to continually practice his philosophy. Try doing the same for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel grief, anger, or fear is to try to escape from something decreed by the ruler of all things, now or in the past or in the future. And that ruler is law, which governs what happens to each of us. To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive — a fugitive from justice.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius, Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of a philosophical or ethical tenet that you struggle to live by. Write down the tenet and again in your own words. Try crafting your own analogy. Do this as often as you need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations from Marcus Aurelius — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of someone you admire. Write yourself advice you think they would give you from their point-of-view.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of 12 year-old you. What “secrets of life” have you acquired that you would want to share with yourself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-daily-reflection--improvement&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Daily Reflection &amp;amp; Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our daily behavior is the best indicator of the type of person we are. Work on improving what you do each day and you will in turn be improving the type of person you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Remember that our own worth is measured by what we devote our energy to. “&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius, Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I lose control of my emotions today? What triggered it? Was that a reasonable response?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I do today that was out of character? What triggered it? Was that a reasonable response?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did you do today that was not a good use of your time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you miss accomplishing an important habit or step in your routine today? What do you think was the reason for it and how can you prevent it from happening again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I crave today? Describe what you craved in its most simplistic form. Did it warrant that level of craving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Break Bad Habits for Good&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The best tips from Atomic Habits on breaking your worse habits&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to break bad habits&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done app review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Marcus Aurelius, often called the philosopher emperor, is a famous stoic philosopher and known as the last good emperor of Rome.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2019-02-05T22:48:39-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-05T22:48:39-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene">&lt;p class=&quot;a-img sml-img&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mastery.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mastery by Robert Green&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastery by Robert Greene is a practical read on helping people find and pursue their Life’s Task (purpose).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally felt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt; was a bit disorganized at times, which was especially apparent looking back at my notes. So below are quotes and thoughts that stuck out to me in the best order I could provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-mastery-and-why-pursueit&quot;&gt;What is Mastery and Why Pursue It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mastery — the feeling that we have a greater command of reality, other people, and ourselves. Although it might be something we experience for only a short while, for others — Masters of their field — it becomes their way of life, their way of seeing the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pursuit of mastery is the pursuit of purpose, whatever your Life’s Task, as Greene refers to it, may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is not mastery for the purpose of dominating nature or other people, but for determining our fate… You are contributing to the most important cause of all — the survival and prosperity of the human race, in a time of stagnation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because being on the path of mastery requires discipline and a strong work ethic towards a craft you enjoy, you will be working towards something great and something you can be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;James Clear points out your daily habits define who you are in Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;, Greene also says pursuing mastery is important because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…people get the mind and quality of brain that they deserve through their actions in life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road to mastery can be defined by three phases and Mastery goes into depth on each phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apprenticeship — you’re a student learning from others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative-Active — you’re a practitioner, adding your own creativity and style to your craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mastery — you have complete command of the craft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[Masters] excel by their ability to practice harder and move faster through the process, all of this stemming from the intensity of their desire to learn and from the deep connection they feel to their field of study. And at the core of this intensity of effort is in fact a quality that is genetic and inborn — not talent or brilliance, which is something that must be developed, but rather a deep and powerful inclination toward a particular subject.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masters become masters not because they seek fame, money, or an outcome, but because they’re obsessed with their craft. There are no shortcuts to mastery. It takes time. It takes effort. There will be failures along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-most-people-dont-achieve-mastery-in-their-lives&quot;&gt;Why Most People Don’t Achieve Mastery in Their Lives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A natural response when people feel overwhelmed is to retreat into various forms of passivity… The less we attempt, the less chances of failure. If we can make it look like we are not really responsible for our fate, for what happens to us in life, then our apparent powerlessness is more palatable. For this reason we become attracted to certain narratives: it is genetics that determines much of what we do; we are just products of our times…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are born into a reality that has existed before us with masters already present. We see them online, in TV, we read about them. When we start working toward a particular field, we learn who the masters are already. It’s easy to become envious and to think, “I’ll never be as good, as famous, as well liked by the community. They were born with more natural talent. Why should I try too hard?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the attitude of most people and it can have devastating consequences toward your Life’s Task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This [attitude] can diminish your levels of effort and discipline below the point of effectiveness. Conforming to social norms, you will listen more to others than to your own voice. You may choose a career path based on what peers and parents tell you, or on what seems lucrative. If you lose contact with this inner calling, you can have some success in life, but eventually your lack of true desire catches up with you. Your work becomes mechanical. You come to live for leisure and immediate pleasures. In this way you become increasingly passive, and never move past the first phase. You may grow frustrated and depressed, never realizing that the source of it is your alienation from your own creative potential.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you get past this passive attitude? For one, you must find your Life’s Task — your natural inclination towards a particular field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This intense connection and desire allows them to withstand the pain of the process — the self doubts, the tedious hours of practice and stuffy, the inevitable setbacks, the endless barbs from the envious. They develop a resiliency and confidence that others lack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you know you Life’s Task, you can work through inevitable roadblocks, challenges, and failures. You will find it easier to get back up again, to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discovering-your-calling-the-lifestask&quot;&gt;Discovering Your Calling: The Life’s Task&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a difference between wishing you were a master at something, and wishing you were doing something to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…he didn’t care so much about the finished product; it was the search and process in creating something that had always excited him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to love the work. You have to feel a profound connection to it. You must be obsessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Work is often seen as a means for making money so we can enjoy that second life that we lead.… This is a depressing attitude, because in the end we spend a substantial part of our waking life at work. If we experience this time as something to get through on the way to real pleasure, then our hours at work represent a tragic waste of the short time we have to live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you find work that you love to do, it doesn’t feel like work is something you have to do to live, but an opportunity to create something beyond yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find work you like, Greene recommends trying various fields you’ve always been interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Eventually, you will hit upon a particular field, niche, or opportunity that suits you perfectly. You will recognize it when you find it because it will spark that childlike sense of wonder and excitement; it will feel right. Once found, everything will fall into place. You will learn more quickly and more deeply. Your skill level will reach a point where you will be able to claim your independence from within the group you work for and move out on your own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you grow older as an adult, it’s harder to find these natural inclinations. For years, we’ve already been influenced by the culture we live in, our peers, our family, the influencers we look up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You must dig for signs of such inclinations in your earliest years. Look for its traces in visceral reactions to something simple; a desire to repeat an activity that you never tired of; a subject that stimulated an unusual degree of curiosity; feelings of power attached to particular actions… You have nothing to create; you merely need to dig and refine what has been buried inside of you all along. If you reconnect with this core at any age, some element of that primitive attraction will spark back to life, indicating a path that can ultimately become your Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you find this inclination, practice journaling and reflecting on your feelings toward different types of work and ask yourself why you feel this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Become who you are by learning who you are.” — Pindar, Ancient Greek poet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you allow yourself to learn who you really are by paying attention to that voice and force within you, then you can become what you were fated to become — an individual, a Master.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a two pathways you can take for finding your field. First, find a deep narrow niche in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[once you’ve found a field you like] …look for side paths that particularly attract you… When it is possible, you make a move to this narrower field. You continue this process until you eventually hit upon a totally unoccupied niche, the narrower the better. In some ways, this niche corresponds to your uniqueness…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can combine two entirely different fields into one and create a new category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Once you have mastered your first field, you look for other subjects or skills that you can conquer, on your own time if necessary. You can now combine this added field of knowledge to the original one, perhaps creating a new field, or at least making novel connections between them. You continue this process as long as you wish… Ultimately you create a field that is uniquely your own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Once you know you’re on the path of your Life’s Task, don’t let anything stand in the way — nothing is more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In dealing with your career and its inevitable change, you must think in the following way: You are not tied to a particular position; your loyalty is not to career or a company. You are committed to your Life’s Task, to giving it full expression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t let the field itself to evolve beneath you and leave you behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…it is up to you to foresee the changes going on right now in your profession. You must adapt your Life’s Task to these circumstances. You do not hold on to past ways of doing things. Because that will ensure you will fall behind and suffer for it. You are flexible and always looking to adapt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be lured to other paths that seem easier or more lucrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The road to mastery requires patience. You will have to keep your focus on five or ten years down the road, when you will reap the rewards of your efforts… In the end, the money and success that truly last come not to those who focus on such things as goals, but rather to those who focus on mastery and fulfilling their Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…direct yourself toward the small things you are good at. Do not dream or make grand plans for the future, but instead concentrate on becoming proficient at these simple and immediate skills. This will bring you confidence and become a base from which you can expand to other pursuits. Proceeding in this way, step by step, you will hit upon your Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-i-submit-to-reality-the-ideal-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;Phase I. Submit to Reality: The Ideal Apprenticeship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apprenticeship phase begins when you’ve identified the particular field you have a deep interest and inclination for. You may not have found exactly your Life’s Task, but you’re on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-best-kind-of-apprenticeships&quot;&gt;The Best Kind of Apprenticeships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the goal of an apprenticeship is not money, a good position, a title, or a diploma, but rather the transformation of your mind and character — the first transformation on the way to mastery. You enter a career as an outsider.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start an apprenticeship that offers the best opportunities for learning. Sometimes this means accepting the lowest position at a good company. It would be a mistake to seek out the best pay if it’s at a company that won’t mold you to be an expert in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must value learning above everything else.… opt for the situation that will give you the most opportunities to learn, particularly with hands-on work.… choose a place that has people and mentors who can inspire and teach you. A job with mediocre pay has the added benefit of training you to get by with less — a valuable life skill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentors who you can learn from are essential to your career and skill growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Practical knowledge… is what will pay you dividends for decades to come — far more than the paltry increase in pay you might receive at some seemingly lucrative position that offers fewer learning opportunities. This means that you move toward challenges that will toughen and improve you, where you will get the most objective feedback on your performance and progress. You do not choose apprenticeships that seem easy and comfortable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid of a challenging job with low pay. Your reward in an apprenticeship is not money — it is in skills and character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-you-do-when-you-have-an-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;What You Do When You Have an Apprenticeship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting an apprenticeship, a good attitude is an essential foundation for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You are naïve and full of misconceptions about this new world. Your head is full of dreams and fantasies about the future. Your knowledge of the world is subjective, based on emotions, insecurities, and limited experience. Slowly, you will ground yourself in reality, in the objective world represented by the knowledge and skills that make people successful in it. You will learn how to work with others and handle criticism. In the process you will transform yourself from someone who is impatient and scattered into someone who is disciplined and focused, with a mind that can handle complexity. In the end, you will master yourself and all of your weaknesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep a humble a mind and to not attempt to rise to the top. At some points, you may think you know everything and that you’re ready to go out on your own, but you will see there is a lot to learn before proceeding to the next phase of adding your own style and ideas to the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The greatest mistake you can make in the initial months of your apprenticeship is to imagine that you have to get attention, impress people, and prove yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“These thoughts will dominate your mind and close it off from the reality around you. Any positive attention you receive is deceptive; it is not based on your skills or anything real, and it will turn against you. Instead, you will want to acknowledge the reality and submit to it, muting your colors and keeping in the background as much as possible, remaining passive and giving yourself the space to observe. You will also want to drop any preconceptions you might have about this world you are entering. If you impress people in these first months, it should be because of the seriousness of your desire to learn, not because you are trying to rise to the top before you are ready.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to impress in any way other than through your hard work, determination, and desire to learn. You need to learn your new environment inside and out. How companies in the field work, even at the levels above you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the ability to observe any unfamiliar environment will become a critical lifelong skill. You will develop the habit of stilling your ego and looking outward instead of inward. You will see in any encounter what most people miss because they are thinking of themselves. You will cultivate a keen eye for human psychology, and strengthen your ability to focus… This will be a very important skill for the next, creative phase in life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By being able to critically observe all aspects of your environment, you will be able to make better decisions with your work by seeing the whole picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to accept that apprenticeships will require monotonous and tedious work. This is something you will have to push through and embrace. Even if you don’t think you have anything left to learn, you will learn the power of disciple — the ability to do what you know needs to be done even when your body and mind don’t want you to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discipline-and-the-resistance-practice&quot;&gt;Discipline and the Resistance Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[The Resistance Practice means] you go in the opposite direction of all of your natural tendencies when it comes to practice. First, you resist the temptation to be nice to yourself. You become your own worst critic; you see your work as if through the eyes of others. You recognize your weaknesses, precisely the elements you are not good at.… Second, you resist the lure of easing up on your focus. You train yourself to concentrate in practice with double the intensity, as if it were the real thing times two. In devising your own routines, you become as creative as possible. You invent exercises that work upon your weaknesses. You give yourself arbitrary deadlines to meet certain standards, constantly pushing yourself past perceived limits. In this way you develop your own standards for excellence, generally higher than those of others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is a super power. If you can develop strong discipline, you can consistently do the work required to be on the path for mastery and success. Set high standards for yourself, even if your friends, peers, or even family think you’re crazy. They most likely won’t have the same levels of expectations for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mistakes and failures are precisely your means of education. They tell you about your own inadequacies. It is hard to find out such things from people, as they are often political with their praise and criticisms. Your failures also permit you to see the flaws of your ideas, which are only revealed in the execution of them. You learn what your audience really wants, the discrepancy between your ideas and how they affect the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one becomes a master with 100% perfect record. It is okay to fail because with patience and time, you will recover and grow even more skillful and stronger due to those learning experiences. Be the own judge of your quality — coworkers and even bosses will not say as much as they think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You want to learn as many skills as possible, following the direction that circumstances lead you to, but only if they are related to your deepest interests. Like a hacker, you value the process of self-discovery and making things that are of the highest quality. You avoid the trap of following one set career path. You are not sure where this will all lead, but you are taking full advantage of the openness of information, all of the knowledge about skills now at our disposal. You see what kind of work suits you and what you want to avoid at all cost. You move by trial and error.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning lots of different skills allows you to combine different skills later in life, and get you closer to discovering your Life’s Task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You are not wandering about because you are afraid of commitment, but because you are expanding your skill base and your possibilities. At a certain point, when you are ready to settle on something, ideas and opportunities will inevitably present themselves to you. When that happens, all of the skills you have accumulated will prove invaluable. You will be the Master at combining them in ways that are unique and suited to your individuality. You may settle on this one place or idea for several years, accumulating in the process even more skills, then move in a slightly different direction when the time is appropriate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching work like this will keep you from finding yourself locked in a boring career and instead provide opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The very desire to find shortcuts makes you eminently unsuited for any kind of mastery.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;absorb-the-masters-power-the-mentordynamic&quot;&gt;Absorb the Master’s Power: The Mentor Dynamic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the apprenticeship phase, it’s critical to find and work under a master as a mentee. With their experience, they can guide you on the right path and help you grow your skills far faster than you could alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best mentor-mentee relationships are with people you work with on a daily basis, such as your manager. If your direct manager isn’t a suitable mentee, then possibly another leader at your company you have the ability to interact with. If no one at your workplace is suitable, find a better company or the next best thing is finding a mentor online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To learn requires a sense of humility. We must admit that there are people out there who know our field much more deeply than we do. Their superiority is not a function of natural talent or privilege, but rather of time and experience. Their authority in the field is not based on politics or trickery. It is very real.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect masters for what they have accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Even if we have teachers in our lives, we tend not to pay full attention to their advice, often preferring to do things our own way. In fact, we come to believe that being critical of Masters or teachers is somehow a sign of our intelligence, and that being a submissive pupil is a sign of weakness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a huge mistake to think you know better than a master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As the relationship progresses you can make this absorption process more conscious and direct, questioning them about the principles underlying their way of doing things. If you are clever,… getting them to analyze their own creativity for you, and mining all kinds of rich ideas in the process. They are often grateful for the opportunity to reveal the inner workings of their power, particularly to someone they do not perceive as a threat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-people-as-they-are-the-social-intelligence&quot;&gt;See People As They Are: The Social Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat the work you do, no matter how small the job and responsibility is as art — as a demonstration of your craft. But don’t do it alone. When appropriate, bring other people in, be open to feedback, and create something together to make not just yourself win, but others with you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…your work is the single greatest means at your disposal for expressing your social intelligence. By being efficient and detail oriented in what you do, you demonstrate that you are thinking of the group at large and advancing its cause. By making what you write or present clear and easy to follow, you show your care for the audience or public at large. By involving other people in your projects and gracefully accepting their feedback, you reveal your comfort with the group dynamic. Work that is solid also protects you from the political conniving and malevolence of others — it is hard to argue with the results you produce. If you are experiencing the pressures of political maneuvering within the group, do not lose your head and become consumed with all of the pettiness. By remaining focused and speaking socially through your work, you will both continue to raise your skill level and stand out among all the others who make a lot of noise but produce nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your work speak for yourself while others around you try to get ahead by playing political games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also keep up a healthy appearance. Even if you don’t think it’s true, people are and will judge you based on your appearance. Use this to your advantage by crafting an appearance that portrays the character you want to be known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“… turn this dynamic around by consciously molding these appearances, creating the image that suits you, and controlling people’s judgments. At times you will find it appropriate to stand back and create some mystery around you, heightening your presence. At other times you will want to be more direct and impose a more specific appearance. In general, you never settle on one image or give people the power to completely figure you out. You are always one step ahead of the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t go too far in trying to always persuade and figure out what the people around you are thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In dealing with fools you must adopt the following philosophy: they are simply a part of life, like rocks or furniture. All of us have foolish sides. Moments in which we lose our heads and think more of our ego or short-term goals. It is human nature. Seeing this foolishness within you, you can then accept it in others. This will allow you to smile at their antics, to tolerate their presence as you would a silly child. And to avoid the madness of trying to change them. It is all part of the human comedy, and it is nothing to get upset about or lose sleep over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius’s stoic philosophy also teaches this mindset in dealing with other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations from Marcus Aurelius — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-ii-awaken-the-dimensional-mind-the-creative-active&quot;&gt;Phase II. Awaken the Dimensional Mind: The Creative-Active&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Dimensional Mind has two essential requirements: one, a high level of knowledge about a field or subject; and two, the openness and flexibility to use this knowledge in new and original ways.… Once the mind is freed from having to learn these basics, it can focus on higher, more creative matters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dimensional Mind is a concept that combines knowledge and skepticism — having deep knowledge about a particular subject, but not so set in stone in order to be open to new ideas and perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-how-to-obtain-a-dimensional-mind&quot;&gt;Here’s How to Obtain a Dimensional Mind:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…first, choosing the proper Creative Task, the kind of activity that will maximize our skills and knowledge; second, loosening and opening up the mind through certain Creative Strategies; and third, creating the optimal mental conditions for a Breakthrough or Insight. Finally, throughout the process we must also be aware of the Emotional Pitfalls — complacency, boredom, grandiosity, and the like — that continually threaten to derail or block our progress. If we can move through the steps while avoiding these traps, we cannot fail to unleash powerful creative forces from within.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat all your work like art. Hone your craft. Do not think about false goals like money or fame, but focus on creating the best thing you’re capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you go at your work with half a heart, it will show in the lackluster results and in the laggard way in which you reach the end. If you are doing something primarily for money and without a real emotional commitment, it will translate into something that lacks a soul and that has no connection to you. You may not see this, but you can be sure that the public will feel it and that they will receive your work in the same lackluster spirit it was created in. If you are excited and obsessive in the hunt, it will show in the details. If your work comes from a place deep within, its authenticity will be communicated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very difficult to even think about “going down” in your level of lifestyle, but to achieve mastery, you can’t be afraid of that happening. You most likely will have to make some sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must let go of your need for comfort and security. Creative endeavors are by their nature uncertain. You may know your task, but you are never exactly sure where your efforts will lead. If you need everything in your life to be simple and safe, this open-ended nature of the task will fill you with anxiety. If you are worried about what others might think and about how your position in the group might be jeopardized, then you will never really create anything.… your ideas will grow stale and flat. If you are worried about failure or going through a period of mental and financial instability,… your worries will be reflected in the results. Think of yourself as an explorer. You cannot find anything new if you are unwilling to leave the shore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the challenging path of mastery worth it? Because we don’t get anywhere near the same level of satisfaction from exercising our creativity as anything else. It defines who we are. It makes an impact on our community; to the human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Engaged in the creative process we feel more alive than ever, because we are making something and not merely consuming, Masters of the small reality we create. In doing this work, we are in fact creating ourselves. Although it involves much pain, the pleasure that comes from the overall process of creativity is of an intensity that makes us want to repeat it. That is why creative people return again and again to such endeavors, despite all of the anxiety and doubt they stir up. It is nature’s way of rewarding us for the effort; if we had no such rewards, people would not engage in such activity, and mankind would suffer irreparably from this loss. This pleasure will be your reward as well, to whatever degree you pursue the process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With discipline, good work, and time, your skills will grow towards Mastery. And if time is a part of the process, then the more time you have, the more your skills will grow. Time, therefore is an ally. Have patience. By trying to rush to the next level quickly, you’re removing time from the equation and therefore decreasing your skill output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must come to embrace slowness as a virtue in itself. When it comes to creative endeavors, time is always relative. Whether your project takes months or years to complete, you will always experience a sense of impatience and a desire to get to the end. The single greatest action you can take for acquiring creative power is to reverse this natural impatience. You take pleasure in the laborious research process; you enjoy the slow cooking of the idea, the organic growth that naturally takes shape over time. You do not unnaturally draw out the process, which will create its own problems (we all need deadlines), but the longer you can allow the project to absorb your mental energies, the richer it will become. Imagine yourself years in the future looking back at the work you have done. From that future vantage point, the extra months and years you devoted to the process will not seem painful or laborious at all. It is an illusion of the present that will vanish. Time is your greatest ally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fuse-the-intuitive-with-the-rational-mastery&quot;&gt;Fuse the Intuitive With the Rational: Mastery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the path to Mastery, it’s important to lose sight of your goal. Mindset is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must also maintain a sense of destiny, and feel continuously connected to it. You are unique, and there is a purpose to your uniqueness. You must see every setback, failure, or hardship as a trial along the way, as seeds that are being planted for further cultivation, if you know how to grow them. No moment is wasted if you pay attention and learn the lessons contained in every experience. By constantly applying yourself to the subject that suits your inclinations and attacking it from many different angles, you are simply enriching the ground for these seeds to take root. You may not see this process in the present, but it is happening. Never losing your connection to your Life’s Task, you will unconsciously hit upon the right choices in your life. Over time, mastery will come to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerful tool as you face increasing challenges is learning how to manage stress and anxiety — and even better, learn how to use it to your advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We must learn how to quiet the anxiety we feel whenever we are confronted with anything that seems complex or chaotic. In our journey from apprenticeship to mastery we must patiently learn the various parts and skills that are required, never looking too far ahead. In moments of perceived crisis, we must develop the habit of maintaining our cool and never overreacting. If the situation is complex and others are reaching for simple black-and-white answers, or for the usual conventional responses, we must make a point of resisting such a temptation. We maintain our Negative Capability and a degree of detachment. What we are doing is gaining a tolerance and even a taste for chaotic moments, training ourselves to entertain several possibilities or solutions. We are learning to manage our anxiety, a key skill in these chaotic times.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path to mastery is a long road. Temptations to abandon your path will come from all angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The problem is that we humans are deep conformists. Those qualities that separate us are often ridiculed by others, or criticized by teachers.… anything that is peculiar to our makeup is precisely what we must pay the deepest attention to and lean on in our rise to mastery. Mastery is like swimming — it is too difficult to move forward when we are creating our own resistance or swimming against the current. Know your strengths and move with them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing in mastery is to stay true to who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Your false self is the accumulation of all the voices you have internalized from other people — parents and friends who want you to conform to their ideas of what you should be like and what you should do, as well as societal pressures to adhere to certain values that can easily seduce you. It also includes the voice of your own ego, which constantly tries to protect you from unflattering truths.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Greene is my one my favorite writers because the way he likes to weave historical stories into practical advice. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt;, Greene helps people find their purpose in life, which he thinks is better called your Life’s Task. Although long and a little disorganized, Mastery was a fun read that revealed a desire for creativity and craft within me for my work. I still think I’m young in my career (apprenticeship phase) and Mastery provided some practical advice on how to make best use of my position and time to move closer to mastery. I wanted a bit more detail with the practical advice, but I still found it quite useful. I rate Mastery an 8/10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations from Marcus Aurelius — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Google Sheets Budget Template — Simple and Beautiful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-monthly-budget-template" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Google Sheets Budget Template — Simple and Beautiful" /><published>2019-02-01T07:51:34-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T07:51:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-monthly-budget-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-monthly-budget-template">&lt;p&gt;You can download my template using the link at the bottom of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I graduated college, I received an inheritance check for $30k. &lt;strong&gt;About a year later it was gone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the money to move out, get a new car, eat out constantly — all while telling myself I’m going to be making $10k a month before I know it as freelance marketer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that didn’t work out (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/marketing/comments/9qsktw/i_made_130k_with_year_as_a_b2b_marketer_in_saas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;but didn’t turn out so bad&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Every month I knew I was spending more than I was making, but I was too scared to look at my bank account or my credit card statement. Just click pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It took me wasting all my money and having only one month left to survive on my own to push me to get a real job and start budgeting.&lt;/strong&gt; If you can learn from my mistakes, you won’t need to let it get this bad for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did I get my finances back on track? As you can tell by the title, it was from creating and &lt;strong&gt;following&lt;/strong&gt; a budget. Sticking to the budget you created is the key — if you can’t do that, your budget is worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ultimate goal of a budget is not to see where your money is going, but to create a change in your behavior to spend less money on stupid shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-reason-doing-your-budget-on-google-sheets-will-drive-behavior-change-to-spendless&quot;&gt;The Reason Doing Your Budget on Google Sheets Will Drive Behavior Change to Spend Less&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It forces you to enter your expenses manually. Although seemingly tedious, I found it the most important exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Entering expenses manually forces you to review every transaction, to feel the pain of every dollar spent — that is what will drive a change in your spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And something tools like Mint that try and automate everything are terrible at doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The other benefit is you’re forced to self categorize each transaction, which means they’ll be more accurate and useful for budgeting.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using Google Sheets to manage my finances for four years now. And after much tinkering and revisions, it’s the most beautiful and easiest to use I’ve made yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-how-itworks&quot;&gt;Here’s How It Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the budget template with easy-to-follow orange prompts to make it super simple to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/budget1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;easy to use google sheet buget template&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with entering your income, annual budget, and monthly budget data to get started. Then enter your bank account, other assets, credit cards, loans etc to get your financial picture. All that’s left is entering expense data and that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything else other than entering expenses is automated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve been using it for a few months and get some data in there (or even better enter historical data) you can use this chart to see how you’ve been spending vs your budget by each category or in total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/budget2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;see a graph of your spending in a google sheet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;download-my-google-sheets-monthly-budgettemplate&quot;&gt;Download My Google Sheets Monthly Budget Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click the link below to access a “view only” version of the template. You will need to click File &amp;gt; Make a Copy in order to use it for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VRczmKEyg96fFixxz4LtR-1Yh2_V4xILIGVrpRqN38w/edit?usp=sharing&quot; title=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VRczmKEyg96fFixxz4LtR-1Yh2_V4xILIGVrpRqN38w/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download: Google Sheets Monthly Budget Template&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
_Click File &amp;gt; Make a Copy to create your own you can edit._docs.google.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VRczmKEyg96fFixxz4LtR-1Yh2_V4xILIGVrpRqN38w/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-tips&quot;&gt;Bonus Tips&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A budget is only good if you update it consistently, keep it accurate, and spend time analyzing your spending. That’s why I made it a point to make it look nice, be easy to use, and be rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes that’s still not enough. &lt;strong&gt;There’s definitely been times where I don’t do it for a few weeks at a time and the more you wait, the more work you’ll have to do, and the more you won’t look forward to it&lt;/strong&gt;. I‘ve made it a habit to log my expenses every Sunday vs once every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe a budget will help you get control of your spending, read this guide on how to stick to new habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tip is to use a credit card for all transactions when possible. Using a credit card makes it much easier to keep track of your spending and at the same time protects your bank account from fraud, builds your credit, and you can earn points and rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think of the spreadsheet. If you found some places where I messed up or have ideas for new functionality, leave me a note in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/i-made-317-per-month-from-two-amazon-niche-sites-last-year-and-heres-how-i-did-it&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;I Made $317 / Mo. From Two Amazon Niche Sites Last Year&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And here’s how I did it.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/i-made-317-per-month-from-two-amazon-niche-sites-last-year-and-heres-how-i-did-it&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/niche site amazon affiliate.png&quot; alt=&quot;niche site amazon affiliate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">You can download my template using the link at the bottom of this article.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2018 Year Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018-year-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2018 Year Review" /><published>2019-01-25T09:46:11-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-25T09:46:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018-year-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018-year-review">&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-100kyr-by30&quot;&gt;Make $100k/yr by 30&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an arbitrary “goal,” but nonetheless one I wrote down at the beginning of the year. In fact it’s something I always had as a goal in the back of mind since I started working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some hard work and definitely some luck mixed in, I was able to make it. What’s funny is earlier in the year, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/marketing/comments/6kg6kv/who_here_makes_100k/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;asked the r/marketing subreddit who made $100k&lt;/a&gt; and what was their path and advice. It ended up getting way more comments than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comments were pretty inspiring and kind of pointed out I was a little underpaid at where I was at the time. So I used that to make some moves and did two things: 1) turned a lucrative job offer into a raise and 2) got a high paying freelancing client doing paid Facebook Ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was awesome to go back to the community at r/marketing and do an update post and an ask me anything: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/marketing/comments/9qsktw/i_made_130k_with_year_as_a_b2b_marketer_in_saas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“I made $130k this year as a B2B Marketer in SaaS. AMA”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-1-book-amonth&quot;&gt;Read 1 Book a Month&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t quite make this one. I read 7 books and listened to 8 on Audible. I decided I’m not the biggest fan of audiobooks — while entertaining during drives, at the gym, or doing whatever, I just don’t retain as much information. Since I wanted to read a book a month to learn practical knowledge, audiobooks therefore just can’t count towards this goal. So from now on, Audiobooks will be reserved for just fun books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kindle (7): 48 Laws of Power, Meditations, Mastery, Man’s Search for Meaning, The Boron Letters, Atomic Habits, Pre-Suasion,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audible (8): Rome’s Last Citizen (2x), Conspiracy, The Obstacle is The Way (2x), Washington: A Life, Thomas Jefferson: The Art of Power, Ego Is The Enemy, First Break All The Rules, and Way of the Wolf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations from Marcus Aurelius — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The essential book to help you find your purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mastery-book-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;mastery book summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;start-trackinghabits&quot;&gt;Start Tracking Habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the year off strong using a pen and planner method, but after a couple months I started to miss a few days tracking, which eventually led me to stop completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of 2018, I started using a &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;habit tracking app called Done&lt;/a&gt;, which was a huge improvement over pen and paper. Reading &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; also helped me tremendously to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;stick with my new habits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I have to mark this goal as a fail, but I’ve made big improvements here that I don’t feel bad about it. I’m pretty confident I’ll stick to my habits and tracking them everyday in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done app review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;doing-habits&quot;&gt;Doing Habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img med-img-4&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/journal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/floss.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gym.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only habit I kept up from the beginning of the year was going to the gym. My goal at first was to go 3x a week and then it went to 4x. Due to some injuries, illness, and a vacation to Europe, I didn’t quite meet my goal. I averaged 2.85x per week. Not bad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journaling was tough. I was fired up in the beginning of the year, but then I couldn’t keep it up. Again thanks to Atomic Habits, I was able to find a way to integrate journaling into my routine that stuck (December I went to Europe and got sick hence the lower number).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditating was something I first tried in 2018. I liked it for a while, but began to feel it wasn’t really doing much for me practically. I picked it back up again, but still have some doubt about how much it helps me in my day-to-day thoughts and feelings. I’m going to test switching from Headspace to Sam Harris’s Waking Up app and see if I can get more value from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hardly ever flossed in my life, but after being told how disgusting I was every night by my girlfriend, I decided to give it a go. Surprisingly, it wasn’t that hard to keep up after I got used to doing it. It was also great to hear a dentist tell me that I’ve been doing a good job flossing — a life first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-things-thathappened&quot;&gt;Other Things That Happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moved-into-a-new-apartment&quot;&gt;Moved Into a New Apartment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Deanna (my girlfriend) and I moved out of our studios and into a one bedroom apartment together. We had to renew our lease in 2018 or leave the building and we decided to stay, but upgrade to a better unit with an awesome and balcony and view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img lg-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/apartment.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facebook-ads-for-musclepharm&quot;&gt;Facebook Ads for MusclePharm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a six month freelance project for my most high-profile company yet—&lt;a href=&quot;https://musclepharm.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MusclePharm&lt;/a&gt;. I learned a lot doing paid Facebook ads at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ServiceTitan&lt;/a&gt; (the company I worked for at the time) after spending over $1.5 million in FB ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from this project. For one, I don’t think I’ll freelance again while at a full-time job. While the extra income is very nice, the opportunity cost is very high — most notably less free time and a hit to my performance at my main job. The latter is important because I was in a great position at ST and I could have done better during my time there. I believe freelancing was one of the major factors of my decrease in performance there, which led to me not going as high and far as I could have gone there — earning me more money long term than the freelance project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;turned-30&quot;&gt;Turned 30&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hit the big 3–0 last year. Deanna took me out to a delicious steak dinner, and other than that I didn’t really celebrate too much. She did get me some amazing gifts though — a new Louis Vuitton wallet and some nice Clark Dessert Boots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bought-a-newcar&quot;&gt;Bought a New Car&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love cars. Over the years I’ve had two Honda S2000s, a super clean ’96 BMW E36 328is coupe in manual, and an ’09 BMW e92 328i coupe. Then the unthinkable happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got rear ended hard and the ’09 Bimmer was totaled. To make it worse, it was right after I was laid off so I didn’t want to spend a lot of money while my income was uncertain. That’s how I ended up driving a VW Passat for two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in 2018 I finally got myself a new-to-me car: a ’14 BMW F32 435i coupe in manual with 25k miles. I’ve modded the car a lot so far (with more to come). Finally, I have a car I love getting into and driving again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img lg-img-pt&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/435.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;went-toseattle&quot;&gt;Went to Seattle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a quick vacation in Seattle, the first time I’ve ever been there. It’s the most beautiful city I’ve ever visited in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img lg-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/seattle.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-experience-managing-a-directreport&quot;&gt;First Experience Managing a Direct Report&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my career, a big highlight in 2018 was beginning my management experience after being given the responsibility to manage someone. Although it was only for 9 months or so, it was a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sole contributor, your core focus is to do your job and help the company achieve goals. As a team contributor and manager, it’s still your job to help achieve company goals, but it’s also a big part to help another person achieve &lt;strong&gt;their&lt;/strong&gt; goals. And in many ways, that’s more rewarding. I’m excited for more opportunities to grow in a leadership role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;servicetitan-to-chilipiper&quot;&gt;ServiceTitan to Chili Piper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest change in 2018 was my job change from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ServiceTitan&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chilipiper.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chili Piper&lt;/a&gt;. I spent 2.5 years at ServiceTitan and have grown tremendously during that time. During my time there, the company went through two major rounds of funding, a valuation from $300 million to $1.6 billion right after I left, and from 115 employees to nearly 600.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the company grew and our marketing department ballooned in size, the skills asked of each team member in our team changed narrowed dramatically. When I joined, the marketing team was 6 people and when I left it was close to 30. In the beginning, we were asked to wear a lot of hats — be really good at and do many different things. As the team grew, the company was able to afford to place specialists in more siloed roles. This didn’t really fit my skill set and how I wanted to progress in my career, so the company and I agreed to part ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now thrilled to join Chili Piper, a small start up with around a dozen people who make a suite of tools for marketing and sales people — a demographic I know well since I’m a marketer myself who works closely with sales. This is a welcomed change, because having empathy for your buyers is a huge advantage to success as a marketer and job fulfillment — something I struggled with at ServiceTitan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;went-to-paris-and-amsterdam&quot;&gt;Went to Paris and Amsterdam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out I was going to Paris two weeks before my departure date. I joined Chili Piper in November during a contest they were running where if we break the most revenue generated in a single month, our founders were taking all of us to Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw the number we were at and the one we needed to hit, and I actually didn’t expect us to make it. But we have some absolute monsters on our team and they hit the number. Next thing I knew, I was going to the US Passport Agency in downtown LA one week before departure to rush order a new passport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img lg-img-pt&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/paris.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been to Paris, and it instantly became my favorite city in Europe. The architecture was beautiful and the food everywhere I went was delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I extended my Paris trip to visit my friend in Amsterdam. I’ve been once before so long ago I don’t even remember anything — it felt like I was visiting for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img lg-img-pt&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/amsterdam.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amsterdam was also a beautiful place. While it felt much smaller than Paris and it was definitely a touristy place, I still really enjoyed this unique city and my time there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-a-yearlyreview&quot;&gt;Why Do a Yearly Review?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this yearly review more as a personal exercise of reflection and gratitude. If I don’t take the time to reflect on what I’ve done and memories created, it becomes easy for me to forget and think time is flying by. Before this reflection, I would have said I didn’t do much in 2018 and maybe even ask myself “what am I doing with my life?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the reflection, it’s much more clear to see what I’ve done, experiences had, and memories created. It makes me think, “Hey my life isn’t that boring after all,” a mindset easy to give in to with social media. Finally, it’s an exercise in gratitude in appreciating the people in your life, the things in your life, and even the very flow of time itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Goals:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Break Bad Habits for Good</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-break-bad-habits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Break Bad Habits for Good" /><published>2019-01-24T15:45:09-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-24T15:45:09-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-break-bad-habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-break-bad-habits">&lt;p&gt;Stopping a bad habit is usually much more difficult than starting a new habit, especially if it’s a bad habit you’ve had for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason bad habits get started in the first place is throughout our day we experience a wide range of feelings and sensations, which can unconsciously trigger an action to fulfill or solve such feeling—all without a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the best action is found to deal with that feeling, it becomes ingrained in us and we tend come back to it whenever we experience that feeling again. Typically these solutions are short term solutions that can provide instant gratification, but can harm us in the long run— physically and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the following examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smoking cigarettes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long video game sessions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alcoholic drinks after each work night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Picking up and checking your phone constantly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Browsing Instagram constantly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying a coffee and donut every morning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They provide instant gratification to solve some kind of feeling (the trigger). Typically, solutions that provide instant gratification have a long term consequences. But because that instant gratification is so fulfilling and rewarding, it makes it extremely difficult to give up that instant gratification and remove it from your routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your current habits are not necessarily the best way to solve the problem you face, they are just the methods you learned to use. Once you associate a solution with the problem you need to solve, you keep coming back to it — an explanation for why habits are hard to break. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are six tips from &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; that helped me be break my worse habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-write-down-the-bad-habits-you-want-to-quit-andwhy&quot;&gt;1. Write Down the Bad Habits You Want to Quit and Why&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help make your promise to yourself more concrete, almost like a contract between your conscious and unconscious self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as important, write down why you want to stop each one. Usually this turns into crafting a new desired identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: I don’t want to eat a donut for breakfast every morning. Why? Because I don’t want a sugar rush in the morning with a crash in the afternoon. I don’t want to eat all those calories and it will help me lose some weight. New identity: I live a healthy lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ultimate form of intrinsic motivation is when a habit becomes part of your identity. You might start a habit because of motivation, but the only reason you’ll stick with one is that it becomes part of your identity. True behavior change is identity change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this seems like you’re just playing a trick on yourself at first, once it becomes ingrained in you, it’s a powerful resistance to temptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-remove-the-cues-that-trigger-your-badhabits&quot;&gt;2. Remove the Cues That Trigger Your Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may be difficult to pin down exactly what causes you to suddenly desire your bad habit, once you’re able to stop the cue (or limit it as much as possible), you’re much more likely to not desire and therefore do your bad habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you have a desire to do the bad habit in question, think about why you want to do it. Did something you see caused it? Something you felt? Something in your environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you’re constantly picking up and checking your phone, maybe it was a notification that caused it? Once you’ve identified the cue, you can remove it as best you can. In this case, you can turn on do not disturb mode and stop the notifications from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-increase-friction-between-you-and-badhabits&quot;&gt;3. Increase Friction Between You and Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For extremely ingrained habits, sometimes removing the cue is not enough so you can go a step further by adding friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only can you turn off notifications, you can also put your phone in another room out of reach. Then if you felt the urge to pick it up, you’d have to get up from where you are and go get it, all the while remembering that you put it in that room for a purpose — a promise you made to yourself that you don’t want to break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples: throw out the alcohol you have in your home to stop drinking at home after work. Store your video game consoles in the closet so you’d have to take it out each time and set it up just to play. Delete Instagram from your phone so every time you want to check it you have to download the app again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-replace-a-bad-habit-with-a-goodhabit&quot;&gt;4. Replace a Bad Habit with a Good Habit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believing the why, removing the cue, and increasing friction is likely to help you stop most of your habits. But there could still be unfulfilled feelings that leave you feeling empty or deprived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the case, you may be using too much willpower to stop your bad habits—and that can only last so long before you give in. Perhaps it’s best to find a different and better solution to solve that feeling, rather than trying to ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, replace the donut in the morning with a fruit smoothie. Replace the drink after work with a decaf latte. Replace the video games with &lt;a href=&quot;/book-notes&quot;&gt;a great book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-record-your-progress-in-a-habittracker&quot;&gt;5. Record Your Progress in a Habit Tracker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing your progress and how far you’ve come can also be a great long term source of motivation. With a good system for tracking your habits, you’ll be able to see the number of days (or weeks) in a row you refrained from a bad habit. As that number increases, you’ll want to break it less and less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can track habits using pen and paper, a Google Sheet, or an app. After trying a few of these methods, I settled on an app being the easiest to use and because it was the easiest and fastest way to track habits, it was the system I could actually stick to using every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app I use is called Done. &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;Check out my review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done app review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-reward-yourself-for-resisting-your-badhabits&quot;&gt;6. Reward Yourself for Resisting Your Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, give yourself a reward for refraining from a bad habit. If you don’t have a donut in the morning for a week, treat yourself to a nice breakfast on Sunday mornings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t drink at home after work for a week, reward yourself with a drink out on Saturday night. If you don’t play video games for a week, reward yourself with a long session just on Sundays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using these strategies, I was able to completely break, or significantly reduce, some bad habits of mine, and even replace some of them with positive habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s your best to tip to break a bad habit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Stopping a bad habit is usually much more difficult than starting a new habit, especially if it’s a bad habit you’ve had for a long time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-make-habits-stick" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out" /><published>2019-01-21T08:44:36-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-21T08:44:36-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-make-habits-stick</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-make-habits-stick">&lt;p&gt;Has this ever happened to you? You’re completely motivated to start some new habits, it started off well because you’re fired up, but your fire inevitably died out after just a short time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s happened to me plenty of times. I’d start logging my habits everyday, which turned into every 3 days, which turned into once a week and so on until I completely stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;reading Atomic Habits (AH)&lt;/a&gt;, I realized why I couldn’t keep up my new habits and how I can make new habits actually last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, without any signs of fatigue so far, I’ve been able to keep up several new habits — meditation, journaling, reading, working out, and flossing just to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s six tips that helped me the most:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-ask-yourself-who-do-i-want-to-be-and-write-itdown&quot;&gt;1. Ask Yourself, “Who Do I Want to Be?” and Write It Down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each habit (or goal) you want to start doing, write down why you want to do it and how it helps you get closer to the person you want to be. Who you are is shaped by your habits and your behavior (not your thoughts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ultimate form of intrinsic motivation is when a habit becomes part of your identity. You might start a habit because of motivation, but the only reason you’ll stick with one is that it becomes part of your identity. True behavior change is identity change. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I want to journal every morning because I want to be grateful for who I am and what I have, and I want to live more purposefully. This helps me become a less envious and more happy person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing down the “why” develops long-term motivation by making your habits a part of your identity, which is much stronger than a burst of motivation that dies out quickly.&lt;/strong&gt; Now if you were to skip doing your habits, you will be going against who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Remember that our own worth is measured by what we devote our energy to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt; 7.3&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-reframe-from-i-have-to-to-i-getto&quot;&gt;2. Reframe From “I Have To” to “I Get To”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After your initial burst of motivation runs dry, habits quickly begin to feel like something “you have to do.” I couldn’t tell you the amount of times I’ve said aloud, “Shit, I can’t go to bed yet because I have to do x.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, think of each of your habits as an opportunity to make a step toward your desired identity. Continuing with journaling, I now tell myself “I get to journal today and it’s going to help me be more a grateful and happy person tomorrow.” At first, you will feel like you’re only trying to trick yourself. The concept is easy to understand, but it takes a while to naturally internalize it and that is when this mindset becomes a powerful motivator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reframing your habits to highlight their benefits rather than their drawbacks is a fast and lightweight way to reprogram your mind to make a habit more attractive. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-set-up-your-environment-forsuccess&quot;&gt;3. Set Up Your Environment for Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every night I set up my environment for a successful morning routine. That means I pre grind my coffee beans and get everything out to make a pour over, make sure my AirPods are charged for meditation, have my journal on my desk for morning journaling, and I have my light on my desk set to turn on automatically at 5:45 AM. This helps remove as much friction as possible between me and my morning routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My coworker Emil also read AH and says this tip has been one of the most helpful for him to surf more often. He’ll get his board, wetsuit, and anything else he needs out the night before to make it as easy as possible to just go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-focus-on-repetition-not-perfection&quot;&gt;4. Focus on Repetition, Not Perfection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s more important to get it done than to do it perfectly.&lt;/strong&gt; If you’re low on energy, you can do a quick workout, you can do a shorter meditation, or you can read or write half as much as you normally do. It’s not the best path to do this all the time, but it can be important on days when you’re not feeling well, when you’re tired, when something came up and your short on time, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help keep the chain alive — the chain (or streak) is the number of days or weeks in a row you’ve completed your habit. Not wanting to break the chain can be a motivator itself so making sure it continues, even if you’re not doing your best, can help you get through that low moment and still continue off strong tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you want to master a habit, the key is to start with repetition, not perfection. You don’t need to map out every feature of the new habit. You just need to practice it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-use-a-habittracker&quot;&gt;5. Use a Habit Tracker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why tracking your habits is so important — you can see how many times in a given week, month, year etc you’ve completed your habit, and how many days (or weeks) in a row you’ve done it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habit trackers give you a visual representation of your progress, can motivate you by calculating and showing your chains, and remind you to complete or log your habits if you’r using an app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habit trackers can be made with pen and paper, in a spreadsheet, or in an app. After trying all three of these, I found the &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;habit app Done&lt;/a&gt; to be the habit tracking system I was able to stick to. Here’s my review of the app:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done app review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-rewardyourself&quot;&gt;6. Reward Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to help me get through my morning routine, I withhold myself from checking email, Reddit, Twitter, LinkedIn, or anything else on my phone until after my morning routine is completed. This is like a reward to myself for accomplishing the routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For larger habits or goals, like publishing an article once per week, I’ll allow myself to play video games on the weekend. The only way rewards work is you can’t give yourself the reward unless you accomplish the action it’s rewarding. Now there’s an element of risk to your habits if you don’t do them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these six tips, I have been able to continue my habits better than ever in my life. They are designed to help motivate you to do them and to avoid not doing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has helped you make your habits stick?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Break Bad Habits for Good&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The best tips from Atomic Habits on breaking your worse habits&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to break bad habits&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Has this ever happened to you? You’re completely motivated to start some new habits, it started off well because you’re fired up, but your fire inevitably died out after just a short time?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meditations from Marcus Aurelius — Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meditations from Marcus Aurelius — Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2018-12-06T21:36:59-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-06T21:36:59-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus_Aurelius&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt; was an ancient Roman emperor from the years 161 to 180. And we have access to his personal journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although born into a rich and politically connected family, Marcus wasn’t born to be emperor — he wasn’t the biological son of the emperor he preceded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His father died when he was three years old and he was mostly raised by his great grandfather. Taught by a variety of private tutors, Marcus was first introduced to philosophy by a painting teacher. It was then when he began to live life as a philosopher — wearing Greek philosopher clothes and sleeping on the hard floor at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emperor at the time, Hadrian, became very ill. Before his death, he named Aurelius Antoninus as his successor on the condition he legally adopt Marcus, with the intention that one day Marcus would then become emperor of Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did Hadrian see in Marcus? He saw young man with excellent character and without the thirst for power — heavily influenced by philosophy. Marcus was not happy with his new path in life, but grew to accept it and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-meditations&quot;&gt;What is Meditations?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0812968255/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0812968255&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=8dbf0e74c04495dc6d0390c6e1d2e404&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt; is a collection of notes Marcus wrote to himself while emperor of which he never intended to be published. These notes span a variety of topics and for Marcus were an exercise to help him think clearly and rationally. His journals were preserved, translated, and curated into a single collection which came to be known as Meditations — obviously not a name Marcus himself chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img sml-img&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0812968255/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0812968255&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=8dbf0e74c04495dc6d0390c6e1d2e404&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Link to Amazon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read the Gregory Hays translation, which also has a very interesting introduction and history lesson that provides helpful context that I think is needed before diving into his Marcus’ actual writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his notes, Marcus would frequently write about the same reoccurring themes as a way to remind himself of them and actively live his life thoughtfully and purposefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my studying and notes of Meditations, I categorized these themes by what I determined practical and important. Other people (who are more knowledgeable on Marcus’s Meditations) may group the themes differently. Mine are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daily Attitudes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Happiness, purpose, your value, desires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What other people think&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obstacles and Fate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leadership and how to treat others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goals and time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditations is divided into several chapters, each without a theme on its own (as far as I can tell). So the parts I highlighted are all from different chapters across the book. Similarly to the Bible, each note has its own number to make it easy to reference and find a quote in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each theme I’ve identified, I provided a brief summary and a few of my favorite notes on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-dailyattitude&quot;&gt;On Daily Attitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some universal pieces of wisdom in Meditations that I should always be top of mind, or even read to yourself each morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[2.1] When you wake up in the morning, tell yourself: The people I deal with today will be meddling, ungrateful, arrogant, dishonest, jealous, and surly. They are like this because they can’t tell good from evil. But I have seen the beauty of good, and the ugliness of evil, and have recognized that the wrongdoer has a nature related to my own — not of the same blood or birth, but the same mind, and possessing a share of the divine. And so none of them can hurt me. No one can implicate me in ugliness. Nor can I feel angry at my relative, or hate him. We were born to work together like feet, hands, and eyes, like the two rows of teeth, upper and lower. To obstruct each other is unnatural. To feel anger at someone, to turn your back on him: these are obstructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t expect everything to go your way so you won’t be surprised and react when they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[6.13] Like seeing roasted meat and other dishes in front of you and suddenly realizing: This is a dead fish. A dead bird. A dead pig. Or that this noble vintage is grape juice, and the purple robes are sheep wool dyed with shellfish blood. Or making love — something rubbing against your penis, a brief seizure and a little cloudy liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Perceptions like that — latching onto things and piercing through them, so we see what they really are. That’s what we need to do all the time — all through our lives when things lay claim to our trust — to lay them bare and see how pointless they are, to strip away the legend that encrusts them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy for desires to consume your thoughts at the cost of your peace and your ability to think and do more virtuous things. Grounding your perceptions can clear restlessness and allow space for gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[10.25] When a slave runs away from his master, we call him a fugitive slave. But the law of nature is a master too, and to break it is to become a fugitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To feel grief, anger, or fear is to try to escape from something decreed by the ruler of all things, now or in the past or in the future. And that ruler is law, which governs what happens to each of us. To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive — a fugitive from justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large majority of events that cause us to grieve, feel anger, or fear are outside of our control. And if they are out of our control, we could not have prevented it. Accept that things happen because they simply happen. Outbursts of anger or long periods of grief don’t ever fix anything, but only make you worse off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[10.8] Epithets for yourself: Upright. Modest. Straightforward. Sane. Cooperative. Disinterested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Try not to exchange them for others. And if you should forfeit them, set about getting them back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that “sanity” means understanding things — each individual thing — for what they are. And not losing the thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And “cooperation” means accepting what nature assigns you — accept it willingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And “disinterest” means that the intelligence should rise above the movements of the flesh — the rough and smooth alike. Should rise above fame, above death, and everything like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you maintain your claim to these epithets — without caring if others apply them to your or not — you’ll become a new person, living a new life. To keep on being the person that you’ve been — to keep being mauled and degraded by the life you’re living — is to be devoid of sense and much too fond of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-happiness-purpose-your-valuedesires&quot;&gt;On Happiness, Purpose, Your Value, Desires&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus found happiness by suppressing desire, ignoring what other people think, appreciating the moment, and accepting what happens as natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[7.27] Treat what you don’t have as nonexistent. Look at what you have, the things you value most, and think of how much you’d crave them if you didn’t have them. But be careful. Don’t feel such satisfaction that you start to overvalue them — that it would upset you to lose them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good exercise to think (or write in your journal) about what you have as a reminder that you have them. This helps suppress desire and increase gratitude for the fortune you have in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[7.3] Remember that our own worth is measured by what we devote our energy to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you think about and what you do every day casts votes for who you are, exactly &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes&quot;&gt;what James Clear reminds us in Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[6.16] What is it in ourselves that we should prize?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not just transpiration (even plants do that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Or respiration (even beasts and wild animals breathe).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Or being struck by passing thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Or jerked like a puppet by your own impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Or moving in herds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Or eating, and relieving yourself afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then what is to be prized?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An audience clapping? No. No more than the clacking of their tongues. Which is all that public praise amounts to — a clacking of tongues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So we throw out other people’s recognition. What’s left for us to prize?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think it’s this: to do (and not do) what we were designed for. That’s the goal of all trades, all arts, and what each of them aims at: that the thing they create should do what it was designed to do. The nurseryman who cares for the vines, the horse trainer, the dog breeder — this is what they aim at. And teaching and education — what else are they trying to accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So that’s what we should prize. Hold on to that, and you won’t be tempted to aim at anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And if you can’t stop prizing a lot of other things? Then you’ll never be free — free, independent, imperturbable. Because you’ll always be envious and jealous, afraid that people might come and take it all away from you. Plotting against those who have them — those things you prize. People who need those things are bound to be a mess — and bound to take out their frustration on the gods. Whereas to respect your own mind — to prize it — will leave you satisfied with your own self, well integrated into your community and in tune with the gods as well — embracing what they allot you, and what they ordain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great summation of everything Marcus views as the path to happiness and tranquility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-what-other-peoplethink&quot;&gt;On What Other People Think&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggle heavily with comparing myself to others and caring too much about what other people think, so I grouped Marcus’s thoughts on the subject into its own theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does Marcus have to say on this topic? Two things: 1) you can’t control what other people think about you, so don’t worry about it, and 2) it’s foolish to entrust your happiness to others when you can entrust it to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[2.6] Yes, keep on degrading yourself, soul. But soon your chance at dignity will be gone. Everyone gets one life. Yours is almost used up, and instead of treating yourself with respect, you have entrusted your own happiness to the souls of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Nuff said. #yolo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[6.18] The way people behave. They refuse to admire their contemporaries, the people whose lives they share. No, but to be admired by Posterity — people they’ve never met and never will — that’s what they set their hearts on. You might as well be upset at not being a hero to your great-grandfather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all like to idolize actors, musicians, or start up founders, but why not the people we actually know and interact with? Your family, your friends, or even coworkers? People who can care about you back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[7.71] It’s silly to try to escape other people’s faults. They are inescapable. Just try to escape your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will inevitably disappoint people. The only opinion of yourself that matters is yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[9.30] To see them from above: the thousands of animal herds, the rituals, the voyages on calm or stormy seas, the different ways we come into the word, share it with one another, and leave it. Consider the lives led once by others, long ago, the lives to be led by others after you, the lives led even now, in foreign lands. How many people don’t even know your name. How many will soon have forgotten it. How many offer you praise now — and tomorrow, perhaps, contempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That to be remembered is worthless. Like fame. Like everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why make a legacy your ultimate goal in life? No matter who you are, people will eventually forget you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[12.4] It never ceases to amaze me: we all love ourselves more than other people, but care more about their opinion than our own. If a god appeared to us — or a wise human being, even — and prohibited us from concealing our thoughts or imagining anything without immediately shouting it out, we wouldn’t make it through a single day. That’s how much we value other people’s opinions — instead of our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just accept people are thinking nasty things about you and you won’t be surprised if/when they make it evident. You won’t be affected because you saw that it could come. So don’t be afraid to be yourself and don’t change your opinion to try and fit in with the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-obstacles-andfate&quot;&gt;On Obstacles and Fate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important tenets of Stoicism is the understanding and application of knowing what’s in your control and what is not. If it is not in your control, you should accept it as “what nature demanded” (or fate). And what nature demands is neither good nor bad. It just is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[4.7] Choose not to be harmed — and you won’t feel harmed. Don’t feel harmed — and you haven’t been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst part of an unfavorable event is not the event itself, but the emotion that takes over you. If you didn’t get the promotion you wanted, the anger and grief you display at the office in retaliation will do you more harm than the event of not getting the promotion did. Or getting frustrated and anxious about traffic is worse for you then the traffic itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[6.41] You take things you don’t control and define them as “good” or “bad.” And so of course when the “bad” things happen, or the “good” ones don’t, you blame the gods and feel hatred for the people responsible — or those you decide to make responsible. Much of our bad behavior stems from trying to apply those criteria. If we limited “good” and “bad” to our own actions, we’d have no call to challenge God, or to treat other people as enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no value or usefulness in labeling an event as bad (or good). If it happened, it happened and there wasn’t anything you can do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[8.15] Remember: You shouldn’t be surprised that a fig tree produces figs, nor the world what it produces. A good doctor isn’t surprised when his patients have fevers, or a helmsman when the wind blows against him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People (even friends or family) can do or say things that hurt you, bother you, or get in your way. And it shouldn’t surprise you because they are human. And if it doesn’t surprise you, you’re less likely to be hurt or affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[5.20] In a sense, people are our proper occupation. Our job is to do them good and put up with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But when they obstruct our proper tasks, they become irrelevant to us — like sun, wind, animals. Our actions may be impeded by them, but there can be no impeding our intentions or our dispositions. Because we can accommodate and adapt. The mind adapts and converts to its own purposes the obstacles to our acting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The impediment to action advances action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What stands in the way becomes the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-leadership-and-how-to-treatothers&quot;&gt;On Leadership and How to Treat Others&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus didn’t write about leadership directly, but because he was an emperor, he was a leader to everyone around him. Still, his main focus was to not let people upset him and to gently help set them straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[7.22] To feel affection for people even when they make mistakes is uniquely human. You can do it, if you simply recognize: that they’re human too, that they act out of ignorance, against their will, and that you’ll both be dead before long. And, above all, that they haven’t really hurt you. They haven’t diminished your ability to choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the use of getting upset or frustrated at other people when life is short. One, the act of being upset or frustrated hurts you when you don’t need to let that happen, and two you lose the opportunity to help those other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[7.26] When people injure you, ask yourself what good or harm they thought would come of it. If you understand that, you’ll feel sympathy rather than outrage or anger. Your sense of good and evil may be the same as theirs, or near it, in which case you have to excuse them. Or your sense of good and evil may differ from theirs. In which case they’re misguided and deserve your compassion. Is that so hard?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A logical way to withhold anger, disappointment, and frustration at other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[8.17] If it’s in your control, why do you do it? If it’s in someone else’s, then who are you blaming? Atoms? The gods? Stupid either way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blame no one. Set people straight, if you can. If not, just repair the damage. And suppose you can’t do that either. Then where does blaming people get you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No pointless actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything people do comes from many different influences. It’s not really them as a person making a decision on their own, even if it seems that way on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-goals-andtime&quot;&gt;On Goals and Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big tenants of Stoicism is the reflection on the shortness of life (memento mori). Often, Marcus reminds himself that life is short so it’s best to not waste time and get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[2.7] Do external things distract you? Then make time for yourself to learn something worthwhile; stop letting yourself be pulled in all directions. But make sure you guard against the other kind of confusion. People who labor all their lives but have no purpose to direct every thought and impulse toward are wasting their time — even when hard at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus. If you identify what your goal is, strive to make a step forward everyday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[4.43] Time is a river, a violent current of events, glimpsed once and already carried past us, and another follows and is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus often makes the analogy of viewing time as a river. It’s useful to remind us to live in the present and forget the past, but also to remember that legacy after you die is meaningless because eventually no one will remember you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[5.1] You don’t love yourself enough. Or you’d love your nature too, and what it demands of you. People who love what they do wear themselves down doing it, they even forget to wash or eat. Do you have less respect for your own nature than the engraver does for engraving, the dancer for the dance, the miser for money or the social climber for status? When they’re really possessed by what they do, they’d rather stop eating and sleeping than give up practicing their arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to figure this out and sometimes it changes in our lives (e.g. a dancer can’t be a dancer forever). But once you find it, do it everyday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[6.51] Ambition means tying your well-being to what other people say or do.&lt;br /&gt;
Self indulgence means tying to the things that happen to you. &lt;br /&gt;
Sanity means tying it to your own actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to achieve tranquility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[9.29] Do what nature demands. Get a move on — if you have it in you — and don’t worry whether anyone will give you credit for it. And do so expecting Plato’s Republic; be satisfied with even the smallest progress, and treat the outcome of it all as unimportant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step-by-step. Action-by-action. It doesn’t have to be perfect as long as you make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anger&quot;&gt;Anger&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[11.18.vi] When you lose your temper, or even feel irritated: that human life is very short. Before long all of us will be laid out side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting frustrated or angry is a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[11.18.vii] How much more damage anger and grief do than the things that cause them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And harms you more than the event itself that caused it, because it’s hurting your state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[11.18] When you start to lose your temper, remember: There’s nothing manly about rage. It’s courtesy and kindness that define a human being — and a man. That’s who possesses strength and nerves and guts, not the angry whiners. To react like that brings you closer to impassivity — and so to strength. Pain is the opposite of strength, and so is anger. Both are things we suffer from, and yield to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Nuff said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[12.26] To be angry at something means you’ve forgotten:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That everything that happens is natural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That the responsibility is theirs, not yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And further…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That whatever happens has always happened, and always will, and is happening at this very moment, everywhere. Just like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What links one human being to all humans: not blood or birth, but mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That it’s all how you choose to see things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That the present is all we have to live in. Or to lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-death&quot;&gt;On Death&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[6.49] It doesn’t bother you that you weigh only x or y pounds and not three hundred. Why should it bother you have only x or y years to live and not more? You accept the limits placed on our body. Accept those placed on your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Death is inevitable and expected. By letting it bothering you, you’re obstructing nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[9.3] Don’t look down on death, but welcome it. It too is one of the things required by nature. Like youth and old age. Like growth and maturity. Like a new set of teeth, a beard, the first gray hair. Like sex and pregnancy and childbirth. Like all other physical changes at each stage of life, our dissolution is no different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So this is how a thoughtful person should await death: not with indifference, not with impatience, not with disdain, but simply viewing it as one of the things that happen to us. How you anticipate the child’s emergence from its mother’s womb; that’s how you should await the hour when your soul will emerge from its compartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus wrote a lot on death. I think he feared it a lot and that’s why he wrote pretty much the same message in so many different ways — implying from my point of view that he needed these reminders often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[9.17] A rock thrown in the air. It loses nothing by coming down, gained nothing by going up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you took the time to read some of these quotes, you’ll see why this summary is so long. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0812968255/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0812968255&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=8dbf0e74c04495dc6d0390c6e1d2e404&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt; has been the most influential book on my life. At a time where I felt I lack a purpose or satisfaction with my life (of course these feelings and thoughts still occur), Meditations is helping me push through and find tranquility. Easily, Meditations is a 10/10 must read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The essential book to help you find your purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mastery-book-summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;mastery book summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Marcus Aurelius was an ancient Roman emperor from the years 161 to 180. And we have access to his personal journals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gymaholic App Review: The Best Gym App for Workout Tracking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gymaholic-app-review-the-best-gym-app-for-workout-tracking" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gymaholic App Review: The Best Gym App for Workout Tracking" /><published>2018-11-29T18:41:56-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-29T18:41:56-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gymaholic-app-review-the-best-gym-app-for-workout-tracking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gymaholic-app-review-the-best-gym-app-for-workout-tracking">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gymaholic-workout-tracker/id648518560?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gymaholic&lt;/a&gt; religiously for exactly a year now and have tracked every workout with it. Below is my review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been paying for the premium version for about a year now and so the below review doesn’t distinguish between what’s in the free vs. the paid to keep it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-lets-talkdesign&quot;&gt;First, Let’s Talk Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is just such a big thing to me. I have to love using and being in the app. At first, I hated Gymaholic’s design — I’ll admit it. I even think I deleted it because it was so complex. I tried to get used to it and I just gave up. But when I tried other apps, it made me realize just how good Gymaholic actually is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, tracking your workouts to a point of actually being useful is very number based in nature. The only way to get around it is to dumb it down. What I now appreciate about Gymaholic is they didn’t dumb it down, but they’ve worked to keep their interfaces as clean as possible. For example, the Apple Watch app looks great, but is incredibly useful. They’ve cleverly hid advanced features and controls behind force touches (or long presses) that make the Apple Watch app itself seemingly complete app on its own— so much so I don’t even open the iPhone app while working out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got the hang of it, I began to love it. It had a steep learning curve, but as I got used to it, I really appreciated just how much it can do. It’s very flexible to my needs and gives me more data than I ever need (or want).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and two words: Dark Mode. Yes, one of my favorite things about it. And it has a true dark mode. Straight black. Looks great on my iPhone X with the OLED screen. (Side note: I think it was actually originally made with a black background and they added white later)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing I’ll say about the design is something I thought was a total gimmick, but turned out to be pretty useful. It uses augment reality (AR) really well. For every built in exercise in Gymaholic, you can see a video of a person doing it. You can spin them around and see the model perform it from different angles. But with AR, you can actually bring the model out of the app and into the space around you. I thought this was a gimmick, but for complex exercises (like a barbell row or deadlift), seeing the model in the gym, performing the exercise, with the ability to zoom and twist, actually helped me learn and improve my form to prevent injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AR helps teach proper form and give cues for what muscles to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I give Gymaholic’s design a 9/10. Pretty much everything is great, but the reports + charts leave a little to be desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-itworks&quot;&gt;How it Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has a ton of Exercises you can group together as a Workout. Each exercise has a 3D model to show you how it’s done and what primary and secondary muscles the exercise works. There is also a description to help explain it and help provide the right cues to make sure you do it right. They have all kinds of exercises from dumbbell, barbell, body-weight, machine, kettlebell, and even cardio exercises. If they don’t have an exercise you like, you can add a custom one and enter the data yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make as many workouts as you want. A Workout is essentially just one session. You can group together multiple Workouts if you’re following a program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ONE: List of Workouts. TWO: Detailed Workout View. THREE: Detailed Exercise View.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you complete a workout, it sends all the data to the Health app. The Gymaholic home screen will also show you what muscles need resting and which are at 100% so it’s easy to pick out your next workout. I’ll get to more about reports further down, but you can also see reports of how much you’re working out the different parts of your body so you can see if something isn’t even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img sml-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using an Apple Watch so during a workout, I do everything from there. The Apple Watch app tells you what exercise is up, which set you’re on, and how many reps you need to do at what weight. Once you do it, tap the “set ring” and it logs the set while starting a rest countdown timer (which you can customize on a per exercise OR workout basis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They just added the ability to swipe right to see the model performing the exercise, or swipe left to control your music or audio — which is SUPER convenient (AHH I just love how the devs keep adding little touches that just make this app perfect).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sml-img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ONE: Home screen on Apple Watch. TWO: Looping video of exercise on swipe right. THREE: Music controls on swipe left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where it gets even more convenient. What if you need to adjust your workouts on the fly? You can force touch the set ring to open a hidden menu of options where you can adjust the number of sets, the reps, or weight. You can even add in another exercise if you want!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sml-img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic11.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic12.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic13.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Force touch (or long press) on the Apple Watch allows you to edit sets, reps, and weight on the fly. You can also add in new exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the workout, Gymaholic gives you the option whether you want to save those changes to the Workout so next time you do that Workout, you’ll do the adjust sets, reps, weight, exercises that you modified. Or, you have the option to not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on and on about what else this app does, but I’m going to leave it at that for functionality. I would be impressed if this app doesn’t work with your workout routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of functionality, Gymaholic gets a 10/10 easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tracking-progress&quot;&gt;Tracking Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the History tab, you can see a monthly calendar view of all the days you’ve completed at least one workout. Or you can switch to list view and see all your workouts completed from most recent to oldest including the workout name, date, and duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the bottom is a row of prebuilt charts and reports. In terms of habit tracking, my goal is simply to go to the gym 4x per week — nothing more detailed than that. The most important thing for me is to make sure I keep getting my ass to the gym. Tracking this is wonderful in Gymaholic. I love how it just has a simple bar chart for the number of Workouts completed per month. You can adjust the date range to show the data just how you want. Me? I like to see the last 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic14.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic15.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic16.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ONE: Calendar of completed workouts. TWO: Or a list view. THREE: You can add your favorite charts to your home screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you cycle through the built in charts, you can pin them to your Gymaholic home screen so they’re always right there when you open the app. I always know how many times I’ve been to the gym this month vs last month. I always know what muscles are rested, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only can you track progress of your workouts and strength gains, you can also track progress with your body. You can take progress pics and add measurements for most parts of your body so you know beyond just wait what parts of your slimming down, what parts are getting bigger, and how your body is changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s so much more in tracking progress and the reports that I could keep going, but this covers the major parts of it. If you’re a real gym rat or data nerd, you’re going to love the details and stats these reports offer. Overall, I give Gymaholic’s tracking and reporting features a 9/10. It tracks a lot, but I wish the charts were a bit more customizable and looked a bit more polished, but for the most part, it gets the job done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;price&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gymaholic-workout-tracker/id648518560?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gymaholic&lt;/a&gt; does run on a subscription model, but it’s SO worth it. To get all the features with the premium version, it costs $4.99 per month or $31.99 annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done app review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been using Gymaholic religiously for exactly a year now and have tracked every workout with it. Below is my review.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker" /><published>2018-11-22T10:17:19-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-22T10:17:19-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app">&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had miserable success with tracking habits until I found an app called &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/done-a-simple-habit-tracker/id1103961876?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Done&lt;/a&gt;. I would always start off strong, then the number of days in a row I would log would taper off until I stopped completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried spreadsheets, a pen and planner system, and a variety of apps, but I couldn’t stick to any of them (until Done).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why track your habits at all? Because seeing your progress and not wanting to break the number of days (or weeks) in a row you’ve done your habit is a strong motivation in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Making progress is satisfying, and visual measures provide clear evidence of your progress. As a result, they reinforce your behavior and add a little bit of immediate satisfaction to any activity. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— James Clear, &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So obviously the most important thing in a habit tracking system is one that you can stick to — no matter how it looks or how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other systems and apps didn’t work because they were either too much work to fill out each day (friction) or weren’t fun to use (not rewarding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;done-is-everything-i-needed-in-a-habit-trackingapp&quot;&gt;Done Is Everything I Needed In a Habit Tracking App&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great design (I’m &lt;strong&gt;attracted&lt;/strong&gt; to using it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to use (there shouldn’t be unnecessary &lt;strong&gt;friction&lt;/strong&gt; to track habits)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fun when completing habits (&lt;strong&gt;rewarding&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robust reports to see + feel good about my progress (also &lt;strong&gt;rewarding&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/done-a-simple-habit-tracker/id1103961876?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Done&lt;/a&gt; has dark mode. Already a huge winner there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has an awesome design. I like the icon, I like the bright colors, and I like how the home screen looks on both my iPhone and on my Apple Watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can customize the color of your habits, too. If you want to use all the same color or groups of colors to signify a type (e.g. good vs bad habits), the app lets you do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rate the design an 8/10. It’s great, especially compared to competitors. It’s more than good enough to keep me comfortable using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ease-ofuse&quot;&gt;Ease of Use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me a few minutes of exploring to get used to how the app worked, but was pretty intuitive once I learned the overall structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of different options to set up how you want to track a habit. You can set a goal for &lt;strong&gt;x&lt;/strong&gt; number of times per day, week, or month, which gives you the flexibility to track daily habits or a habit you want to do 3&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of new habits — ONE: New habit once per day. TWO: New habit twice per week. THREE: Limit bad habit to no more than three per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also easy to track bad habits you want to limit or all out quit. For example, you can add a bad habit and set the limit to 3&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; per week (what I do for video games), or to zero times per day if you want to quit it.The Apple Watch app is also a great way to quickly mark a habit as done while on the go + right in the moment (unlike a spreadsheet or handwritten tracker).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;done-apple-watchapp&quot;&gt;Done Apple Watch App&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you set up your habits on the iPhone app, you can use the Watch app to mark habits as done while on the go and at the moment of completing the habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img sml-img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LEFT: Complication bottom middle. RIGHT: App view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you set up Habits for work, you can mark them done while at work right from your watch. The app lists your habits in the order you choose on the iPhone app and always displays the goal for each habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for complications, Done only has the small icon complication for quickly opening the app from your Watch face. It would be nice to have a larger complication show you the next habit you have up to complete for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t do anything else, but it doesn’t really need to either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-itworks&quot;&gt;How It Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mark a habit as complete, you tap the habit once on the home screen. The habit will turn from a light gray to the bright color you selected. This small subtle change does feel rewarding in itself. Everyday I want to turn all my habits their bright color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For habits with a goal of 3&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; per week for example, Done thought of a neat little trick that looks like a progress bar. Only a portion of the “habit bar” will turn a color signifying there’s still some way to go (see my Gym habit below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ONE: A grey background means the habit is incomplete. TWO: A bright color means the habit is complete or in progress of being completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the app’s home screen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/done-a-simple-habit-tracker/id1103961876?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Done&lt;/a&gt; gives you two different customization choices to display the information you care about most: 1) the big number on the left of the habit to display streaks, count, or left-to-goal, and 2) a line of text below the habit name for motivational notes or time since last completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, I care most about my streaks so I display it in a large number. Streaks are the number of days in a row you complete a habit (weekly habit streaks are counted as weeks in a row). So each day I complete a habit, I can see the streak rise by one which is also pretty rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also care about how long it’s been since I last completed a habit. This is better for habits that are set up as an X number of times per week so I can see how long it’s been since I last did it. I also switch every once in a while to displaying notes at the bottom of each habit to reinforce that each habit is contributing to my desired identity — an important technique for sticking to habits I learned from the book &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img lg-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;You can customize the big number on the right and the small text below the habit name.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can customize the big number on the right and the small text below the habit name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tracking-progress&quot;&gt;Tracking Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have both a calendar view of your habits and a chart view so you can see when you did or didn’t do your habits, how many times a habit was completed in any given period, and your current and longest streaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;a-img img-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/done11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ONE: Calendar view of one habit. TWO: Month-over-month comparison. THREE: Daily comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their reporting system makes it super easy to compare how I did week-over-week and month-over-month. And it’s all in there automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/done-a-simple-habit-tracker/id1103961876?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Done&lt;/a&gt;, I don’t think I’d be able to keep up my habits, because visually seeing the progress is extremely powerful. I rate their reporting features a 9/10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;price&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/done-a-simple-habit-tracker/id1103961876?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Done&lt;/a&gt; is not using a subscription model. They have a free tier that lets you track just a few habits and the premium tier for only $5.99 lets you add unlimited habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Break Bad Habits for Good&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The best tips from Atomic Habits on breaking your worse habits&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to break bad habits&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits — Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/gymaholic-app-review-the-best-gym-app-for-workout-tracking&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Gymaholic App Review: The Best Gym App for Workout Tracking&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;No other app comes even close.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/gymaholic-app-review-the-best-gym-app-for-workout-tracking&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gymaholic review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;gymaholic review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve always had miserable success with tracking habits until I found an app called Done. I would always start off strong, then the number of days in a row I would log would taper off until I stopped completely.</summary></entry></feed>