<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-26T23:45:28-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">regpaq</title><subtitle>B2B Marketer. Avid reader &amp; writer.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;regpaq&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Untethered Soul by Michael Singer—Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/untethered-soul-summary-notes-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Untethered Soul by Michael Singer—Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2023-10-26T05:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-26T05:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/untethered-soul-summary-notes-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/untethered-soul-summary-notes-quotes">&lt;p&gt;I’m not a spiritual person and certainly don’t believe we have souls. So when a good friend recommended me the Untethered Soul by Michael Singer, I was hesitant about reading it. But after getting it, reading it, and writing my thoughts about it, surely this friend owes it me to read a book I recommend, right? Well I’d say that’s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokes aside, I did find a few excellent insights and thought exercises helpful in calming and exploring my thoughts. However, I largely disagree on much of Singer’s metaphysics and how he arrives at the conclusions he does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/untethered-soul-michael-singer-book-cover.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/untethered-soul-michael-singer-book-cover.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/untethered-soul-michael-singer-book-cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Buy The Untethered Soul on Amazon&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Untethered-Soul-Journey-Beyond-Yourself/dp/1572245379?&amp;amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=65730e08500e6523caca641e91a6e603&amp;amp;language=en_US&amp;amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl&quot;&gt;Buy The Untethered Soul on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-i-awakening-consciousness&quot;&gt;Part I. Awakening Consciousness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness is on a scale. We can be less conscious or more conscious, with the highest level of consciousness described as “true inner freedom.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start awakening our consciousness, it begins with being aware of our thoughts (Singer calls this “the voice inside our head”) and acknowledging that our thoughts are not what we call “us”. It is explained that because we can hear this voice inside our head and we can digest what it’s saying, that means who we are (the Self) and our thoughts are separate things. “We” are just the ones who hear it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To be aware that you are watching the voice talk is to stand on the threshold of a fantastic inner journey.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do think this is true. When I’m careful to pay attention to the thoughts in my head, I can start asking why those thoughts are appearing. For most of our thoughts, we can look toward the causes and influences. When I understand what’s causing and influencing my thoughts, I can attempt to turn up positive influences and turn down negative influences (that are within my control).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although moderating our influences is not an exercise discussed in the book, Singer teaches two other positive mindset techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some negative thoughts are regarding the outside world. But since we have no control of the outside world, this is “incessant chatter” and we can dismiss them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some of thoughts are nonsensical and unreasonably negative, which we can learn to acknowledge their appearance (because we can’t exactly prevent them) and should also dismiss them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Eventually you will see that the real cause of problems is not life itself. It’s the commotion the mind makes about life that really causes problems.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I don’t agree that the “voice in my head” is not a part of me, these are fantastic techniques we should practice throughout the day as often as possible. It reminds me of the Stoic philosopher Seneca who said, “We often suffer more in imagination than reality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear whether he considers the voice a part of the consciousness or a completely different entity (It seems the voice must be separate from consciousness, otherwise he must concede our consciousness is not wholly ours). At one point, he says the voice is not who we are, and at another says it’s the other half of our inner being. The questions of why the voice exists is answered unsatisfyingly as “a buildup of energy inside that needs to be released.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s even more unclear when he discusses who the author of the voice in our head is, which he makes analogous to an “inner roommate.” At one point he says, “&lt;em&gt;when you’re just thinking, you’re free to create whatever thoughts you want in your mind, and these thoughts are expressed through the voice.&lt;/em&gt;” This means we’re in control of our thoughts (and doesn’t this contradict that the voice isn’t us?). However, at another point he says, “&lt;em&gt;you may have a clear intention to be quiet inside, but your roommate won’t cooperate&lt;/em&gt;,” which implies we don’t control our thoughts. I think he believes we’re only in control of some of our thoughts/voice, and through practice we can work to control more of it, but we don’t control it completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serious problems arise however when he tries to make this idea applicable. He says, “&lt;em&gt;If you want to achieve peace in the face of your problems, you must understand why you perceive a particular situation as a problem.&lt;/em&gt;” He uses the experience of feeling jealous to explain. When we feel jealousy, ask ourselves, “&lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; part of me &lt;em&gt;is jealous?&lt;/em&gt;” If we can identify the &lt;em&gt;part of us&lt;/em&gt; that is jealous, that means &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; are not the one experiencing jealousy (because &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; are just the observer). Therefore we can dismiss the feeling, because it’s not ours, it’s our &lt;em&gt;inner roommate’s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This appears to me as being an extremely unhealthy and incomplete way of dealing with negative feelings. I would rather:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify the feeling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;determine the causes and influence of the feeling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify which causes are inside or outside of my control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work to change the situation that’s in my control and attempt to accept/let go what is not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singer suggests this technique should be applied to all the negative things our inner roommate is telling us, but how do we identify what is our bad inner roommate from what Singer calls our “willful intentions?” For example, let’s say I’m thinking of quitting my job because I’m unhappy and underpaid. If I dismiss this as a negative thought from my inner roommate, it’s possible I could learn to be less unhappy about it, but I could very well be prolonging a poor situation and forgoing the opportunity to earn more. On the other hand, I might be telling myself that quitting is a bad idea because there is no guarantee I’ll land a job I’ll be happier at and with higher pay. If I dismiss this thought and go through with quitting, I very well could go on for months without a job, my savings spent, and the only job I could get has even less favorable conditions than the job I just quit. In this situation, how would I determine which negative thought is from my inner roommate and which should be dismissed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem arises around positive feelings, like happiness. Couldn’t I identify the part of me that is happy? This would mean that it’s not me who’s feeling happy, but it’s my inner roommate who is. Should I dismiss the feeling of happiness as I dismiss the feeling of unhappiness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if I’m not my thoughts or feelings, who am &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;? What is &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;? Singer’s best answer to this question is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I am the one who sees. From the back in here somewhere, I look out, and I am aware of the events, thoughts, and emotions that pass before me.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add further clarification, he says our mind is not &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; either. The mind can be used, so there must be a user. This is how he arrives at the existence of souls and claims the center of consciousness is the “&lt;em&gt;seat of the Buddhist Self, the Hindu Atman, and the Judeo-Christian Soul.&lt;/em&gt;” He goes on to say, “&lt;em&gt;You’re not even a human being. You just happen to be watching one.&lt;/em&gt;” Of course, there is no evidence for the existence of souls. &lt;strong&gt;I believe we are purely material. We have a body and a part of that body is the mind. We’ve defined our subjective experience as “consciousness” and we know that it is a product of the brain. I can get a heart transplant, and I’d still be the same person. That wouldn’t be the case if I got a brain transplant. Unless I believe I have a soul, then it must be true that our mind, thoughts, and emotions, including our awareness of them, is all a part of &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/free-will-doesnt-exist&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Free Will Doesn’t Exist&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;We can&amp;#39;t control our choices because we can&amp;#39;t control who we are and this changes everything.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/sam-harris-free-will-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/sam-harris-free-will-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/sam-harris-free-will-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/sam-harris-free-will-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/sam-harris-free-will.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sam Harris on free will&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the first section, it’s abundantly clear this book is aimed at helping people who are going through some difficulty in their lives. Many of Singer’s ideas are framed around obtaining “true personal growth”, “true inner freedom”, and “true spiritual awakening.” There is not any evidence or logical arguments to support why and how things are the way they are. It’s not that kind of book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Singers’s beliefs about consciousness don’t come from any published psychologists, neuroscientists, philosophers, or anything academic at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Fortunately, the nature of consciousness has been studied very closely in deep teachings such as yoga. In fact, the ancient teachings of yoga are all about consciousness. The best way to learn about consciousness is through your own direct experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Singer has many good ideas and positive mindset techniques, I think many are flawed. This is why it’s important to arrive at conclusions through evidence or, if not possible, logical arguments that hold up against philosophical scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-ii-experiencing-energy&quot;&gt;Part II. Experiencing Energy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside all of us is an unlimited amount of energy, but we don’t use it all the time because we block it off. Energy is blocked by “&lt;em&gt;closing your heart, by closing your mind, and by pulling yourself into a restrictive space inside.&lt;/em&gt;” This energy is “&lt;em&gt;what you’re experiencing when love rushes up into your heart… [and] …when you’re enthused by something and all this high energy comes up inside of you.&lt;/em&gt;” This energy “&lt;em&gt;can even affect the health of your body… When you start to feel the tendency of an illness coming on, you just relax and open. When you open, you bring more energy into the system, and it can heal.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blockages occur at energy centers inside of us and the one we know most intuitively is the heart (the figurative/spiritual heart). We can remove blockages and access this energy more often by learning how not to close ourselves off in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I don’t believe in souls or spiritual energy, ironically it is in this section I find my favorite passages in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Do not let anything that happens in life be important enough that you’re willing to close your heart over it. When your heart starts to close, just say, ‘No. I’m not going to close. I’m going to relax. I’m going to let this situation take place and be there with it.’ Honor and respect the situation, and deal with it. By all means deal with it. Do the best you can. But deal with it with openness. Deal with it with excitement and enthusiasm.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I interpret “to close” in Singer’s metaphysics as to be affected by something outside of my control. It’s a challenge to the reader to be better every day in every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, thoughts of embarrassing things I’ve done in my past often come through my inner roommate and “haunt” me. It happens about one to three times per day. These are an example of what’s called Samskaras, which are past energy patterns that we’ve stored. How to deal with them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If old energies come back up because you were unable to process them before, let go of them now. It’s that easy… Be happy that this Samskara, which has been stored down there for all this time, has the opportunity to make it through you. Just open, relax your heart, forgive, laugh, or do anything you want. Just don’t push it back down. Of course it hurts when it comes up. It was stored with pain; it’s going to release with pain. You have to decide if you want to continue to walk around with stored pain blocking your heart and limiting your life. The alternative is to be willing to let it go when it gets stimulated. It only hurt for a minute and then it’s over.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m reminded that the past is out of my control. Perhaps there are things that are within my control that I can do to help remedy these Samskara’s, but it’s important I remember that what’s happened has happened. Trying to suppress the memory isn’t going to help - as evident by their frequent reappearance. It’s better to acknowledge the Samskara, acknowledge that it’s out of my control, and laugh about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to new, negative or unproductive thoughts that arise throughout the day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When the energies inside start to move, you do not have to go there. For instance, when your thoughts start, you do not have to with them. Let’s say you’re outside taking a walk and a car drives by. Your thoughts say, ‘Boy, I wish I had that car.’ You could just keep on walking, but instead you start getting upset. You want a car like that, but your salary isn’t high enough. So you begin thinking about how you can get a raise or a different job. You didn’t have to do all that. It could have just been - here comes the car and there it goes, and here comes the thought and there it goes. They’re both gone together because you didn’t go with them.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first did meditation, I realized how valuable the skill of clearing my mind was. Like Singer says, my mind doesn’t want to stay quiet and often these thoughts are counterproductive to my tranquility. The exercise of meditation teaches us how to clear our mind such that we can do it all throughout the day, not just when sitting still with our eyes closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iii-let-go-now-or-fall&quot;&gt;Part III. Let Go Now or Fall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the topic of fear, Singer’s ideas are somewhat interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We think we’re supposed to figure out how life should be, and then make it that way. Only someone who looks deeper, and questions why we need the events of life to be a particular way, will we question this assumption. How did we come up with the notion that life is not okay just the way it is, or that it won’t be okay the way it will be? Who said that the way life naturally unfolds is not all right?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m drawn to his Stoic ideas, which to be fair, strongly overlaps with the foundation of his philosophy. Marcus Aurelius said, “To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive - a fugitive from justice.” And I like that. However, that’s the end of what I find interesting about his ideas on fear. He says “fear is the cause of every problem” and any feeling of fear should be completely eradicated. I can get behind a message of courage and bravery, but completely disregarding fear leads to rashness and detrimental endings. I see fear as a tool and there are better ways to determine whether my fear should be dismissed or heeded than always choosing to dismiss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2.png&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But right after the chapter on fear is my favorite thus far, &lt;em&gt;Removing Your Inner Thorn.&lt;/em&gt; It’s one of my favorites, because I recognize I have a lot of thorns, which are essentially deep sources of disturbances or sensitives inside us. Examples of thorns I have are about my physical appearance, rejection, creative prowess - I could go on. The most common way people deal with these thorns is they push them down or look outside for ways to fix them. For example, a person with sensitives to loneliness might avoid going to places where lots of couples go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to deal with thorns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure nothing touches it (avoid places with couples)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remove the thorn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we choose to make sure nothing touches it, we’re really modifying our life to navigate around them. In a sense, our thorns are running our lives. I’ve noticed in my own life that I can sometimes navigate around a deep fear or insecurity successfully, but that success is only temporary and it always comes back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to remove thorns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Because you’re always doing something to avoid feeling them, they are not given the chance to naturally work themselves out. If you want, you can simply permit the disturbances to come up, and you can let them go. Since your inner thorns are simply blocked energies from the past, they can be released. The problem is, you either completely avoid situations that would cause them to release, or you push them back down in the name of protecting yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best advice he has to offer us is to, again, let go. I just find this deeply unsatisfying, but at the same time, I don’t know what’s better. If I want to remove my thorn of my physical appearance insecurity, the outside things I might do to avoid this pain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avoid being in pictures or videos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;deleting certain social media apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;going to the gym&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;getting surgery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spending extra money and time on skincare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the first two are clear avoidances, the following three are also avoidances, but have arguments for being a remover (or solver). I’m always susceptible to getting out of shape again (or never in shape enough), finding something else on my face I want to change, or getting a breakout. &lt;strong&gt;However, getting in shape and taking care of my skin are low risk, high reward activities that should be pursued if I want to feel better about my physical appearance. They might not remove the thorn completely or forever, but they are much longer and proper solutions than the first two. And from another perspective, letting go of this disturbance could also be interpreted as avoiding it. It seems wrong to consider getting in shape and taking care of my skin to not be worthwhile endeavors as they are actually making an improvement at the source.&lt;/strong&gt; I remind myself there is only so much I can change about my physical appearance. I acknowledge I didn’t choose my body or what it looks like, but the insecurity still pops up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to say, “Once you learn that it’s okay to feel inner disturbances, and they can no longer disturb your seat of consciousness, you will be free.” Continuing with my example, this means to recognize that I am not my body and I am not my insecurity because I’m witnessing my body and my insecurity. I’m not convinced souls exist so I think my body, consciousness, and thoughts are all a part of what makes me, me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I will think on for a while and perhaps come back to later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iv-going-beyond&quot;&gt;Part IV. Going Beyond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until we start working on our “freedom” or become “spiritually awake,” we keep ourselves caged up in our comfort zone. The comfort zone is our expectations/mental model for how we expect events in our life to unfold. Living in our comfort zone is like trying to control the outside world. When things inevitably go awry, it causes us to be upset and disappointed. We can chose to live life devoted to our comfort zone, or we can devote our life to freeing ourselves from our comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not explicitly said, it seems Singer is saying before we free ourselves, we are not exercising free will. If we break out of our comfort zone, then we are free. The word “free” is used a lot, but I don’t believe he has really discussed free will specifically and what that means, at least as of yet. It’s interesting, however, that he supports the idea of causality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you really want to see why you do things, then don’t do them and see what happens. Let’s say you’re a smoker. If you decide to stop smoking, you quickly confront the urges that cause you to smoke. These urges are the reason you smoke. &lt;strong&gt;They are the outermost layer of cause. If you can sit through these urges, you will see what caused them. If you can get comfortable with what you see, you will face the next layer of causation, and so on, layer upon layer… There’s a reason for everything you do.&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition for there being an outside reason for everything we do, Singer also believes that “what thoughts we cling to and what person we create” is not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; up to us, with “just” implying &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have some free will here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There are acceptable and unacceptable social behaviors for almost everything - how to sit, how to walk, how to speak, how to dress, and how to feel about things. How does our society engrain these mental and emotional structures within us? When you do it well, you are rewarded with hugs and showered with positive accolades. When you don’t do it well, you are punished, either physically, mentally, or emotionally.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Singer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going beyond is breaking free from these causes and influences, but I don’t believe it’s possible to escape the natural causal order. It’s nonsensical. This doesn’t leave much room, if at all, for free will unless we believe in a “true self” that’s outside our mind and body.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I can’t help but picture Singer’s idea of our true self as that of a restrained passenger trapped inside of a material mind and body of which it is has no control over. All it can do is be aware of its mind’s and body’s stimulants. The only way any of this makes sense is that this isn’t actually real, but just a mind trick to help people feel better about themselves.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-v-living-life&quot;&gt;Part V. Living Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On happiness: Happiness is a choice. It’s under our control to be happy, but our comfort zone/model/expectations get in the way. Regardless of what happens, we can be happy. &lt;em&gt;“Events don’t determine whether or not you’re going to be happy. You determine whether or not you’re going to be happy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disagree with this. I can’t just choose to be happy any time I want. There are certain things that happen that can make me happy, but it is just a feeling, and that feeling will fade just like any other feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If you’re totally innocent and they lock you up, you might as well have fun.”&lt;/em&gt; I mean really? Tell that to someone imprisoned in a concentration camp. I don’t think I can choose to be happy, perhaps only artificially. And if there are things I can do within my control to improve my situation, I should still try to do them. If I’m imprisoned unjustly, I should still strive for a court hearing or to seek justice in whatever capacity I’m able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an ocean-sized difference between not letting small things bother me (like getting cut off in traffic) and being happy in the face of an objectively terrible situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On willpower: We (the Self) have the ability to resist the reality of life through our willpower. “The power of Self, when it is concentrated and directed into the physical, mental, or emotional realms, creates a force, and we call that force ‘will’”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He says if something happens we don’t like, we use our willpower to resist it. If our Self uses our willpower to resist, and emotions are a product of resisting, how does it not follow that our emotions are &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; emotions? He also says our willpower makes our arms and legs move, but earlier he said we are not even a human being. Either there is an inconsistency or contradiction with what Singer is saying is/isn’t &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; or under our control (earlier he said we’re not our emotions), or there are times our thoughts, actions, emotions are from our Self, and other times they are not. But how do we tell them apart?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really do think there are some good mindset techniques, perspectives, and thought exercises to improve our wellbeing in The Untethered Soul but I have fundamental disagreements on Singer’s metaphysics and how he arrives to these insights - and there are plenty of other insights I just simply disagree with or don’t follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can understand why this book and its message are so popular. I think the biggest theme in the book is letting go of expectations and emotions, especially with outside events that are not under our control. In Western philosophy at least, this theme was popularized in 300 BC with Stoicism, which has provided me several moments of clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I have with this book is Singer presupposes the existence of the soul, which isn’t a problem for new readers who already believe in the soul, but is a huge problem for someone like me. Many of the ideas, thought exercises, and perspectives he’s asking readers to take is fundamentally based on the claim souls exist, which leaves me without good reason to accept what he’s saying. &lt;strong&gt;I have read that many people have found this book life changing and I can understand why, but I don’t think it’s based fundamentally on truth. One might ask if it matters since people are benefiting from it, but I’d say that doesn’t make it any different than following a religion because it feels good to. I think it’s more wise to believe in dissatisfying truths than happy myths.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">I’m not a spiritual person and certainly don’t believe we have souls. So when a good friend recommended me the Untethered Soul by Michael Singer, I was hesitant about reading it. But after getting it, reading it, and writing my thoughts about it, surely this friend owes it me to read a book I recommend, right? Well I’d say that’s worth it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/untethered-soul-michael-singer.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/untethered-soul-michael-singer.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">War on Normal People—Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/war-on-normal-people-summary-notes-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="War on Normal People—Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2023-08-29T05:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-29T05:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/war-on-normal-people-summary-notes-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/war-on-normal-people-summary-notes-quotes">&lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang was a U.S. presidential candidate in the 2020 election who caught the attention of myself and millions of others through his unique approach to identifying and solving many of America’s problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems and solutions were published in his book &lt;em&gt;The War on Normal People&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-book-cover.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-book-cover.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-book-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Buy The War on Normal People on Amazon&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/War-Normal-People-Disappearing-Universal-ebook/dp/B075CRY4TZ?keywords=war+on+normal+people+andrew+yang&amp;amp;qid=1691294761&amp;amp;sprefix=war+on+normal+people%2Caps%2C157&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=aabce6b2856f3a6b0357d0893749897b&amp;amp;language=en_US&amp;amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl&quot;&gt;Buy The War on Normal People on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book had a big impact on me. I have a better understanding of the kind of life the average American has and it increased the empathy I have for those in our country who are less fortunate than me. Yang brings up a variety of problems Americans face (and solutions), which I haven’t heard from politicians before. This had me questioning “what are the success metrics for a country?” And not least of all, it convinced me universal basic income should be seriously considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is divided into three parts: jobs, people, and solutions. The thesis of each are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jobs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millions of jobs have and will continue to be lost to automation and artificial intelligence. New jobs created from emerging technology won’t cover the amount of jobs lost, new jobs will be consolidated in cities abundant with tech and highly educated talent, and the people who do lose their jobs can’t be trained to fill the new jobs. This will cause a “great displacement” of tens of millions of workers across the country, affecting rural and small cities the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second part, Yang reveals more of his personal philosophy as he shows how the quality of American life is deteriorating. This quote sets the stage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…many of us came up through the meritocracy and we’ve internalized its lessons. The underlying logic of the meritocratic system is this: if you’re successful, it’s because you’re smart and hardworking, and thus virtuous. If you’re poor or unsuccessful, it’s because you’re lazy and/or stupid and of subpar character. The people at the top belong there and the people at the bottom only have themselves to blame.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High rates of unemployment and under employment are linked to an array of social problems, including substance abuse, domestic violence, child abuse, drug abuse, depression, lower marriage rates, and the fragmentation of the family structure with rising rates of single mothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part three, Yang lays out his case for a new way forward, beginning with changing the utility of free market capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We must make the market serve humanity rather than have humanity continue to serve the market. We must simultaneously become more dynamic and more empathetic as a society.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rise of automation and artificial intelligence (AI), capital will continue to consolidate and leave people behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the United States, we want to believe that the market will resolve most situations. In this case, the market will not solve the problem - quite the opposite. The market is driven to reduce costs. It will look to find the the cheapest way to perform tasks… The market will continue to throw millions of people out of the labor force as automation and technology improve. In order for society to continue to function and thrive when tens of millions of Americans don’t have jobs, we will need to rethink the relationship between work and being able to pay for basic needs.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His solution is a form of universal basic income (UBI) of $1,000/mo for every American citizen from the age of 18 to death. One thousand dollars is somewhat of a magic number. It’s not enough to live off and serve as a job replacement, but it’s enough to serve as an income supplement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-of-the-war-on-normal-people&quot;&gt;Summary of The War on Normal People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yang’s thesis on the economy and the future is this: automation and AI is putting us through the “fourth industrial revolution.” This will cause millions of workers to be displaced, especially hitting rural communities the hardest. The solution is a universal basic income to help people through the transition, provide an influx of money into every community in the country, and give people a bigger safety net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His universal basic income proposal would cost ~$3 trillion per year, while the existing federal budget is ~$4 trillion. Before looking more into his proposals to fund it, here is his reasoning for why it’s needed in the first place. Note that there are far more data points in the book than presented here. I simply chose what I think to be most interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-one-whats-happening-to-jobs&quot;&gt;Part one: What’s happening to jobs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section, there are several chapters full of statistics to show how the current economy is not benefiting “normal people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;job-growth-has-been-on-the-decline&quot;&gt;Job growth has been on the decline&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, we can see historical data for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/PAYEMS#0&quot;&gt;total number of employed people over the past several decades&lt;/a&gt;. Although the number of employed people is clearly not decreasing, the &lt;em&gt;rate at which it’s growing&lt;/em&gt; is on the decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book, Yang shows job growth is on the decline, but he presents it grouped by ten-year-long increments. When I downloaded this data and looked into it further, I found this narrative of declining job growth to change based on where you start the groupings. With Yang’s choice, job growth appears to be on a sharp decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-jobs-added-to-economy.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-jobs-added-to-economy.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-jobs-added-to-economy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Job growth decline as portrayed in 'The War on Normal People'&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Job growth decline as portrayed in 'The War on Normal People'&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why not just present the annual growth rate in a line graph?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-job-growth-rate-chart.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-job-growth-rate-chart.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-job-growth-rate-chart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Annual U.S. job growth rate, U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Annual U.S. job growth rate, U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The periods of declining job growth align with economic recessions and, as Yang points out, each of these recessions have &lt;em&gt;“stripped out more jobs and taken longer to recover from than the last,”&lt;/em&gt;. This does appear to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yang warns there aren’t as many new jobs being created as there used to and eventually we’ll have a negative job growth rate. But the amount of new jobs being created is irrelevant without taking into consideration population. That’s why the unemployment rate exists, but &lt;strong&gt;the problem with the unemployment rate is it doesn’t take into account &lt;em&gt;“people who drop out of the workforce for any reason, including disability or simply giving up trying to find a job… It also doesn’t take into account people who are underemployed - that is, if a college graduate takes a job as a barista or other role that doesn’t require a degree.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is such a thing to help account for this called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/U6RATE&quot;&gt;“U-6” Unemployment rate&lt;/a&gt;, which does looks healthy and is currently at its lowest rate since we began tracking this metric (1994). However, we can also look at the arguably better &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/CIVPART&quot;&gt;civilian labor force participation rate&lt;/a&gt;, which is a percentage of the number of people in the labor force (people employed/looking for employment) compared to the total civilian population (over 16, non-military, not confined to an institution). Most notably, this includes people who have given up looking for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-labor-participation-rate.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-labor-participation-rate.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-labor-participation-rate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;U.S. labor force participation rate, U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/CIVPART&quot;&gt;U.S. labor force participation rate, U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current labor force participation rate is 62.6%, a rate which we haven’t seen since 2015, and since then the late 1970s. It’s down 7% since its all time high of around 67.3% in 2000. To put this into perspective, a 100 basis point decrease in the rate represents around 2.5M people leaving the labor force. So a 7% decrease represents 17.5M people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’m not sure what a healthy labor force participation rate is, I assume more people working who are of working age is better for the economy, but 63% is in line with other comparable countries &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SL.TLF.CACT.ZS&quot;&gt;according to The World Bank&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Country&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Labor force participation rate (2022)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;63%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;China&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;67%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Denmark&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;63%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;France&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Germany&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;62%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;India&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;49%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Japan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;62%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Netherlands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;66%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;South Korea&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;UK&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;62%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yang’s point is &lt;em&gt;“the numbers clearly show an economy that is having a harder time creating new jobs at previous levels.”&lt;/em&gt; While jobs are still growing, job &lt;em&gt;growth rate&lt;/em&gt; is on the decline and at a slower rate than the growth of the working age population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is this happening? Yang’s big hypothesis is that automation and AI are taking jobs from people and will continue to take them in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Companies can now prosper, grow, and mint record profits without hiring many people or increasing wages. Both job creation and wage growth have been weaker than the top-line economic growth would suggest since the 1970s.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest tech companies of today compared to the largest companies of the “last generation” have far less employees, but with a higher market cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Yang compared Apple to IBM as an example of this, I think a more revealing example of the direct effect technology has on jobs and company value is Blockbuster compared to Netflix. Blockbuster at its peak in 2004 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockbuster_LLC&quot;&gt;employed 84,300 people&lt;/a&gt; with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibtimes.com/sad-end-blockbuster-video-onetime-5-billion-company-being-liquidated-competition-1496962&quot;&gt;market cap of $8.1B&lt;/a&gt; after adjusting for inflation. Netflix, who killed Blockbuster through technological innovation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/587671/netflix-employees/&quot;&gt;employs just 12,800 people&lt;/a&gt; with a market cap of $186.9B - 85% less employees and a 2,207% higher market cap. &lt;strong&gt;Companies of today, with the advancements in technology, can create much more valuable companies with much fewer employees.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;who-is-normal-in-america&quot;&gt;Who is normal in America&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to derive our sense of the country by what we see around us, but the following statistics probably show an America very different from what you’re familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is normal according to the U.S. Census Bureau:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/data/tables/2021/demo/educational-attainment/cps-detailed-tables.html&quot;&gt;only 38% of Americans 25 years and older have a bachelor’s degree or more; 61% if Asian, 42% if white, 28% if black, and only 21% if Hispanic (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/data/tables/time-series/demo/income-poverty/cps-pinc/pinc-01.2021.html#list-tab-2012835591&quot;&gt;median personal income of Americans 25 years and older is $41.6k with nearly 70% making $65k or less (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/housing/hvs/data/histtabs.html&quot;&gt;66% of Americans own their own home as of 2023, down from the high of 69% in 2005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the median income &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt; for people 25 years or older over the last 24 years (1997 to 2021) was only 14.9% after &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usinflationcalculator.com/&quot;&gt;adjusting for inflation&lt;/a&gt;. The S&amp;amp;P 500, on the other hand, rose 190.9% over the same time period. This comparison isn’t made directly in &lt;em&gt;The War on Normal People,&lt;/em&gt; but mediocre job and wage growth over the past 20 years shows that a rising stock market doesn’t drive or align with wage growth. It is likely more correlated with unemployment rates, but is it also correlated with wealth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We tend to use the stock market’s performance as a shorthand indicator of national well-being. However, the &lt;strong&gt;median level of stock market investment is close to zero&lt;/strong&gt;. Only 52% of Americans own any stock through a stock mutual fund or a self-directed 401(k) or IRA, and the bottom 80% of Americans own only 8% of all stocks. […] This means that the average American benefits minimally from a rising stock market beyond the wealth effect, which is that the rich people around them spend more money and the economy is more buoyant.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/266807/percentage-americans-owns-stock.aspx&quot;&gt;American stock ownership was at 52% in 2016&lt;/a&gt;, it is now at 61%, which has been about the average level. But according to the Federal Reserve, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/research/how-many-americans-own-stock/&quot;&gt;bottom 90% of Americans by net worth do only own 11.1% of all stocks&lt;/a&gt;, which is a 37.9% decline since 1989. So an increasing stock market also adds only a little benefit to the wealth of most Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-we-do-for-a-living&quot;&gt;What we do for a living&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/emp/tables/emp-by-major-occupational-group.htm&quot;&gt;five largest occupational groups in the US&lt;/a&gt; (in 2016) are office and administrative support, sales and retail, food preparation and serving, transportation and material moving, and production. In total, 69 million Americans work in these groups, which is 47% of the total American workforce. Yang claims each of these groups is at risk of being severely affected by automation and AI. As of 2021, production is no longer a top five occupation, and it has been replaced with management occupations. For the sake of covering the book, I’m going to ignore this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”Although the seriousness of [automation] has not reached the mainstream yet, […] many Americans are in danger of losing their job right now due to automation. Not in 10 or 15 years. Right now.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a table of the number of employees in these occupational groups from 2016 and 2021 compared to the total workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Occupational group&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Total number of employees (2016)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Total number of employees (2021)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Change&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;All occupations&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140.4M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;158.1M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Office &amp;amp; admin. support&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;22.0M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19.6M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-11%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sales &amp;amp; retail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.5M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.7M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-1%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food prep. &amp;amp; serving&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13.0M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.8M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Transportation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.7M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13.3M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;37%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Production&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.1M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.8M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-3%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, only one group did not decline in job count since 2016: transportation increased 37%. It’s difficult to say the decline in office and admin jobs was due mainly to automation without significant research. Transportation jobs jumped, but the decline of jobs in transportation is not expected until full autonomous trucks are ready for the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it is interesting that four out of the top five occupations are declining, however total jobs are increasing and the occupations that are growing appear at first glance to have a higher median wage. Although this is good overall, this could be bad for the folks who are losing these jobs and don’t have the qualifications to enter the growing, and higher paying occupations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Transportation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all these occupational groups, Yang’s largest concern are truck drivers. At least in 2014, driving trucks is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/money/2015/02/05/382664837/map-the-most-common-job-in-every-state&quot;&gt;most common job in 29 states&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trucking.org/economics-and-industry-data&quot;&gt;3.54 million truck drivers nationwide (2022)&lt;/a&gt;. They are mostly high school graduate men with an average age of 49.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are huge financial incentives for transportation companies to adopt autonomous transportation vehicles. Not only are the 3.5 million truck drivers at risk of losing their jobs, but also the businesses along these routes to serve the drivers when they need to eat, drink, rest, sleep etc. Yang claims there are “as many as 7.2 million workers [who] serve the needs of divers at truck stops, diners, motels and other businesses,” but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.route-fifty.com/infrastructure/2015/05/driverless-trucks-small-town-economic-impact/113101/&quot;&gt;his source for this figure&lt;/a&gt; didn’t specify this number and the American Trucking Associations put the figure at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trucking.org/economics-and-industry-data&quot;&gt;4.35 million&lt;/a&gt;, however it’s not clear if this figure also represents workers outside of the trucking industry who serve truckers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, as of 2021 and compared to 2016 and back to 2000, jobs in the transportation sector have greatly increased. However, autonomous trucks have yet to really hit the market so the impact of automation on this and related industries are yet to be seen and Yang can’t say &lt;em&gt;“I told you so”&lt;/em&gt; just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Production&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/MANEMP&quot;&gt;More than 5 million manufacturing workers lost their jobs after the year 2000&lt;/a&gt;, due to a combination of trade (outsourcing) and automation. Although there is debate as to which is the major cause, Yang cites a Ball State University study that attributes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/dec677c0-b7e6-11e6-ba85-95d1533d9a62&quot;&gt;85% of these job losses to technological change and automation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-manufacturing-jobs.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-manufacturing-jobs.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people-manufacturing-jobs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;All Employees, Manufacturing, U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/MANEMP&quot;&gt;All Employees, Manufacturing, U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2013 survey of these displaced manufacturing workers found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geartechnology.com/issues/0813x/displaced_manufacturing_workers.pdf&quot;&gt;41% were still unemployed by January 2012&lt;/a&gt; or dropped out of the labor market within three years of losing their job. Of the 59% who found re-employment, 69% found employment in different fields. The manufacturing jobs that still exist are requiring more technical expertise and advanced education. Since 2000, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2017/01/america-is-still-making-things/512282/#:~:text=Manufacturing%2C%20like%20most%20other%20industries,as%20it%20did%20in%201960.&quot;&gt;manufacturing jobs for people with less than a high-school education fell 44% and jobs requiring a graduate degree grew by 32%&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the 41% of displaced manufacturing workers become destitute and apply for disability to survive. From 2000 to 2011, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/statcomps/di_asr/2019/sect01a.pdf&quot;&gt;the number of workers on disability rose by 3.5 million&lt;/a&gt;. Yang states this was mostly in manufacturing-heavy states like Ohio, Michigan and Pennsylvania, but he didn’t provide a specific source other than Michigan. About &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crainsdetroit.com/article/20150726/NEWS/307269975/disability-rolls-surge-in-state&quot;&gt;half of the 310,000 residents who left the workforce in Michigan between 2003 and 2013 went on disability&lt;/a&gt;. One in 12 adults aged 18-64 in Michigan receive disability and it’s the state with the 7th largest population receiving disability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of 2023, manufacturing jobs have not recovered to the levels seen in 2,000. The above data shows that it’s difficult for these people to find new work; however, and it bears repeating, the total number of employed people is still growing. The situation these folks find themselves is unfortunate, but whether this is a piece of a bigger crisis to come is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About White Collar Jobs and AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation is not limited to replacing just blue-collar jobs with routine functions, but also white collar jobs including doctors, lawyers, accountants, wealth advisors, traders, psychologists, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Super-intelligent computers (and AI), are entering the market, which can synthesize complex data sets, perform tasks, and make decisions as good as or better than humans, leading to a dramatic change in the way companies operate and employ people. As time goes on, “employing lots of people will mean that you’re behind the times.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Federal Reserve categorizes 44% of total jobs as routine, which are in danger of automation and AI to replace workers. As this occurs, workers will only be left with either low-end service jobs or high-end cognitive jobs with middle-skill jobs disappearing. The Fed is calling this “job polarization” and will lead to increasing income inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Humanity and Work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s worth considering whether humans are not actually best suited for many forms of work. Consider also the reverse: Are most forms of work ideal for humans? That is, if we’re not good for work, is work good for us?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between humanity and work reveals a negative correlation between the most human roles and their monetary compensation. While roles such as parent, artist, or teacher often have high social impact, they typically receive low or no pay. Conversely, lucrative jobs like corporate lawyers or financiers require a higher degree of efficiency and detachment from human qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-two-whats-happening-to-us&quot;&gt;Part two: What’s happening to us&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part two, Yang makes several points about how the quality of life for normal Americans is breaking down in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;life-in-the-bubble&quot;&gt;Life in the bubble&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our smartest college graduates are being absorbed by the financial services and technology industries out of Manhattan and Silicon Valley. Why? They want to succeed and success is heavily defined by market success. And failure to succeed brings catastrophic economic and social consequences. So college isn’t a time for intellectual exploration, it’s a mass sift that determines one’s future prospects and lot in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the bubble, many of us came up through the meritocracy and we’ve internalized its lessons. The underlying logic of the meritocratic system is this: if you’re successful, it’s because you’re smart and hardworking, and thus virtuous. If you’re poor or unsuccessful, it’s because you’re lazy and/or stupid and of subpar character. The people at the top belong there and the people at the bottom only have themselves to blame.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But success in entering these industries isn’t actually as meritocratic as the ones in the bubble like to admit. It’s more so based on one’s family background, the community in which one lives, and one’s ability to score high on tests. Therefore if success and a life worth living is defined by market success, then human worth is defined by test scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The logic of the marketplace is seductive to all of us. It gives everything a tinge of justice. It makes the suffering of the marginalized more palatable, in that there’s a sense that they deserve it. Perhaps the most remarkable thing is that they often agree - they think they deserve it, too.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mindsets-of-scarcity-and-abundance&quot;&gt;Mindsets of Scarcity and Abundance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a mindset of scarcity. The average American lives paycheck to paycheck with a variable work schedule. This means they spend a lot of bandwidth stressing about uncertainties - enough hours to work, enough money to pay bills, what days they have off to set appointments, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A culture of scarcity is a culture of negativity. People think about what can go wrong. They attacked each other. Tribalism and divisiveness go way up. Reason starts to lose ground. Decision-making gets systematically worse. Acts of sustained optimism - getting married, starting a business, moving for a new job - all go down. If this seems familiar, this is exactly what we’re seeing by the numbers here in America. We are quickly transforming from the land of plenty to the land of “you get yours, I’ll get mine.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;geography-is-destiny&quot;&gt;Geography is Destiny&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the available good jobs and opportunity start decreasing in a city or town, the first people to leave are the most educated who have the best opportunities elsewhere. So they move out, and the average education level of that city starts to decrease as well. This is why America’s most educated people congregate in CA (Silicon Valley) and NY (Manhattan) and smaller cities tend not to prosper at the same rate. Although remote work is starting to change this, it is yet to be determined if this is a long term trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last 15 years, the majority of cities in America have seen more business close than open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A series of studies by the economists Raj Chetty and Nathaniel Hendren showed how important where you grow up is to your future prospects… If a child from a low-mobility area moved to a better-performing area, each year produced positive effects on his or her future earnings. They were also more likely to attend college, less likely to become single parents, and more likely to earn more with each year spent in the better environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;men-women-and-children&quot;&gt;Men, Women, and Children&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A Pew research study showed that many men are foregoing or delaying marriage because they do not feel financially secure. The same study said that, for women, having a steady job was the single biggest factor they were looking for in a spouse. Getting married is an act of optimism, stability, and prosperity. It can also be expensive. If you don’t have a stable job all of the above becomes more difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across all education attainment levels, marriage rates are declining, but are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2017/09/14/as-u-s-marriage-rate-hovers-at-50-education-gap-in-marital-status-widens/&quot;&gt;declining much more sharply in the lowest levels of education attinment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of babies born to unmarried women is 40%, up from 30% in the early 1990’s, and up from 15% in the late 1970’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“At a time when raising and educating children and forming our human capital is of the utmost importance, we’re heading in the other direction.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-permanent-shadow-class-what-displacement-looks-like&quot;&gt;The Permanent Shadow Class: What Displacement Looks Like&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an absurd amount of Americans on and applying for disability benefits every year. In 2014, nearly 2.5m Americans applied for disability and 9m working-age Americans are currently receiving disability benefits. It has become not only a bloated bureaucratic government program, but also a big private industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After someone receives disability benefits, only 1% ever return to the workforce despite the average monthly benefit amount being only &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ssa.gov/disabilityfacts/facts.html&quot;&gt;$1,234/mo as of 2019&lt;/a&gt;. This is barely enough to keep someone above the poverty line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The fact that a program designed for a relatively small number of Americans has now become such a major lifeline for people and communities is part of the Great Displacement. […] After one gets on disability, one enters a permanent shadow class of beneficiaries. Even if you start feeling better, you’re not going to risk a lifetime of benefits for a tenuous job that could disappear at any moment. And it’s likely easier to think of yourself as genuinely disabled than as someone cheating society for a monthly draw.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Disability illustrates the challenges of mandating the government to administer such a large-scale program. It’s essentially the worst of all worlds, as the truly disabled and needy may find themselves shut out by red tape, while the process rewards those who lawyer up and the lawyers themselves. It sends a pervasive message of “game the system and get money” and “think of yourself as incompetent and incapable of work.” It’s subject to fraud. And once you’re on, you never leave.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-shape-were-in--disintegration&quot;&gt;The Shape We’re In / Disintegration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These worrying trends show Americans are not in great shape right now and will make transitioning to a new economy much more difficult:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are getting older&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we don’t have adequate savings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are financially insecure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we use a lot of drugs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are not starting new businesses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we’re depressed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we owe a lot of money, public and private&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our education system underperforms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our economy is consolidating around a few mega-powerful firms in our most important industries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our media is fragmented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our social capital is lower&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we don’t trust institutions anymore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Among the things being questioned is our capitalist system. Among young people, polls show a very high degree of sympathy for other types of economies, in part because they’ve witnessed capitalism’s failures and excesses these past years.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…capitalism, with the assistance of technology, is about to turn on normal people. Capital and efficiency will prefer robots, software, AI, and machines to people more and more. [Capitalism and technology] started saying things like, “Ah, let’s automate everything” and “if the market doesn’t like it, get rid of it,” which made reasonable people increasingly nervous.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If capitalism in America continues as it is with the rise of AI and automation, there will be an even more staggering increase in income inequality. Society will be dramatically bifurcated between the rich (educated) and poor (uneducated), desperation and destabilization will rise, and could spur a revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If there is a revolution, it is likely to be born of race and identity with automation-driven economics as the underlying force. A highly disproportionate number of people at the top will be educated whites, Jews, and Asians… African Americans and Latinos will almost certainly make up a disproportionate number of the less privileged in the wake of automation, as they currently enjoy lower levels of wealth and education. Racial inequality will become all the more jarring as the new majority remains on the outside. […] Less privileged whites may be more likely to blame people of color, immigrants, or shifting cultural norms for their diminishing stature and shattered communities than they will automation and the capitalist system. Culture wars will be the proxy wars for the economic backdrop.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-three-solutions-and-human-capitalism&quot;&gt;Part Three: Solutions and Human Capitalism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-freedom-dividend&quot;&gt;The Freedom Dividend&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core solution Yang advocates for is a universal basic income - a monthly check of $1,000 to each U.S. citizen above the age of 18 regardless of the city they live in, the number of dependents they have, work status, or the amount of income they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The first major change would be to implement a universal basic income (UBI), which I would call the ‘Freedom Dividend.’ The United States should provide an annual income of $12,000 for each American aged 18 [and above], with the amount indexed to increase with inflation. It would require a constitutional super majority to modify or amend. The Freedom Dividend would replace the vast majority of existing welfare programs. This plan was proposed by Andy Stern, the former head of the largest labor union in the country, in his book &lt;em&gt;Raising the Floor&lt;/em&gt;. The poverty line is currently $11,770. We would essentially be bringing all Americans to the poverty line and alleviate gross poverty.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main critiques of UBI that make people quickly dismiss even considering it. These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$1,000/mo is only enough money to scrape by&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will cost too much to implement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will cause runaway inflation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first let’s talk about why UBI is worth considering before addressing these critiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;benefits-of-ubi&quot;&gt;Benefits of UBI&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to traditional welfare programs, a UBI with no strings attached removes the disincentive for people to work as wages earned from working will stack on top of UBI. And in contrast to increasing minimum wages, it will give people more flexibility with the work they choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would be a massive stimulus to lower-cost areas of living as the spending power of residents dramatically increases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would make losing a job less stressful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would empower workers with the ability to leave exploitative employers and find better work environments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would allow people to work jobs they enjoy even if the pay is less than they could earn in a job they dislike.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would help people avoid making terrible decisions based on financial scarcity and month-to-month needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would increase rates of entrepreneurship by reducing the risk of starting a business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would enable people to more effectively transition from shrinking industries and environments to new ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would reduce stress, improve health, decrease crime, and strengthen relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would support parents and caretakers for the work that they do, particularly mothers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would give all citizens an honest stake in society and a sense of the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would stimulate and maintain the consumer economy through the automation wave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would maintain order and preserve our way of life through the greatest economic and social transition in history.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would make our society more equitable, fair, and just.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;cost&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give $1,000/mo to all citizens above the age of 18 would cost somewhere around $1.3 trillion per year. So how could the US government pay for it? The two biggest sources of potential are folding existing welfare programs and implementing a new value added tax (VAT). A VAT is a tax on consumption, levied on non-essential goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All developed countries have a VAT except for the US. And in Europe, the average VAT is 20%. A VAT’s efficacy has been solidly established. Obviously, implementing a VAT on non-essential goods would increase the cost of those goods; however, essential goods for people’s basic needs shouldn’t be affected. This means people with a low income who spend the majority of their income on essential goods will be affected the least from a VAT and will benefit the most from UBI. At a 20% VAT, one spending less than $60,000 per year on non-essential goods will come out on top with a UBI + VAT policy (20% of $60k = $12k). Therefore, only high income earners (and spenders) will pay more in tax after their UBI is accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, not every category of good would have a 20% VAT. Depending on the type of good, a different percentage of a VAT could be applied. For example, clothing could have a 10% VAT while new cars could have a 25% VAT and et cetera. These percentages could be tweaked to again affect low income earners and spenders less so than high income earners and spenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“UBI… is not shaming - everyone participates. It does not try to control the economy from the top - people can spend their money on what they want and therefore steer the economy as it has always been best steered, by the consumer. It could free up the job market in ways that are hard to appreciate… I am entranced by UBI, not just as a needed fix but as an institute that unleashes people’s potential… I find myself convinced that UBI is natural, and would lead to a more productive and happier world - and it would allow us to fully harness people’s creativity and the technology they create.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Richard Garfield, creator of Magic: The Gathering&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike America’s current welfare program, a UBI shouldn’t increase the size of the government or create a new bureaucracy. There would be no qualifying criteria or capacity limits and therefore no need for the thousands of government employees that are needed to administer today’s welfare benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[UBI is] less an expenditure and more a transfer to citizens so they can use it to improve their lives, pay each other, patron the local businesses, and support the consumer economy. Instead of hiring a new army of government employees, every dollar will be put into the hands of an American citizen and then largely spent within the American economy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some critics of UBI might say that if we give people cash instead of vouchers (like food stamps), people will just spend it on drugs, alcohol, or gamble it away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The idea that poor people will be irresponsible with their money and squander it seems to be a product of deep-seated biases rather than emblematic of the truth. There’s a tendency for rich people to dismiss poor people as weak-willed children with no cost discipline. The evidence runs in the other direction. As the Dutch philosopher Rutger Bregman and others put it, “Poverty is not a lack of character. It’s a lack of cash.”
“Scarcity research indicates that the best way to improve decision making is to free up people’s bandwidth. People won’t ever make perfect choices. But knowing that their basic needs are accounted for will lead to better choices for millions of people each day.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to a job guarantee policy, which would be very difficult to organize and create a huge bureaucracy, a UBI would more naturally create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Many people have some artistic passion that they would pursue if they didn’t need to worry about feeding themselves next month. A UBI would be perhaps the greatest catalyst to human creativity we have ever seen. Perhaps most crucially, endless new businesses would form. This would play out over and over again throughout the economy, resulting in millions of new jobs - 4.7 million according to the Roosevelt Institute’s analysis. A UBI would address a significant proportion of the lack of work through increased humanity, caring, creativity, and enterprise.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;human-capitalism&quot;&gt;Human Capitalism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the goal of our country? Of our government? Well, outside of wartime, the answer seems absent other than increasing GDP every year and keeping inflation and unemployment in control - all economy focused. But should it not be to ever improve the lives of all its citizens?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part one of the book, it’s clear improving the well-being of citizens is not the goal. If it is, then we’re doing the exact opposite. Instead of improving the economy above all else, Yang proposes what he calls “Human Capitalism,” which is geared toward maximizing human well-being and fulfillment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Human Capitalism would have a few core tenets: (1.) Humanity is more important than money. (2.) The unit of an economy is each person, each dollar. (3.) Markets exist to serve our common goals and values.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Our economic system must shift to focus on bettering the lot of the average person. Capitalism has to be made to serve human ends and goals, rather than have our humanity subverted to serve the marketplace. We shape the system. We own it, not the other way around.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do we measure a country’s current state and progress of improving the well-being and fulfillment of its citizens? Here are some ideas Yang proposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;median income and standard of living&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;levels of engagement with work and labor participation rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;health-adjusted life expectancy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;childhood success rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infant mortality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;surveys of national well-being&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;average physical fitness and mental health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quality of infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proportion of elderly in quality care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;human capital development and access to education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marriage rates and success&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;deaths of despair/despair index/substance abuse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;national optimism/mindset of abundance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;community integrity and social capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;environmental quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reacclimation of incarcerated individuals and rates of criminality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Human Capitalism will reshape the way we measure value and progress, and help us redefine why we do what we do.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Yang&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yang continues this section of the book on requirements for human capitalism to take effect in our government with ideas and suggestions for new policies to help the US get closer. Ideas range from congressional salary changes, work restrictions after terms are over, anti-corruption/anti-lobbying, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Yang has various ideas to improve the health care system because how it’s setup currently doesn’t provide the best incentives for either businesses, care providers, or the people receiving care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to improving the lives of people at the individual level, Yang focuses heavily on education, suggesting improvements in both quality and access. As shown in part one, a person’s education level is one of the biggest leading indicators of one’s earning potential and quality of life. Yang dissects many of the issues with the current education system in the US and provides ideas and suggestions on how to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve reduced a great length of the end of the book into the previous three paragraphs. While each chapter I’ve found very interesting, I think the core ideas of UBI and human-centered capitalism to be the most important in his book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I love most about Yang’s “The War on Normal People” is its theory on how a country ought to be, what it should strive for, and how its progress toward that goal ought to be measured. I recommend this book for people interested in data-driven political theory and political ideas outside contemporary thought.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Andrew Yang was a U.S. presidential candidate in the 2020 election who caught the attention of myself and millions of others through his unique approach to identifying and solving many of America’s problems.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/andrew-yang-war-on-normal-people.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Became Vegan</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vegan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Became Vegan" /><published>2023-01-14T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-14T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vegan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vegan">&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost three years since I stopped eating or buying anything made from animals because I became convinced it’s unethical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t a conclusion I reached on a whim. It took many years for my mind to change. Most people think being vegan is a diet, but I learned veganism is really a philosophy. This is my first time writing about it, so for now I only want to cover the definition of veganism and why I find its core argument so convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-veganism&quot;&gt;What is veganism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s true that someone who doesn’t eat or drink anything made wholly or partly from animals is vegan, it doesn’t capture the complete picture of veganism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a definition for veganism I’ve slightly modified from The Vegan Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Veganism is a philosophy and way of living which seeks to avoid the exploitation and use of animals-as far as is possible and practicable-for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; purpose, including food, clothing, furniture, entertainment, makeup, personal products, and any other items that use materials or ingredients derived from animals.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophical part of veganism is really about ethics. Like humans, non-human animals are conscious and sentient beings. They have individual personalities, desires, experience pleasures, and feel pain. &lt;strong&gt;Despite being a different species from humans, their preferences for seeking pleasures and avoiding pain should be respected and protected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Veganism is about taking the most basic and fundamental natural right that we believe all humans have, the right to life, and extending it to animals.&lt;/strong&gt; We shouldn’t treat sentient beings like objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most people think being vegan is a more ethical choice than not, but also that it’s not &lt;em&gt;unethical&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be vegan. The difference is veganism says &lt;em&gt;it is&lt;/em&gt; unethical to not be vegan. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;core-argument-for-veganism&quot;&gt;Core argument for veganism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animals suffer in the production of animal products, and since we have access to sufficient alternatives that don’t require the use of animals to be made, that means products made from animals are unnecessary and the animal suffering is unnecessary. It is unethical to cause unnecessary suffering, therefore it is unethical to consume, purchase, or create products made from animals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to believe it’s &lt;em&gt;not unethical&lt;/em&gt; to take and use the bodies of animals for food and other materials, then we must have a truly legitimate &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; for them that is &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt; to be satisfied in any other &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most obvious &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; of animal products would be for food. We need to eat to survive, right? And generally, meat, eggs, milk, etc. contains the important nutrients we need to survive. &lt;strong&gt;However, because it’s &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; to get these nutrients from a plant-based diet, then we don’t need animal products to survive. Yes, we need food to survive, but that food doesn’t need to come from animals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it was not possible to eat a plant-based diet and live a healthy life (or in other words that didn’t cause illness or premature death), then eating food made from animals would be necessary, and the suffering animals would go through to produce that food would generally not be unethical to inflict. However, there already has been more than sufficient research done to show that people can not only survive on a plant-based diet, but is often correlated with reduced risk of cancer and longer life spans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But is it &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; to switch to a healthy plant-based diet? Well, I admit it’s not easy and there are some costs.&lt;/strong&gt; You will have to learn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what you need to eat to be healthy on a plant-based diet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to shop at grocery stores and read ingredients labels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what and how to order at restaurants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to deal with social events that revolve around food&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people think it would be too difficult for them to switch to a vegan diet, but after a few months most of these become non issues. The only thing I still find somewhat of a challenge after being vegan for nearly three years is the social aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However, none of these obstacles make switching to a vegan diet impractical enough for us to say we have a legitamte need for animal products. The far majority of people living in first world countries have access to modern grocery stores that have everything one would need to eat a healthy plant-based diet. This means it’s both possible and practical to not consume animal products. Therefore the production of animal products is unecessary and animal suffering is unecessary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality is however, that most people just don’t care about the well-being of animals. Most people love the way they taste more than they think their life is worth.&lt;/strong&gt; So how did I start caring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-changed-my-mind&quot;&gt;What changed my mind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started in 2007 when I attended a bullfight in Spain and it was the first time I can remember giving serious thought to the well-being of animals. Just imagine being the bull for a minute in this scenario…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/vegan-bull-crowd.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-crowd.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-crowd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The beginning of a bullfight in Spain&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The beginning of a bullfight in Spain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re forced into a stadium and paraded around to entertain the spectators. Then you start getting stabbed with spears repeatedly. With each piercing comes tremendous pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/vegan-bull-stab.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-stab.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-stab.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The bull is repeatedly stabbed by spears with red, decorative hilts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The bull is repeatedly stabbed by spears with red, decorative hilts&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several spears are sticking out of your body, you lose the strength to run. It’s at this moment a sword is thrust into your neck and you’re killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/vegan-bull-death.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-death.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/vegan-bull-death.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Once the bull is too weak to offer the matador a challenge, a final, fatal blow is delivered&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Once the bull is too weak to offer the matador a challenge, a final, fatal blow is delivered&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As I was watching this bull writhe in pain, I was struck emotionally. What was the point? For our entertainment? Because it’s culture? It was barbaric.&lt;/strong&gt; It was this experience, and many others throughout the years (from books, movies and TV, YouTube videos, conversations), that sparked an uneasiness inside me about our relationship with animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But it was in 2020, when I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/C1vW9iSpLLk&quot;&gt;Alex O’Connor’s video “The Meat Eater’s Case for Veganism”&lt;/a&gt; that flipped me from being somewhat interested in the ethics of how we treat animals to all of a sudden trying to find the best arguments against veganism to refute Alex’s points. I didn’t find any then and I have yet to find any now. I knew at that moment I had to become vegan, because I was convinced it was immoral to eat animals and I had no excuse not be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C1vW9iSpLLk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-you-should-care&quot;&gt;Why you should care&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the other side of your carnitas bowl is a sentient being who was enslaved, abused, and ultimately had their life taken away from them without their consent. They didn’t want to die, and there is no way to kill someone humanely who doesn’t want to die.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you eat animals, you owe it to your conscience, your desire to be a good person, to fully understand how your meat is made and what these sentient beings go through before arriving on your dinner plate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/vegan-inside-animal-farms.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.dominionmovement.com/watch&quot;&gt;What the lives of animals are like in a factory farm, where 99% of American meat comes from.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most people would say veganism is extreme. But I think believing it’s not immoral for us to enslave, abuse, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://animalclock.org/&quot;&gt;kill billions of animals per year&lt;/a&gt; is the extreme position, and to abstain from that to be the sane position.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is how humans are: We question all our beliefs, except for the ones that we really believe in, and those we never think to question.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Orson Scott Card, Speaker for the Dead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;counter-arguments&quot;&gt;Counter arguments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is just my introduction to the vegan argument, I didn’t want to go deeper than I already have. However, it can’t be ignored that there are plenty of good and interesting counterpoints to the argument that we have a moral obligation to be vegan, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“It’s a personal choice what we eat.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Animals are inferior and don’t have the same moral worth as humans so killing them for food is not immoral.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We’ve been eating animals for thousands of years. It’s the natural food chain.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“It’s not immoral if they’re killed humanely, which is more painless than how they would probably be killed in nature.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We’re biologically made to eat meat and we need meat in a balanced diet to live a healthy life.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to address some of these and others in upcoming writings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">It’s been almost three years since I stopped eating or buying anything made from animals because I became convinced it’s unethical.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/vegan.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/vegan.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Supported 62% growth in MRR as Head of Marketing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/revealbot-growth-case-study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supported 62% growth in MRR as Head of Marketing" /><published>2022-04-29T19:37:27-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T19:37:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/revealbot-growth-case-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/revealbot-growth-case-study">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revealbot is a Facebook ad automation tool and therefore relies on Facebook’s ad platform and API to be a functioning company. At the time I joined, Facebook was getting increasingly strict on ad quality and the types of products being advertised. If advertisers were violating these policies, their ad accounts would be banned. And if those advertisers were running ads through a Facebook Partner’s tool, like Revealbot, Facebook would hold the Partner responsible for allowing these low quality advertisers access to Facebook’s ad network. If a Partner received too many violations, Facebook would ban the Partner from their Partner program and from accessing their API. It would be the end for Revealbot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid catastrophe, Revealbot enacted strict quality controls for their customers. If a customer had too many unapproved ads or was linked to ad accounts that were already banned, Revealbot had no choice but to cancel their subscriptions and remove them from the platform. This caused a material decline in growth and MRR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My main objective as the sole marketer of Revealbot was to reposition Revealbot as a tool for well established ecommerce stores and generate revenue through various marketing initiatives.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When Revealbot first launched on Product Hunt, it generated quite a bit of media buzz and was picked up by a few influencers in the Facebook ad marketing and affiliate world.&lt;/strong&gt; Not only did this spur initial revenue growth, but it also resulted in the acquisition of a significant amount of backlinks to the revealbot.com domain. When I discovered this in my SEO audit, &lt;strong&gt;I knew SEO and content marketing would be a significant growth channel.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I covered most of it in its own &lt;a href=&quot;/revealbot-seo-case-study&quot;&gt;SEO case study&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;here’s just a summary of what I did for our SEO and content program:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;an SEO audit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;how we updated existing pages and blog posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;building a Facebook ad cost tool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;short form content in the form of “Revealbot Answers”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the most important content projects we launched to generate signups was competitor pages.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;competitor-pages&quot;&gt;Competitor pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitor pages are one the lowest hanging fruit SEO/content strategies that so many brands are missing out on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the last things buyers do before they make a purchase, after they’ve identified their problem and the type of solution they want, is they look up competing products and services to make sure they’re buying the right one for them. Making competitor pages serves content for these exact search queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of content is a definitive example of bottom of the funnel (BOFU) content. By its nature, it won’t generate a large amount of traffic, but the traffic it does generate is much more likely to sign up for a trial because they are in the buying phase of the buyer’s journey. That’s why this content is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At Revealbot, we built six competitor pages plus a competitor “homepage” where we compare Revealbot to all our competitors and link to each separate competitor page.&lt;/strong&gt; Here’s what they looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-madgicx-alternative.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-madgicx-alternative.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-madgicx-alternative.png&quot; alt=&quot;ONE: Madgicx competitor page. TWO: AdEspresso competitor page. THREE: Competitor 'homepage.'&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-adespresso-alternative.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-adespresso-alternative.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-adespresso-alternative.png&quot; alt=&quot;ONE: Madgicx competitor page. TWO: AdEspresso competitor page. THREE: Competitor 'homepage.'&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-alternative.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-alternative.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-alternative.png&quot; alt=&quot;ONE: Madgicx competitor page. TWO: AdEspresso competitor page. THREE: Competitor 'homepage.'&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;ONE: Madgicx competitor page. TWO: AdEspresso competitor page. THREE: Competitor 'homepage.'&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll see they target keywords such as &lt;strong&gt;[competitor] alternative&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Revealbot vs [competitor]&lt;/strong&gt;, while our competitor homepages targets keywords like &lt;strong&gt;revealbot alternative&lt;/strong&gt;. All our competitor pages use the same layout, but each one is customized to highlight the benefits and features that make Revealbot stand out from the competitor and of course data in the feature comparison tables. You’ll also notice that we don’t just trash talk our competitors. We give the user a fair review of the competitor and the use case that makes the most sense to choose the competitor over us. This builds trust in the eyes of our customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each competitor page is SEO optimized. On their own, they won’t generate a lot of backlinks so it’s important to give them a lot of internal links. The easiest way we did this was by linking them in the footer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other than our homepage and core platform pages, these competitor pages quickly became our highest customer generating pages.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;website-redesign&quot;&gt;Website redesign&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To take advantage of all the traffic the SEO optimizations and new content produced, and to better reposition Revealbot as a tool for well established ecommerce brands, we needed to redesign the website.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a before and after of the old homepage and the new one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-homepage-old.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-homepage-old.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-homepage-old.png&quot; alt=&quot;LEFT: Old homepage. RIGHT: New homepage.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-homepage-new.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-homepage-new.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-homepage-new.png&quot; alt=&quot;LEFT: Old homepage. RIGHT: New homepage.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;LEFT: Old homepage. RIGHT: New homepage.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the new design, you’ll immediately notice the improvement in the hero section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more clear, and value-driven headline and subheadline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opt-in box directly on page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another stand out difference is the new design has much more content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is Revealbot for? (agencies, ecommerce brands, apps)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more testimonials and logos from well established brands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;three new solution sections and pages for the main functions of the product (automating, launching, and analyzing ads)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;highlighting out support team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, as mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/revealbot-seo-case-study&quot;&gt;SEO case study&lt;/a&gt;, we SEO optimized all our solution and feature pages and with the improved design, we were able to convert that additional traffic into signups and revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The highest lead generating pages for the main website and their primary keyword were:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook ad platform page (facebook ad automation)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google ad platform page (google ad automation)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snapchat ad platform page (snapchat ad automation)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook ad automated rules sub feature page (facebook automated rules)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook ad split test and bulk creation sub feature page (facebook bulk creation)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blog needed a redesign, too, to improve the overall reading experience and better convert traffic into signups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The most important changes to improving the conversion rate of blog posts were to add several call-to-actions in every post. Because Revealbot offered a self serve, 14-day free trial, we used that as the offer versus a traditional content or newsletter offer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with one of our developers to create several call-to-action snippets that I could paste directly into the post content wherever I thought it made sense. We made several versions so that the call-to-action could speak to a benefit that is relevant to the topic of the current post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example call-to-action with the ad automation benefit on an article about the Facebook conversion API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-blog-cta.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-blog-cta.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-blog-cta.png&quot; alt=&quot;One example of our Revealbot blog CTAs&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One example of our Revealbot blog CTAs&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;google-ads&quot;&gt;Google Ads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While page redesigns and SEO optimizations were in progress, I decided to relaunch Google Ads. &lt;strong&gt;Before I joined Revealbot, the company had a freelancer set up our Google Ads campaigns, but we turned it all off due to poor performance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it had been over a year since we ran any paid Google ads, I decided to turn back on their campaigns to create a baseline. However, the cost per conversion (trial start) was $300 and so we had to pause everything in less than two weeks due to bad performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-google-ads-old.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-google-ads-old.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-google-ads-old.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Ad campaign performance from previous freelancer&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Google Ad campaign performance from previous freelancer&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The whole account needed a complete overhaul. So after new keyword research, new ad copy, and initial testing, I was able to achieve a cost per trial start of $115, a 62% reduction from the initial $300 CPA.&lt;/strong&gt; And this campaign was for non-brand targeting the US, UK, and AUS. This was more than an acceptable CPA, which allowed us to keep these campaigns running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-google-ads-new.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-google-ads-new.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-google-ads-new.png&quot; alt=&quot;Performance of new and improved Google Ad campaign&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Performance of new and improved Google Ad campaign&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How were we able to achieve this? The improved performance can be attributed to the improved homepage design, ad copy, and keyword optimization, as the homepage was the destination URL from both the initial campaign to the new one was the same.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the approach we took with our ad copy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-google-ads-winners.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-google-ads-winners.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-google-ads-winners.png&quot; alt=&quot;Best performing ads in the new and improved Google Ad campaign&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Best performing ads in the new and improved Google Ad campaign&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary headline, or the first part of the headline, was either benefit or feature focused. Since we were targeting keywords around the topic of “facebook ads automation,” the features and benefits we highlighted were relevant to the topic. So the main headline was either about automating Facebook ads or about what automation can help you achieve - spending less time in ads manager, scaling efficiently, saving money, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secondary headline was either highlighting our offer was risk free by using “Try Revealbot 14 Days Free” or we used it for an additional feature highlight. Surprisingly, our best performing ad used neither and was simply “by Revealbot.” These types of surprises are why I still test things even if I have low confidence in their success. We can’t predict the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video-course&quot;&gt;Video course&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting free trials is one thing, getting them to convert to paying customers is another. &lt;strong&gt;The biggest challenge Revealbot had with its user onboarding flow was its time to value. The product is incredibly flexible, but this brought with it a steep learning curve users needed to overcome to start getting value from the product.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the product team worked on improving the onboarding flow, &lt;strong&gt;I created a video course with 17 videos to walk people through the tool, how to use it, and show some examples of the most popular automations.&lt;/strong&gt; We put the videos up on YouTube and created a spot on our website for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-video-course-webpage.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-video-course-webpage.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-video-course-webpage.png&quot; alt=&quot;The home of Revealbot's video course webpage&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The home of Revealbot's video course webpage&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created a main page for the course and individual pages for each video, complete with transcripts, links to relevant blog articles, and links to relevant help articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-video-course-individual.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-video-course-individual.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-video-course-individual.png&quot; alt=&quot;Each video lesson has its own page with the transcript and helpful resources&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Each video lesson has its own page with the transcript and helpful resources&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video course is very frequently mentioned in feedback from new customers as a resource that helped them get set up on Revealbot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying true to the “move fast” and “done is better than perfect” work culture at startups, this video course was filmed in my apartment with my iPhone.&lt;/strong&gt; You can watch one of the videos here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-video-course-thumbnail.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-video-course-thumbnail.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-video-course-thumbnail.png&quot; alt=&quot;Watch one of the videos&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sC4BOoGxGBk&quot;&gt;Watch one of the videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Despite removing customers (and revenue) due to increasingly strict Facebook Partner compliance policies, the growing number of competitors, and Facebook’s attribution chaos that came with Apple’s iOS 14.5 update, Revealbot’s MRR grew by 62% during my time there.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-revenue-growth.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-revenue-growth.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-revenue-growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Revealbot's MRR grew by 62% (dollar figures hidden)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Revealbot's MRR grew by 62% (dollar figures hidden)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marketing supported this growth in four key areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repositioned Revealbot to be more for well established ecommerce brands and by effect increased customer quality and the lifetime value of our customers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improved the trial to paid customer conversion rate by creating a video course, which helped speed up the time it took customers to get value from the product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased organic traffic by 1,279% to around 8,000 users per week through our SEO and content program.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;redesigned the website which improved the website’s traffic to trial start conversion rate by 10%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New accounts generated per month grew around 22% between December 2019 and June 2021 (we didn’t have accurate tracking before December).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-new-account-growth.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-new-account-growth.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-new-account-growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Revealbot's new account growth (new account numbers hidden)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Revealbot's new account growth (new account numbers hidden)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/revealbot-revenue-growth.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/revealbot-revenue-growth.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Grew Organic Traffic 1,279% Through Content &amp;amp; SEO Program</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/revealbot-seo-case-study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grew Organic Traffic 1,279% Through Content &amp; SEO Program" /><published>2022-04-17T19:37:27-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-17T19:37:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/revealbot-seo-case-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/revealbot-seo-case-study">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined Revealbot, we had several blog posts that were ranking on the bottom of page one and two in Google’s Search Result Pages (SERPs) because our website already had a very strong and healthy backlink profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Although our posts and pages were ranking relatively well, we weren’t getting much traffic to them. They needed to be in the top five results in the SERPs to get meaningful traffic. At the start of committing to improving our organic traffic, we were averaging ~500 organic users per month.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We used three strategies to improve our organic traffic:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find the opportunities with an SEO audit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update existing website pages and blog posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategically create new content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-i---complete-an-seo-audit&quot;&gt;Part I - Complete an SEO Audit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using a combination of Screaming Frog, Ahrefs, Google Webmaster Tools, and Google Analytics, I ran a complete site audit to identify all opportunities for improvement on every page of the public-facing website.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what the main audit looked like in Google Sheets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-audit.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-audit.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-audit.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dynamic SEO audit spreadsheet for Revealbot&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Dynamic SEO audit spreadsheet for Revealbot&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although everything couldn’t fit in this screenshot, the sheet incorporated data from all the data sources mentioned above held in different tabs. This main dashboard was built with formulas so I could always update one of the data sources in their respective tab, for example export the latest data from Webmaster Tools, and now the new data would populate automatically in this dashboard tab. This made the health of our SEO easy to frequently monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the data sources were pulled together, we could immediately identify opportunities, including the foundational items, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Establish a keyword for every URL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update titles - unique, under max character count, included the keyword, yet written for humans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update descriptions - unique, included the keyword, written to generate curiosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change page URL to one that includes the keyword and implement 301 redirects from the old URL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we did some more advanced optimizations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine pages/posts which were competing for the same keyword&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Edit main website and blog template’s HTML to ensure they are following the correct HTML structure best practices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify what stage of the buyer’s journey each page is serving, TOFU, MOFU, or BOFU (or Brand) to quantify opportunity and prioritize pages to update&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add more internal links from pages with the highest page ranking to pages with the highest opportunity for leads and traffic that are not ranking in the top three of the SERPs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add and refine content to pages starting with ones with the highest opportunity to bring in more leads and traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-ii---update-existing-website-pages-and-blog-posts&quot;&gt;Part II - Update existing website pages and blog posts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After making the quick fixes discovered in the SEO audit, it was time to invest in the more significant updates to pages in order to get them to rank higher in the SERPs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the audit, we labeled each page and post with their respective stage of the buyer’s journey based on its content and primary keyword: TOFU, MOFU, or BOFU. Roughly, if it was about accomplishing what the product does, it was BOFU; the challenges people had close to our product, MOFU; not related to the solutions or challenges of our product area but industry relevant, TOFU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we identified the top ranking competing URL for each page’s target keyword that we could reasonably expect to beat (e.g. excluding facebook.com). We analyzed these pages to see what others were doing in terms of how they met the searcher’s intent, content quality, and length that helped them rank so high. This was our standard to beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There were two considerations for prioritizing which pages or posts to update first:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BOFU pages, because more traffic to BOFU pages should produce more leads&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current ranking and perceived difficulty to get to a top three position in the SERPs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we got to work updating the pages and posts knowing these would get us the quickest and most impactful results in 60-90 days. Over time, we rewrote, updated, and optimized every post and page on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iii---strategically-create-new-content&quot;&gt;Part III - Strategically create new content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final solution to increasing our organic traffic was creating new content around valuable search queries we don’t have existing content for. Of course, there were many new pages and posts, so here are my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facebook-ad-cost-tool&quot;&gt;Facebook Ad Cost Tool&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the best ways to generate passive backlinks is to create a report with proprietary data, or in other words be a source of original data.&lt;/strong&gt; With content like this, journalists and other content writers will use our research as a source for their articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revealbot’s proprietary data comes from our customers who need to connect their Facebook ad accounts to our platform to use the product. So we had access to hundreds of millions of dollars of Facebook ad spend data we could combine, anonymize, and analyze. With all this data, we decided to publish monthly reports of Facebook and Instagram advertising costs and its fluctuations over time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test whether this idea would generate traffic and backlinks, we first pulled this data ad-hoc every month and published it in a blog post format with charts of our data. Here’s what it looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-facebook-ad-cost-tool-old.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-facebook-ad-cost-tool-old.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-facebook-ad-cost-tool-old.png&quot; alt=&quot;MVP of Revealbot's Facebook ad cost tool&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;MVP of Revealbot's Facebook ad cost tool&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few months, our article reached the first page in the SERPs and up to position three. That’s when we started getting a ton of traffic for search queries like &lt;strong&gt;facebook advertising costs&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;facebook ad costs&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;facebook cpm&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;facebook cpc&lt;/strong&gt;, etc. Not only that, we started getting backlinks from people referencing our data in their blog posts and even sharing our branded graphs in their article, too. This was the signal we needed to automate it and build it is a proper “mini app.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our engineering team built an &lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/facebook-advertising-costs&quot;&gt;automatically updating Facebook and Instagram ad cost data tool&lt;/a&gt;. It updates every week and provides current and historical data for CPM, CPC, CPE, CPL, and CPI for both Facebook and Instagram ads. The cost data can even be broken down by campaign objective.&lt;/strong&gt; Here’s what the new tool looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-facebook-ad-cost-tool.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-facebook-ad-cost-tool.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-facebook-ad-cost-tool.png&quot; alt=&quot;Completed form of Revealbot's Facebook ad cost tool&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Completed form of Revealbot's Facebook ad cost tool&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And based on what information you’re viewing, for example Facebook CPM, the URL changes. The H1 changes. The supporting content below the graph changes. Everything was built with SEO in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we started getting even more backlinks. We got links from competitors, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.hunchads.com/facebook-ads-cost&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hunch Ads&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wordstream.com/blog/ws/2021/07/12/facebook-ads-cost&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wordstream&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adzooma.com/blog/how-much-does-facebook-marketing-cost/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AdZooma&lt;/a&gt;. Respectable Facebook ad agencies, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://klientboost.com/facebook/how-to-run-facebook-ads/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;KlientBoost&lt;/a&gt;. And huge companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shopify.com/blog/facebook-ads-cost&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shopify&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shopify.com/blog/instagram-ads&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;twice&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.hubspot.com/insiders/how-to-shift-your-marketing-from-traditional-to-inbound&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HubSpot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/the-butt-pajamas-will-follow-you-forever-1845929307&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gizmodo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/08/facebook-reveals-top-posts-but-still-wont-share-key-data-about-disinformation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ars Technica&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/article/4476242-shopify-the-future-of-retail&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Seeking Alpha&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As of writing this case study, the tool has generated backlinks from over 380 domains, over 100k unique visitors, and increased the awareness of our brand and product in the industry. It has boosted the SEO of our entire revealbot.com domain helping to improve the rankings of all our other pages.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-ad-cost-tool-backlinks.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-ad-cost-tool-backlinks.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-ad-cost-tool-backlinks.png&quot; alt=&quot;Number of domains linking to Revealbot's Facebook ad cost tool&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Number of domains linking to Revealbot's Facebook ad cost tool&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on top of all that SEO goodness, it’s been a consistent driver of new customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;revealbot-answers&quot;&gt;Revealbot Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes answering a search query just doesn’t need one to two thousand words to answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We created Revealbot Answers, a section on our blog, for short form content to target keywords in a question format.&lt;/strong&gt; Here’s what the section looked like on the blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-answers.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-answers.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-answers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dedicated section on the blog for Revealbot answers&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Dedicated section on the blog for Revealbot answers&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of the content we wrote for Revealbot Answers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/blog/how-much-should-i-spend-on-facebook-ads/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How much should I spend on Facebook ads?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/blog/facebook-ad-scheduling/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;What is Facebook ad scheduling?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/blog/facebook-automated-rules-broken-not-working/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Are Facebook automated rules broken after iOS 14.5?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These are much less resource heavy articles, which means we can create many of them quickly. Plus, because these are usually long tailed keywords, we have a great chance of ranking well and quickly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-serp-example.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-serp-example.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-serp-example.png&quot; alt=&quot;Search result page for a Revealbot answers blog post&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Search result page for a Revealbot answers blog post&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This was such a success that I think every B2B blog needs an “answers” section to take advantage of long-tailed keywords written in a question.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facebook-and-instagram-ads-updates-and-changes&quot;&gt;Facebook and Instagram Ads Updates and Changes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being a resource for Facebook and Instagram ad cost data, I wanted Revealbot to be a resource for the ever changing ad platform and algorithm changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We created two blog posts, one for &lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/blog/facebook-update-changes-news/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook ad updates&lt;/a&gt; and another for &lt;a href=&quot;https://revealbot.com/blog/instagram-algorithm-update-news/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Instagram ad updates&lt;/a&gt;. These pieces of content were extremely resource heavy. They not only required a lot of research to be a reliable source of information, but they also required those updates to be timely. When a big update happens, Facebook ad advertisers look for answers immediately. We couldn’t update the post every day, but we did get to a point where we could update them monthly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our timing challenges, we were able to get them up to position three or four in the SERPs and became our second biggest driver of traffic behind our Facebook ad cost tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were able to invest more resources into producing this content, we really could have been a go-to source of Facebook ad update information with a unique design (similar again to a “mini app”) that sets it apart from any other blog post you can find on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At the time I joined Revealbot in August 2019, we were averaging 580 organic users per week. Just about two years later, traffic grew 1,279% to around 8,000 users per week.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo results-full.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo results-full.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo results-full.png&quot; alt=&quot;Results in Google Analytics of 1,000% organic search growth&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Results in Google Analytics of 1,000% organic search growth&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By optimizing our main website pages for search and reaching the top #1 to #3 spots in the SERPs, we were able to generate significant organic signups. Below is a table of the top landing pages that generate new account signups from organic search sessions. A significant portion comes from core sevice pages, competitor pages, and the Facebook Ad Cost Tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-report.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-report.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-report.png&quot; alt=&quot;First column is landing page URL, second column is the number of new signups&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;First column is landing page URL, second column is the number of new signups&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organic clicks from non brand search queries.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-non-brand-organic-traffic-growth.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-non-brand-organic-traffic-growth.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-non-brand-organic-traffic-growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Organic, non-brand traffic growth results in Google Webmaster Tools&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Organic, non-brand traffic growth results in Google Webmaster Tools&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Along with the traffic, our domain strength and SEO profile grew tremendously as well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/revealbot-seo-ahrefs-domain-strength.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-ahrefs-domain-strength.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/revealbot-seo-ahrefs-domain-strength.png&quot; alt=&quot;Backlinks, traffic, and keyword growth from Ahrefs&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Backlinks, traffic, and keyword growth from Ahrefs&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/revealbot-seo-results.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/revealbot-seo-results.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Options Trading 101: Options Explained in Plain English</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/trading-stock-options-101-beginners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Options Trading 101: Options Explained in Plain English" /><published>2020-04-12T05:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-12T05:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/trading-stock-options-101-beginners</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/trading-stock-options-101-beginners">&lt;p&gt;Stock options are just like coupons. And if you know how to use a coupon, you’ll know how trading stock options work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stock-options-101-how-options-work&quot;&gt;Stock Options 101: How Options Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain how options work, let’s start with looking at something you’re already familiar with - a coupon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take this one for example - get ten-piece nuggets for $1.99 before March 15, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-tendies.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-tendies.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-tendies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coupons are exactly like stock options&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Coupons are exactly like stock options&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although coupons are free, options are not. You have to buy them. I’ll cover more on this later so for now, just assume you bought this coupon for $0.50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with this coupon, you have the choice to buy ten-piece nuggets at a guaranteed price of $1.99 before March 15th, but you don’t have to use it if you don’t want to. You have the &lt;em&gt;option&lt;/em&gt; to, but not the obligation. This coupon has essentially the same makeup as a stock option:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ten-piece nuggets are the &lt;strong&gt;underlying asset&lt;/strong&gt;, the thing which you have an option to buy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$1.99 is what’s called the &lt;strong&gt;strike price&lt;/strong&gt;, the price you and the seller &lt;em&gt;struck&lt;/em&gt; a deal on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;March 15, 2020 is the &lt;strong&gt;expiration date&lt;/strong&gt;, the last day you have the option available to use it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The $0.50 you paid for the coupon is called the &lt;strong&gt;premium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investor would buy this coupon if they think the price of chicken will go up before the expiration date so they can buy ten-piece nuggets at a guaranteed price of $1.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say there’s been a global chicken shortage and now the cost for ten-piece nuggets went up from $1.99 ($2 for simplicity’s sake) to $6. Now the investor can &lt;strong&gt;exercise&lt;/strong&gt; their option to use the coupon and buy ten-piece nuggets for the $2 price and resell them on the open market for $6. After factoring in the premium paid of the coupon ($0.50), the investor profited $3.50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if instead veganism has taken over and now ten-piece nuggets only cost $1? Since the investor could now buy ten-piece nuggets for $1 on the open market, they have no reason to use the coupon to buy them for $2. This makes the coupon worthless. In this scenario, the investor wouldn’t exercise their option to use the coupon and their loss is only the $0.50 premium they paid for the coupon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Options, at their core, are really this simple. Although they can get more complex when it comes to buying, selling, and using them in various investment strategies, they aren’t impossible to understand. Let’s leave behind the coupon analogy and now look at the two different types of option contracts and their makeup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-an-options-contract&quot;&gt;What is an Options Contract?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An options contract is an agreement that gives the purchaser an option to buy or sell a stock at a later date at a predetermined price. The agreement is always between two parties, a buyer (a.k.a. the holder or owner) and a seller (a.k.a. the writer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expiration date is when the option expires. When you’re the buyer, you can exercise an option on or before the expiration date. When you’re the seller, you can be &lt;strong&gt;assigned&lt;/strong&gt; to fulfill your obligation of the contract on or before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only two main types of option contracts, call options and put options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call options&lt;/strong&gt;, or “calls” for short, give the buyer the right to &lt;em&gt;call&lt;/em&gt; the underlying asset away from the option seller and buy it at a predetermined price up to a predetermined date. An investor purchases a call option contract when they think the price of the underlying asset will &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; in value beyond the agreed upon strike price before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put options&lt;/strong&gt;, or “puts” for short, give the buyer the right to &lt;em&gt;put&lt;/em&gt; the underlying asset up for sale and sell it to the option seller at a predetermined price up to a predetermined date. An investor purchases a put option contract when they think the price of the underlying asset will &lt;em&gt;decrease&lt;/em&gt; in value beyond the the agreed upon strike price before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both call and put options are contracts that give the buyer &lt;em&gt;the right&lt;/em&gt; to buy or sell the underlying asset, and not &lt;em&gt;the obligation&lt;/em&gt; to do so. Therefore, the seller of the contract is giving up &lt;em&gt;their right&lt;/em&gt; and control. So what’s in it for the seller? Since the option contract has value, the buyer has to pay the seller for it. This payment is called the &lt;strong&gt;premium&lt;/strong&gt;. The price for the underlying asset that the two parties agreed upon is called the &lt;strong&gt;strike price&lt;/strong&gt; because that’s the price they “struck” a deal on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ways-to-exit-an-options-trade&quot;&gt;Ways to exit an options trade&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the underlying asset’s value moves &lt;em&gt;in favor&lt;/em&gt; of the option buyer before the expiration date, they can sell the option contract itself to another buyer at a higher premium for a profit. At expiration, if the price of the underlying asset has moved beyond the strike price (this is called &lt;strong&gt;in the money&lt;/strong&gt;), they can exercise their option of the contract to buy the underlying asset at the strike price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the underlying asset’s value moves &lt;em&gt;out of favor&lt;/em&gt; of the buyer before expiration, they can sell the option at a lower premium for a loss or continue to hold it to see if the underlying asset’s value changes to be in their favor in time for expiration. If at expiration the value of the underlying asset is still below the strike price (this is called &lt;strong&gt;out of the money&lt;/strong&gt;), the buyer can let the option contract expire worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The option seller (the contract writer) can also sell the contract to another investor to close their position before expiration. At expiration, if the option is in the money, they will still be able to keep the premium but they will be assigned to buy or sell (depends on the option they wrote) the underlying asset. If the option is out of the money, their position is automatically closed and their capital is no longer at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are three ways to close out an options trade:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prior to expiration, you can buy or sell the contract itself to close your position (for profit or loss)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prior to or at expiration, the buyer can exercise their option in which the seller would get assigned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at expiration, the buyer can let the contract expire worthless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll discuss closing an options trade in more detail in a future article about option contract pricing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-read-an-options-contract&quot;&gt;How to Read an Options Contract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you know how option contracts work and their makeup, you can now learn to “read” an option. Here’s an example of an options contract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SPY MARCH 15 ’20 $260 CALL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPY&lt;/strong&gt; is the ticker for the underlying asset, in this case the S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MARCH 15 ’20&lt;/strong&gt; is the expiration date&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$260&lt;/strong&gt; is the strike price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call&lt;/strong&gt; is the type of option, in this case a call&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every broker is different and may display the elements of an options contract in different orders and formats, but they are all generally the same. Sometimes you will see an option in shorthand that can look confusing, but it’s all the same information, just more compact. For example, this is the same option as above but for a put instead of a call:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SPY051520P220&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPY&lt;/strong&gt; is the ticker, &lt;strong&gt;051520&lt;/strong&gt; is the expiration date (5/15/2020), &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; is the option type (in this case a put, or could be &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; for call), and &lt;strong&gt;220&lt;/strong&gt; is the strike price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-trade-option-contracts-instead-of-stocks-directly&quot;&gt;Why Trade Option Contracts Instead of Stocks Directly?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With trading stocks (or any equity), you have limited leverage and flexibility. For the most part, you can only &lt;em&gt;buy&lt;/em&gt; a stock or &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; a stock. With trading options, you have much more leverage and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look first at how an option provides more leverage. &lt;strong&gt;A single options contract (almost) always controls 100 shares of the underlying asset.&lt;/strong&gt; So in other words, you can control 100 shares for the price of the option’s premium without having to buy 100 shares of the stock outright. For example, SPY is currently trading at $240. You could buy 100 shares outright for $24,000 or you could buy one call option contract for a fraction of the price, which could be anywhere from, say, $400 to upwards of $1,000 depending on the strike price and expiration. Or, you can invest $24,000 to buy 40 call option contracts with a $6 premium ($600 total per contract) to instead control 4,000 shares of SPY worth $960,000. This is how options provide more leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of flexibility, trading stocks is one directional, up or down, and your profit and loss is directly tied 1:1 with the stock. Here is the profit and loss payoff chart for going long on a stock and shorting a stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/buy-stock-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/buy-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/buy-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and shorting a stock&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/short-stock-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/short-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/short-stock-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and shorting a stock&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Payoff diagrams for buying and shorting a stock&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you buy a stock (a.k.a. go “long”), you profit when the stock’s price increases and incur a loss when the stock’s price decreases. When you short a stock, you profit when the stock’s price decreases and incur a loss when the stock’s price increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are the payoff charts for buying and selling a call option contract and buying and selling a put option contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/buy-call-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/buy-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/buy-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/buy-put-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/buy-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/buy-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/sell-call-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/sell-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sell-call-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/sell-put-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/sell-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sell-put-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Payoff diagrams for buying and selling call and put option contracts&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice immediately the differences. Each of the above option strategies either have a limit to how much loss you can incur or a limit to how much profit you can gain. Behind the scenes, they each have their own levels of risk and probability of making a profit to tolerate with these limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying and selling call or put option contracts are just scratching the surface, too. By combining different types of options with different strike prices, you can create unique option strategies to profit in any kind of market movement. Here’s some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/bull-call-spread-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/bull-call-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/bull-call-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/bear-put-spread-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/bear-put-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/bear-put-spread-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/long-butterfly-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/long-butterfly-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/long-butterfly-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/long-straddle-option-payoff-diagram.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/long-straddle-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image no-dark-filter&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/long-straddle-option-payoff-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Payoff diagrams for various advanced option strategies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about these for now. Just understand that with options, you have the ability to limit both profit and loss in a single trade, profit if there is little movement in an equity, or profit if there is a lot of movement regardless if it’s up or down. This is how options provide more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-read-the-options-chain&quot;&gt;How to Read the Options Chain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pull up a stock or ETF and you should see a link for “options.” Clicking this will take you to what’s called the &lt;strong&gt;options chain&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a scary looking table full of numbers you won’t understand. But don’t worry, here’s how to read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each broker will display their options chain differently, but they will all have the same essential information, and some will offer more. Here’s an example of options chain from E*Trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-option-chain.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-option-chain.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-option-chain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of a simple options chain (from E*Trade)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of a simple options chain (from E*Trade)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled up the options chain for the symbol &lt;strong&gt;SPY&lt;/strong&gt; as indicated in the top left and the type of options chain we’re looking at is the default &lt;strong&gt;Calls &amp;amp; Puts&lt;/strong&gt; chain (don’t worry about the others for now). In the next section is some standard quote information and immediately below that is where the information for the options chain begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The option chains are divided into different sections by the various &lt;strong&gt;expiration dates&lt;/strong&gt; shown as tabs. You’ll see I have &lt;em&gt;April 9 ’20&lt;/em&gt; selected. Clicking on the various expiration dates will change the data in the table beneath it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each row in this table is an individual options contract you can buy or sell. Splitting the table down the middle is the &lt;strong&gt;strike price&lt;/strong&gt; column. By default, option chains will show a certain number of available contracts with a strike price below and above the current price of the underlying asset (again, SPY in this case). The current price of SPY at the time of this screenshot is $272 as seen in the quote section. You can change which strike prices are shown by entering a desired strike price at the top in the “Near” box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left side of the strike price column in the table are &lt;strong&gt;call option contracts&lt;/strong&gt; and to the right of the strike price are &lt;strong&gt;put option contracts&lt;/strong&gt;. Since the current price of SPY is $272, all the call option contracts with a strike price below $272 are shaded blue because they are &lt;strong&gt;in the money&lt;/strong&gt; (often abbreviated as ITM). You can see the same thing on the right side for put option contracts with strike prices above $272. Contracts that are not shaded blue are considered &lt;strong&gt;out of the money&lt;/strong&gt; (OTM). When an option contract’s strike price is the same as the underlying asset’s current price (or within a few cents), it’s considered an &lt;strong&gt;at the money&lt;/strong&gt; option (ATM). ITM, ATM, and OTM are the three types of &lt;strong&gt;option moneyness&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the table you’ll see lots of numbers. Here’s the breakdown of each column:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Interest&lt;/strong&gt; is the total number of these contracts that are currently active and open&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vol&lt;/strong&gt;, short for volume, is the number of these contracts that were opened just today&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change&lt;/strong&gt; is today’s price (premium) movement of that contract since the closing price of the previous trading day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last&lt;/strong&gt; is the price (also called the &lt;strong&gt;mark&lt;/strong&gt;) of the contract’s last completed transaction, whether opened or closed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bid&lt;/strong&gt; is the current maximum price buyers are willing to pay for that contract&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask&lt;/strong&gt; is the current minimum price sellers are willing sell that contract for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a more advanced options chain table from Power E*Trade, their more advanced options trading platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-advanced-options-chain.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-advanced-options-chain.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-advanced-options-chain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the options chain from a more advanced broker (from Power E*Trade)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the options chain from a more advanced broker (from Power E*Trade)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first point out these options chains are &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; looking at call option contracts - notice the strike price column is not in the middle anymore but all the way to the right. That’s because with more advanced option trading platforms, you can hide one side or the other to see more columns of information for a contract all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these options chains look completely different on the surface, it’s still mostly the same information. Take a minute to compare this screenshot to the previous one and try to spot what’s the same and what’s new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first difference you might notice is I’ve selected multiple expiration dates, &lt;em&gt;Apr-09-20&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Apr-15-20&lt;/em&gt; and you can see both option chains displayed below at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a breakdown of the data in the new columns in the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bid Size&lt;/strong&gt; is the number of contracts buyers have placed buy orders for that are waiting to be filled at the current bid price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask Size&lt;/strong&gt; is the number of contracts sellers have placed sell orders for that are waiting to be filled at the current ask price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delta&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Gamma&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Theta&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Vega&lt;/strong&gt; (along with &lt;strong&gt;Rho&lt;/strong&gt; which isn’t shown) are referred to as the &lt;strong&gt;Greeks&lt;/strong&gt; and I’m going to cover this in another article - don’t worry about them for now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implied Volatility&lt;/strong&gt; or IV is a measurement of how volatile the price of that contract is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prob ITM Exp ATM IV&lt;/strong&gt; is the probability that contract will be ITM at it’s expiration date (this is calculated using the IV from the same expiration date contract that’s currently ATM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intrinsic Value&lt;/strong&gt; is the dollar value worth per contract if it expired right now. Only contracts ITM have an intrinsic value greater than 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extrinsic Value&lt;/strong&gt; is the dollar value worth per contract investors give an option based on its profit potential at expiration that has not yet been realized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-buy-to-open-an-option-trade&quot;&gt;How to Buy to Open an Option Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you can buy to open an options contract, you will need to get option approval from your brokerage. How to accomplish this is different with each broker, but should be easy to figure out. There are typically four levels of option access, with each level permitting different types of option strategies. Apply for at least level two. Your broker will tell you what each level grants access to. Once you submit your request, it may take a few trading days to be approved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various ways for each broker to &lt;em&gt;open a new position&lt;/em&gt; for an options contract, but you can most likely click a contract’s ask price to buy it or the bid price to write (sell) it. Here’s what it looks like in Power E*Trade to buy the April 15th $268 contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/basics-stock-options-order.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-order.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/basics-stock-options-order.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of an option order window (from Power E*Trade)&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of an option order window (from Power E*Trade)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at the very top, confirm you have the right account selected&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;below that, confirm the symbol is correct, in this case SPY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confirm whether you want to buy or write the option using the &lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; toggle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;select the number of contracts you want to buy under &lt;strong&gt;Qty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confirm your &lt;strong&gt;Expiration&lt;/strong&gt; date is correct&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confirm your &lt;strong&gt;Strike&lt;/strong&gt; price is correct&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price Type&lt;/strong&gt; let’s you choose how you want your order executed, I recommend to always use limit to secure your desired price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set your desired price under &lt;strong&gt;Limit Price&lt;/strong&gt;. To the right, you can see the bid and ask price for the contract change in real time as you’re placing your order&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set how long you want your order to stay open under &lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set whether you want your order to process only if it can buy or write all the contracts at your limit price under &lt;strong&gt;Special Handling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After everything looks correct, clicking the &lt;strong&gt;Preview&lt;/strong&gt; button will allow you to do one final confirmation of your trade before placing an order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-sell-to-close-an-option-trade&quot;&gt;How to Sell to Close an Option Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close an open position, go to your open positions list in your broker and find the position you want to close. There should be a &lt;em&gt;close&lt;/em&gt; button or link when you hover over it or select it. This is the best way, at least for me, to ensure you’re closing a position, instead of &lt;em&gt;selling to open&lt;/em&gt; a new position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s an overview of what options are, how they work, why options can be a useful instrument for investors, and how to open and close an option trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next article, I’ll cover what affects a contract’s price, dive deeper into the definitions of some of the items in this article (e.g. IV, Prob ITM, etc), and explain what each of the Greeks mean.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Stock options are just like coupons. And if you know how to use a coupon, you’ll know how trading stock options work.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/basics-stock-options-trading.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)" /><published>2020-02-07T00:51:34-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:51:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/google-sheets-budget-template">&lt;p&gt;I have a strange love for spreadsheets and I want to share the budget template I made on Google Sheets that I’ve been using and building for over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make your own copy by clicking the link below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1FyZvG4UI11Kd-kaVPpUiV5mRjgPz4OERfxak_KXCsgU/copy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; id=&quot;budget_download&quot;&gt;Make a copy: My Google Sheets Budget Template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The template is based off the principles and concepts from Ramit Sethi’s personal finance book, &lt;em&gt;“I Will Teach You to Be Rich.”&lt;/em&gt; I’ll cover everything you need to know in this post, but if you want to learn more about it, you can read my summary of the book below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The best introduction to personal finance and how to enjoy spending your money.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ramit Sethi I Will Teach You to Be Rich&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-this-google-sheets-budget-template-better-than-the-others-out-there&quot;&gt;What Makes This Google Sheets Budget Template Better Than The Others Out There&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;all-the-setup-is-on-one-page&quot;&gt;All the setup is on one page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just one configuration tab, you’ll fill out all your info: income, account names, budget, etc. All the other tabs pull data from this &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab so you never have to enter in any information twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-one-page-settings.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-one-page-settings.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-one-page-settings.png&quot; alt=&quot;Once you set up this Config tab, just enter expenses and account balances. That's it!&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Once you set up this Config tab, just enter expenses and account balances. That's it!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;built-in-guided-setup&quot;&gt;Built-in guided setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening up a new Google Sheets budget template with all these numbers and tabs can be daunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I wanted to create a guided setup to make it super simple for anyone to get started. When you open up the template, you’ll be greeted with easy-to-follow prompts so you know exactly what you need to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/guided-tour.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Bright orange prompts make this the easiest Google Sheets budget template to get set up on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setup-checklist&quot;&gt;Setup checklist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing the configuration settings, the checklist shows you where to go next in the template to enter your expenses and account balances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-setup-checklist.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-setup-checklist.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-setup-checklist.png&quot; alt=&quot;The setup checklist will automatically mark things complete as you finish each step.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The setup checklist will automatically mark things complete as you finish each step.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-dashboard-to-rule-them-all&quot;&gt;One dashboard to rule them all&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Google Sheets budget template has four tabs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; - the main tab where you can see your spending vs budget for the current month and analyze previous months’ spending. All the data is pulled from the other tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; - where you enter all your expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; - to record your bank account, retirement account, credit card and loan balances, etc. This data is used to help measure whether your net worth is increasing or shrinking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; - as explained above, this is where you fill out your income, name your accounts, and set your budgets, which is used in all the other tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll spend most of your time in the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;The dashboard is the clearest way to see where you're spending your money.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The dashboard is the clearest way to see where you're spending your money.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;always-know-how-much-of-your-monthly-budget-you-have-left&quot;&gt;Always know how much of your monthly budget you have left&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you fill out your expenses, there’s a “module” where you can see exactly how much of a budget category you’ve used so far in the current month and know exactly how much you have left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve overspent in one budget category, the template will let you take remaining budget from another category to cover it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/budget-module.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This makes it fun to fill out your expenses everyday and it's easy to temporarily take budget from another category to cover one you've overspent in.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budget-and-keep-track-of-annual-irregular-expenses&quot;&gt;Budget and keep track of annual, irregular expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The template is also built to accommodate irregular expenses that you might only spend money on or have to pay for a few times a year. Once you enter a list of the things you want to create an annual budget for, the template will calculate how much you need to save per month to cover it. And that amount is deducted before you set up your monthly budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; alt=&quot;This template helps you plan for irregular or annual expenses.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This template helps you plan for irregular or annual expenses.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spend-your-money-without-feeling-guilty&quot;&gt;Spend your money without feeling guilty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call the monthly budget the &lt;em&gt;“guilt-free budget,”&lt;/em&gt; which is a concept taken from the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://regpaq.com/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I Will Teach You to Be Rich.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Since the budget template is built to help you put aside money for savings before creating your monthly budget, it means you don’t ever have to feel guilty about spending the money you do have left over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a fundamental shift in my perspective about personal finance Ramit calls &lt;em&gt;paying yourself first.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;built-to-drive-behavioral-change&quot;&gt;Built to drive behavioral change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my friends use a budgeting app like Mint and I’ve tried them, too. But these apps don’t really help me spend less money - they just tell me where I spend my money and try to guess (poorly) the category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I love budgets built on spreadsheets. I can customize it exactly the way I need to actually help me spend my money more thoughtfully. On less of things I care little about, and more on the things I care a lot about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A bad budget system only shows you where your money is going. A good budget system will create a change in your behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1FyZvG4UI11Kd-kaVPpUiV5mRjgPz4OERfxak_KXCsgU/copy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; id=&quot;budget_download&quot;&gt;try my Google Sheets budget template&lt;/a&gt;, make a copy of it and try it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are simple and clear instructions with extra notes on cells that have an asterisk(*) - just hover over those cells to the see note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re stuck and need more info to get going, read on to get the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-my-google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;How to Use My Google Sheets Budget Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, cells with an asterisk(*) mean there is a note on that cell with more information. Hover over it to see what it says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-enter-your-income&quot;&gt;I. Enter your income&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the top left box on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab, enter your income. Follow the orange colored cells as cues for which part to fill out next. If you don’t &lt;strong&gt;contribute to a 401k&lt;/strong&gt; or typically receive any &lt;strong&gt;extra monthly income&lt;/strong&gt;, enter $0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-income.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-income.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-income.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your income data in the Income Breakdown box on the Dashbord tab&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your income data in the Income Breakdown box on the Dashbord tab&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This budget template is only made for two sources of income. If you have more than one additional source of income, you can count them together and enter the total as one number for your &lt;strong&gt;extra monthly income&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All income entered here will be available for your budget. Before leaving the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab, you’ll be able to choose how much of it will go into savings, additional retirement accounts, loans, etc, but first you have to name your accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ii-name-your-accounts&quot;&gt;II. Name your accounts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to give a &lt;strong&gt;nickname&lt;/strong&gt; for every type of bank account, asset, and liability you have. The &lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt; is very important to formulas in in the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tabs and cannot be changed. If you don’t have an account with the listed &lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt;, leave it blank and skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-bank-account-names.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-bank-account-names.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-bank-account-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-asset-names.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-asset-names.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-asset-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-liability-names.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-liability-names.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-liability-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Giving each account you have a nickname tells the budget template you have those accounts.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have more accounts than what the &lt;strong&gt;types&lt;/strong&gt; have you can count them together as one. For example, if you have four credit cards, you can count two of them together and give &lt;strong&gt;credit card #3&lt;/strong&gt; the nickname &lt;strong&gt;Amex &amp;amp; Citi cards&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iii-create-your-annual-budget&quot;&gt;III. Create your annual budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why you create your budget for annual expenses before monthly expenses is so that you’re encouraged to set aside money to be better prepared for irregular expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by adding things you pay for once a year or irregularly in the &lt;strong&gt;Annual Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box. You can find examples and suggestions by hovering over the &lt;strong&gt;budget category*&lt;/strong&gt; cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your annual and irregular expenses to prepare for the future.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your annual and irregular expenses to prepare for the future.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you enter in all the annual and irregular expenses you can think of, the budget template will divide the &lt;strong&gt;total&lt;/strong&gt; into a monthly amount inside the &lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-enter-your-fixed-monthly-costs&quot;&gt;IV. Enter your fixed monthly costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; are recurring monthly expenses that you don’t expect to change month-to-month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the list is the monthly amount to set aside for your &lt;strong&gt;annual budget&lt;/strong&gt; and the second item is your &lt;strong&gt;after tax retirement&lt;/strong&gt; account. If you have one and gave it a nickname in the &lt;strong&gt;Asset Names&lt;/strong&gt; box, the nickname will be used for this line item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have one or don’t plan on contributing to the one you do have, enter $0 for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-fixed-monthly-costs.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-fixed-monthly-costs.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-fixed-monthly-costs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter your fixed monthly costs.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter your fixed monthly costs.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is room for eight additional fixed monthly costs. There are suggestions in the note on the &lt;strong&gt;budget category*&lt;/strong&gt; cell. Along with budgeting for annual expenses and retirement, I highly recommend setting more money aside for extra savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;pay yourself first&lt;/em&gt; concept described in &lt;em&gt;“I Will Teach You to Be Rich.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The goal [of pay yourself first] is to make sure that enough income is first saved or invested before monthly expenses or discretionary purchases are made.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/payyourselffirst.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Investopedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you’re left with your &lt;strong&gt;total for guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt;, which is how much you have left for discretionary spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-create-your-guilt-free-monthly-budget&quot;&gt;IV. Create your guilt-free, monthly budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained earlier, it’s called your guilt-free budget because this is what is left over after setting money aside for savings, retiremenet, and future annual expenses. This is your money to spend however you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Guilt-Free Budget&lt;/strong&gt; box, enter categories of expenses and an allotted amount. Again, there are suggestions in the note on the &lt;strong&gt;budget category*&lt;/strong&gt; cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-guilt-free-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;After budgeting money for savings and annual expenses, you can budget your discretionary spending, guilt-free.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve budgeted over what you have available in your &lt;strong&gt;total for guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt; from the &lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; box, this &lt;strong&gt;total&lt;/strong&gt; number will turn red and. The number below the &lt;strong&gt;total&lt;/strong&gt; number is how much you have left from your &lt;strong&gt;guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your monthly and annual budget is now set up! The next step is setting up the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-setting-up-the-balance-sheet&quot;&gt;V. Setting up the balance sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going deep into the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;, you just need to enter your start date in the orange cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start date is the first of a month, current or in the past, written as &lt;em&gt;“1/1/2020”&lt;/em&gt;. Once you enter your start date, it will reformat to &lt;em&gt;“Jan ‘20”&lt;/em&gt; and fill the rest of the range for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/dates-on-balance-sheet.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Write the start date in the format of 1/1/2020.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do here, but it makes sense to first record your expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-how-to-record-expenses&quot;&gt;V. How to record expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; tab you’ll record your monthly and annual expenses - one row per one expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest presumable downsides of doing your budget in Google Sheets is you have to enter in your expenses manually, but this is a blessing in disguise. Entering your expenses manually has a big and positive psychological effect on your spending behavior. It makes you “feel the pain” of every dollar you spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Manually recording your expenses every week will force you to review every transaction, to feel the pain of every dollar spent, and make you think “was that really necessary?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit is you can easily split an expense into two different budget categories, which I’ve found helpful many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/entering-expenses.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of how fast you can enter expenses by using the 'tab' and 'enter' keys&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the heading, you’ll see your &lt;strong&gt;guilt-free budget&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;annual budget&lt;/strong&gt; categories from the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab. When you enter an expense, start with the date in &lt;strong&gt;column a&lt;/strong&gt;, the name of the place you spend the money in &lt;strong&gt;column b&lt;/strong&gt;, and then tab over to the column with the right budget category for that expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and enter all your expenses beginning from the start date you entered on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t enter expenses or transfers you already accounted for in the &lt;strong&gt;Fixed Monthly Costs&lt;/strong&gt; box on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vi-filling-out-the-balance-sheet&quot;&gt;VI. Filling out the balance sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the beginning of every month you’ll fill out the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tab for the previous month. This is where you will add up all the money you have and owe in your accounts so you can see if your wealth and net worth are increasing or shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before moving on, make sure the first three items are marked complete in the &lt;strong&gt;Setup&lt;/strong&gt; checklist on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet’s&lt;/strong&gt; sidebar, you’ll see the accounts you’ve named on the &lt;strong&gt;Config&lt;/strong&gt; tab. At the beginning of the month when you fill this out, you’ll enter the balances of each account in the previous month’s column. For example, if I was filling this out today on February 7th, I’d enter the balances under the &lt;strong&gt;Jan ‘20&lt;/strong&gt; column. So if you’re starting date is the first of this month, you don’t have to fill out anything until the month is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You only need to enter balances in the white rows. You can skip the greyed out columns (don’t delete them) and don’t overwrite anything with a &lt;strong&gt;-&lt;/strong&gt; in the cell. The dashes indicate a placeholder for a formula and will populate if and when it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Enter the previous months' ending balances in each row for the indicated month.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enter the previous months' ending balances in each row for the indicated month.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Liabilities&lt;/strong&gt; section, you’ll do the same thing as you do with your bank accounts but for your rent/mortgage, loans, and credit cards. If you don’t have a mortgage, enter $0 for the &lt;strong&gt;rent&lt;/strong&gt;. Rent is paid on the 1st of the month so by the end of the month, which these totals are representing, you don’t owe anymore rent. So actually, &lt;strong&gt;rent&lt;/strong&gt; should be $0 for every month in the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pay a mortgage, then you can enter the mortgage payoff amount in the &lt;strong&gt;mortgage&lt;/strong&gt; row. I do the same with my &lt;strong&gt;car loan&lt;/strong&gt;. When filling out your credit card balances, make sure any pending credit card payments are already reflected in your bank account balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-liabilities.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-liabilities.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-liabilities.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Liabilities section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Liabilities section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Annual Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; sections automatically sum your expenses for that month for each budget category. You can analyze this easier in the the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-expenses.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-expenses.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-expenses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Monthly and Annual Expenses secions with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Monthly and Annual Expenses secions with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last section is the &lt;strong&gt;Totals&lt;/strong&gt; section, which brings everything together to calculate your &lt;strong&gt;net checking balance&lt;/strong&gt; (money in checking minus current credit card balances) and your &lt;strong&gt;net worth&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last row you can leave notes for yourself if something noteworthy occurred that you might want to come back to. The word “Notes” will auto populate in each month, but to leave an actual note, right-click the &lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt; cell and select “Insert note.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-totals.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-totals.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-balance-sheet-totals.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of the Totals section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Example of the Totals section with sample data on the Balance Sheet tab.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all you need to do on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; tab. As you use this Google Sheets budget template each month, more data on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab will start to populate and be more useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vii-using-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;VII. Using the dashboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the best part - the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;. This is where you can see the most useful insights for your budget. Except for a small part that I’ll explain below, everything on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; is automated and you shouldn’t have to change anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top is an &lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt; box with just a few pieces of information to get your overall personal finance health. It’s updated every time a month is filled out on the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; so if your start date is the first of the current month, you won’t see anything here yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-overview.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-overview.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-overview.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Overview box on the Dashbord tab shows your personal finance health from a bird's eye view.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Overview box on the Dashbord tab shows your personal finance health from a bird's eye view.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the right of your &lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt; box is a graph of your &lt;strong&gt;Net Worth&lt;/strong&gt; growth. This is pulling the last seven months of data from the &lt;strong&gt;Balance Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--thin gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-net-worth.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-net-worth.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-net-worth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualize the grow of your net worth over time.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Visualize the grow of your net worth over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is my favorite part of the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;, the &lt;strong&gt;This Month’s Budget Spent So Far*&lt;/strong&gt; box. This shows how your spending is doing for the current month compared to your budget for each category. Since I update my &lt;strong&gt;Expenses&lt;/strong&gt; tab every morning, I can see my updated budget here every day so I know exactly how much of my budget I have left for each category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/budget-module.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This makes it fun to fill out your expenses everyday and it's easy to temporarily take budget from another category to cover one you overspent in.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you overspent in one category, you can subtract &lt;strong&gt;Remaining&lt;/strong&gt; budget from another budget category by subtracting an amount from it in the &lt;strong&gt;Cut Remaining*&lt;/strong&gt; column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the same module for annual expenses below the monthly one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-annual-budget-module.png&quot; alt=&quot;Always know exactly how much of your budget you have left of your annual budget for each category.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Always know exactly how much of your budget you have left of your annual budget for each category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the monthly and the annual &lt;strong&gt;Budget Spent So Far&lt;/strong&gt; boxes will update automatically every month and year respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is the &lt;strong&gt;Spent vs Budget Previous 7 Months*&lt;/strong&gt; box. This is a dynamic graph that compares your spending to your budget for each category. Use the dropdown selector in the top right of the box to look at a specific budget category or look at the total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;source src=&quot;assets/videos/spent-vs-budget.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/video&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Spent vs Budget box on the Dashbord tab visualizes your spending for each category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this graph is only looking at the previous seven completed months. It doesn’t take into account the current months’s spending because it’s not over yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last on the &lt;strong&gt;Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt; tab is the &lt;strong&gt;Expenses Table Previous 7 Months*&lt;/strong&gt; box. This provides the same data as the graph above, but in a table format. Amounts will turn red if you overspent your budget in that category that month. This is a great way to quickly see how you’re doing staying under budget at a glance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-expense-table.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-expense-table.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-dashboard-expense-table.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Expenses Last 7 Months box shows a table of your spending vs your budget for each category.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Expenses Last 7 Months box shows a table of your spending vs your budget for each category.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-budgeting-tips&quot;&gt;Bonus Budgeting Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A budget is only good if you update it consistently, keep it accurate, and spend time analyzing your spending. That’s why I made it a point to make this budget template in Google Sheets look nice, be easy to use, and be rewarding to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes that’s still not enough. &lt;strong&gt;There’s definitely been times where I don’t do it for a few weeks at a time and the more you wait, the more work you’ll have to do, and the more you won’t look forward to doing it&lt;/strong&gt;. I‘ve made it a habit to enter my expenses every morning instead of once a week or month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you believe a budget will help you get control of your spending, read this guide on how to stick to new habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-make-new-habits-stick.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tip is to use a credit card for all transactions when possible. Using a credit card makes it much easier to keep track of your spending and at the same time protects your bank account from fraud, builds your credit, and you can earn points and rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think of the spreadsheet. If you found some places where I messed up or have ideas for new functionality, let me know on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/regpaq&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">I have a strange love for spreadsheets and I want to share the budget template I made on Google Sheets that I’ve been using and building for over five years.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fathom Analytics Review (From a Marketer)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fathom-analytics-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fathom Analytics Review (From a Marketer)" /><published>2020-01-27T17:02:48-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-27T17:02:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fathom-analytics-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fathom-analytics-review">&lt;p&gt;Fathom Analytics is a cookie-less analytics platform that values user privacy above all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most marketers default to using Google Analytics for every website. It’s free, powerful, and the industry standard. Why try anything else, &lt;em&gt;right?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-wanted-an-alternative-to-google-analytics&quot;&gt;Why I Wanted an Alternative to Google Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s three reasons I wanted something different than Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It adds load time to a website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It uses cookies and requires a GDPR notice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It tracks users for Google’s own data gain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When rebuilding this site from scratch, one of my big focuses was on speed.&lt;/strong&gt; Since I was using Netlify to host and deploy my site from GitHub, I first tried their server-side analytics called &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netlify Analytics is cool because it tracks users on the server side vs the client side. That means it adds zero weight and load time to a website, doesn’t use cookies, and doesn’t track users. &lt;em&gt;Great!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the product isn’t nearly detailed enough to offer any actionable insights, especially at $9/month as I explained in my review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics Review (From a Marketer)&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Is it everything the industry has been waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/netlify-analytics-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/netlify-analytics-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/netlify-analytics-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;netlify analytics review from a marketer&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So still interested in other analytics platforms, I heard about Fathom through Twitter. Although it’s not server-side analytics, it is cookie-less and doesn’t add much more load time than Google Analytics does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of Fathom started in 2018 from a tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pjrvs/&quot;&gt;Paul Jarvis&lt;/a&gt; who asked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What if website analytics software didn’t take your users data to line their pockets for advertising?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul Jarvis&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I love the idea behind this.&lt;/strong&gt; But a problem I couldn’t deal with when switching to Netlify Analytics was, as a marketer, not being able to take away enough actionable insights to improve my content and website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would Fathom Analytics be any different? &lt;strong&gt;Because I don’t want to pay for vanity metrics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is Fathom Analytics more expensive than Netlify Analytics, but it will add to my website’s load time. If I’m going to have to pay more and deal with the load time, it will have to be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So far, I’ve been using and paying for Fathom for seven months now and here’s what I think of it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-review-of-fathom-analytics-can-it-replace-google-analytics-for-marketers&quot;&gt;My Review of Fathom Analytics: Can it Replace Google Analytics for Marketers?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fathom analytics has two types of customers: personal blogs (like this website), and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For personal blogs, the message is simple: Google is kind of a bully and you don’t want to give them data on all your users. And their analytics is complicated to use. So here’s an analytics platform that just gives you the data you need and keeps your user data private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For businesses (and marketers), it’s a different story. We actually know how to use Google Analytics and rely on that data to help drive our SEO, content, and website strategy. &lt;strong&gt;Do most marketers care about their user privacy? Aren’t marketers the ones who are always trying to identify their users?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a much tougher sell. In my opinion, the only companies who are going to ditch Google Analytics for privacy-focused analytics like Fathom are ones with founders who already value data privacy. If they don’t, no chance in hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t think Paul Jarvis or his co-founder &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackellis/&quot;&gt;Jack Ellis&lt;/a&gt; care. They don’t want those types of customers anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The way we run our business is ridiculously simple (not the norm in tech): we charge a fair amount of money for our product, use that money to keep the business running indefinitely, and remain small so that we don’t need a lot of money to be profitable and sustainable.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/about&quot;&gt;Fathom Analytics About Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you, as a marketer, don’t value data-privacy for your users, you’re probably not going to like Fathom Analytics. If you do, it’s then it’s the best privacy-focused analytics solution available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t decide whether you value data-privacy or tracking users more, then read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/ethical-marketing-dilemma.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/ethical-marketing-dilemma.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/ethical-marketing-dilemma.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The ethical marketer's dilemma.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The ethical marketer's dilemma.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-data-can-you-see-from-fathom-analytics&quot;&gt;What Data Can You See from Fathom Analytics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of what you get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;live, real-time data that doesn’t expire like Netlify Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;custom date range picker to filter data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;total unique visits (equivalent to sessions in Google Analytics, I think), page views, average time on site, and bounce rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list of your site’s URLs with the percent of total and number of unique visits and page views&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/support/goals&quot;&gt;unlimited goal creation&lt;/a&gt; by link click, page load, or form submission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list of referrers (actual page referring URL) with the percent of total and number of unique visits and page views (also shows the individual tweets sending you traffic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;device type, browser, and country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all sounds good, but when I dug in, I found some shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-want-from-fathom-analytics&quot;&gt;What I Want From Fathom Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a few things I’d like to see built in future releases. I’m not sure if it’s possible based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/news/anonymization&quot;&gt;their way of measuring traffic&lt;/a&gt;, but if it is, I would be so happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Fathom Analytics, you can’t:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;filter traffic by referrer to see what pages are being viewed by that referring traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or filter traffic by device type, browser, or country (no equivalent to Google Analytics’ dimensions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;filter metrics by looking at a one page URL at a time to see the referrers, device type, country, and goals for any given page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;see bounce rate, average time spent on site, or goal completions by page URL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or see the above by the first page URL of a unique visit (equivalent to Google Analytics’ Landing Page dimension)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these were added, this would give me about 90% of what I use Google Analytics for as a marketer and would be sufficient for a personal blog, but still don’t think it could suffice for a growth-focused company’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they can’t add these features without sacrificing user privacy, Fathom is the type of company to stand its ground and say &lt;em&gt;no.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/usefathom/fathom/issues/283&quot;&gt;Paul Jarvis already denied my request to work with AMP.&lt;/a&gt; I get it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-cool-things-you-can-do-with-fathom-analytics&quot;&gt;Other Cool Things You Can Do With Fathom Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can choose to make your analytics public if you want to have a transparent website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do have an affiliate program where you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;get 25% lifetime commissions and people you refer will get $10 off their first month&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They’re working on an API - I’m going to use it to display page view counts on articles for social proof&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can set up weekly and monthly reports and also set up client reports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can use it on unlimited domains and &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;their pricing is based on total page views&lt;/a&gt; not by domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can get a &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;7-day free trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-fathom-analytics-worth-it&quot;&gt;Is Fathom Analytics Worth It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fathom Analytics costs $14/month and right now, I do feel like I’m paying for vanity metrics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/fathom-analytics-pricing.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/fathom-analytics-pricing.png&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/fathom-analytics-pricing.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fathom Analytics starts at $14/month with unlimited domains.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Fathom Analytics starts at $14/month with unlimited domains.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I enjoy paying for it and using it on this site. It’s rare to come across a company that sticks to its mission which radiates in everything they do - their roadmap, design, content, and podcast. And they’re upfront about charging more than the industry standard so they can afford to stick to their principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I just love it when companies do that. And I’m a sucker for it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So should you make the switch? Well it comes down to whether you can get behind the mission of the company:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Our goal is huge but simple: to make as many websites as possible black holes for data to Google.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul Jarvis&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you vibe with that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/ref/W2AU06&quot;&gt;give it a shot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-april-2020&quot;&gt;Update April 2020&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the decision to switch back to Google Analytics. Because my site isn’t big enough and I don’t write as much as I’d like to, I don’t get enough value from premium analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I enjoy what Fathom is doing, I’m going to pause for now and come back soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the fun of it, I tested the difference in my site speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Requests&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Data over network&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Resources on page&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Load time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fathom&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;233 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;312 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;623 ms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;277 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;430 KB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;384 ms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, Google Analytics added more weight to the page, but was quicker to load. And since I don’t have any third party embeds or sending this data to any third party websites, I still don’t need a cookie consent notice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Fathom Analytics is a cookie-less analytics platform that values user privacy above all.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/fathom-analytics-review.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/fathom-analytics-review.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Will Teach You to Be Rich—Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2020-01-14T06:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T06:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-summary-notes-quotes">&lt;p&gt;It’s unfortunate I Will Teach You To Be Rich has an off-putting title because it’s a fantastic introduction to personal finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi’s goal is to make personal finance exciting and rewarding, a stark contrast from the dry, guilt-inducing material you typically would associate to the personal finance space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He won’t blame you for spending lots of money on the things you enjoy; the same things most people would tell you is irresponsible to spend so much money on. Instead he encourages you to keep doing it unapologetically.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catch? Cut spending harder in other areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Spend extravagantly on the things you love, and cut costs mercilessly on the things you don’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--sml gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-cover.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-cover.jpeg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich-cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Buy I Will Teach You to be Rich on Amazon&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Will-Teach-You-Rich-Second-ebook/dp/B07GNXPP4P/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;linkId=e52afa785fde06ed59be0365987f513d&amp;amp;language=en_US&quot;&gt;Buy I Will Teach You to be Rich on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His refreshing approach to money comes from the idea that money shouldn’t rule our lives, and instead be a tool to help us enjoy life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he’ll encourage financial responsibility. Yes, he’ll advocate &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;using a budget&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, he’ll try to persuade you to start saving for retirement immediately. &lt;strong&gt;But what makes Ramit different is he shows you how to get this important stuff done and out of the way by automating it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes room to think about the fun stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you want to be rich?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does being rich mean to you?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you love to spend money on?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-this-summary-of-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich&quot;&gt;In This Summary of I Will Teach You to Be Rich&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to make credit cards work for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to set up the right bank accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to set up the right retirement accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;how to manage spending and enjoy it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to automate it all to be hands off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to invest intelligently with little work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to briefly cover his main recommendations from each topic, but because of his innovative approach to spending and budgeting and how practical it is, I’m going to spend a bit more time covering them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everybody teaches you how to save. Nobody talks about how to spend.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-make-credit-cards-work-for-you&quot;&gt;How to Make Credit Cards Work for You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section covers a lot about what a credit score is, how it’s calculated, and how credit cards work - all great for beginners. These are the notes I took for myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;always use a credit card over a debit card - builds credit, protects your bank account, accrue rewards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;always pay off credit cards in full each month - treat it like a debit card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up automatic payments so you never miss a payment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;keep old credit cards active by charging a small monthly cost to keep credit history&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;switch credit cards to a no annual fee card when it’s no longer your primary card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;request credit limit increases to improve your credit utilization rate (a factor of your credit score)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be aware of and use your rewards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can negotiate lower APRs and get late fees waived if you call and ask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The section ends with strategies to pay off credit card debt. It can be summarized by paying off debt with the highest intrest rate, but it’s more nuanced than that. If you do have credit card debt, this section is worth reading in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-set-up-the-right-bank-accounts&quot;&gt;How to Set Up The Right Bank Accounts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always surprised when I learn friends use traditional big banks for their accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They typically have the worse benefits, have minimum balance requirements for checking accounts, and a poor online banking experience. Ramit does a good job exposing these pitfalls by explaining how banks make money and the tactics they use to lure you in and make it hard to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a couple, but important takeaways on banks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;switch to an online bank (I recommend Capital One)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open a high-yield savings accounts (Capital One has them for free)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-set-up-the-right-retirement-accounts&quot;&gt;How to Set Up The Right Retirement Accounts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most important section so far, Ramit makes it simple to understand all the different types of retirement accounts and persuasively lays out why it’s so important to start saving for retirement now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He created five systematic steps for investing he calls “The Ladder of Personal Finance.”&lt;/strong&gt; When you finish the first step, or if it’s not an option, you proceed to the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;contribute 100% of what your employer matches in a company 401k&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pay off credit card or other debt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open a Roth IRA and contribute up to the annual maximum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;max out your 401k beyond or regardless of a company match&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;put the rest in a non retirement brokerage account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this section goes deep into each step of the ladder, explaining everything very clearly. I was finally able to understand the tax advantages of each different kind of retirement account and also why it was valuable to start now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-manage-spending-and-enjoy-it&quot;&gt;How to Manage Spending and Enjoy It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can learn to how to better manage your money he says you need to understand where you’re spending it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, he doesn’t recommend creating a budget where you track your finances down to the penny, but instead do what he calls a “Conscious Spending Plan,” which still sounds an awful lot like a budget, just a little more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious Spending is Ramit’s method of allowing yourself to spend money on the things that bring you joy, even if they seem frivolous to other people, or even frivolous to you. In exchange, you cut the spending elsewhere. This is how Ramit defines frugality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Frugality isn’t about cutting your spending on everything. That approach wouldn’t last two days. Frugality, quite simply, is about choosing the things you love enough to spend extravagantly on - and then cutting costs mercilessly on the things you don’t love.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-make-a-conscious-spending-plan&quot;&gt;How to make a conscious spending plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divide up where your take home pay goes into four major buckets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Money Buckets&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Percent of take home pay to allocate&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;I. Fixed Costs - Rent, utilities, debt, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50-60%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;II. Investments - 401(k), Rotha IRA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;III. Savings - Vacations, gifts, house down payment, unexpected expenses&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5-10%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IV. Guilt-free spending money - Dining out, drinking, movies, clothes, shoes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20-35%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed costs are expenses you have to pay every month no matter what. Once you total them up, subtract that amount from your take-home pay.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figure out how much you want to save for retirement in a 401k and or IRA and then deduct that amount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about what you want to save for in the short and long term. Calculate how much you need to save per month to reach that goal and then deduct that amount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After allocating money for fixed costs, retirement and investments, and savings, the rest is for guilt-free spending.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;I made a budget template on Google Sheets&lt;/a&gt; based on Ramit’s Conscious Spending Plan that can you help do all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/google-sheets-budget-template&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;My Google Sheets Budget Template (for Millennials)&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the spreadsheet budget I made to make budgeting fun.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/google-sheets-budget-template-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/google-sheets-budget-template.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;google sheets budget template&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tips-to-optimize-your-conscious-spending-plan&quot;&gt;Tips to optimize your Conscious Spending Plan:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;always try to cut fixed costs and guilt-free spending before cutting how much you allocate to investing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;focus on big wins to cut spending, not small ones like buying generic brands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you’re more likely to stick to a new budget by making a gradual change than a dramatic one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;actually write out tangible savings goals to increase motivation to achieve them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-envelope-system-to-target-big-wins&quot;&gt;Use the “envelope system” to target big wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The envelope system is essentially a second bucket system for your guilt-free spending. You allocate a certain amount of your guilt-free spending to certain categories (envelopes) and once you spend all the money in that envelope, that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s much easier to figure out how much money you should put into each envelope by looking at your last three months of spending in each category, averaging them out, and then setting an achievable goal for each one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good objective to try and meet your spending goal for each category, but you can dip into other envelopes if you need to. The most important thing is keeping your total spending below what you have for guilt-free spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;activity-based-envelopes&quot;&gt;Activity based envelopes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One trick Ramit mentions that I’ve used in the past is instead of using the general categories that credit card companies and banks typically use, create categories more personal to you and &lt;em&gt;around events&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I have used these categories in the past:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;eating out alone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coffee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alcohol for home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;going out with friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this requires a manual categorization of each expense, it will highglight the driving activities behind your spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to keep track of spending is to always use a credit card (as long as your responsible) so you can just pull up your account to enter expenses into your budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The best part about setting up a strategic budget is that it guides your decisions, letting you say no much more easily - ‘Sorry, it’s not in my plan this month.’ - and freeing you up to enjoy what you do spend on. This is guilt-free spending at its best.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-automate-it-all-to-be-hands-off&quot;&gt;How to Automate It All to be Hands Off&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re contributing to a 401k, that’s probably already automated by your employer before even receiving your paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then your paycheck gets deposited into your checking account and from there you set up a monthly automatic transfer to your other retirement and savings accounts. &lt;strong&gt;By transferring the money automatically right after you get paid, you’re paying yourself first, not spending first and saving what’s left over.&lt;/strong&gt; That’s why the money left over to spend is guilt-free spending money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what the flow looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;picture&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/always-pay-yourself-first-ramit-sethi-teach-you-to-be-rich.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;source srcset=&quot;assets/images/always-pay-yourself-first-ramit-sethi-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;image &quot; src=&quot;assets/images/always-pay-yourself-first-ramit-sethi-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;How to automate your finances. Automatically transfer to savings first. Your percentage allocation may differ.&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;How to automate your finances. Automatically transfer to savings first. Your percentage allocation may differ.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“By setting up an automatic payment plan you actually make it difficult to stop the contributions to your retirement account! Not because you can’t - you can adjust your system any time - but because you’re lazy and you won’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More automation tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up all bills to be paid by credit card automatically&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if a bill (like rent) can’t be paid by card, set up auto bill pay to have your bank automtically send a check on your behalf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up your credit card bill to be paid automatically from your checking account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set a reminder in the middle of the month to check how you much you’ve spent compared to what you’ve allocated for guilt-free spending&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-invest-intelligently-with-little-work&quot;&gt;How to Invest Intelligently with Little Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section of &lt;em&gt;I Will Teach You to be Rich&lt;/em&gt;, Ramit walks us through how to invest the money in your 401ks and IRAs. It’s a good introduction to the foundational topics of investing that can be summed up in a few points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be less risk averse when you’re younger, more risk averse when older&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hardly anyone beats the market, even full-time investors so it’s not worth trying to pick the right stocks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t invest in any funds with high fees, like mutual funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;it’s better long term to invest in low-fee index funds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some diversification is good, just remember to rebalance your ratios annually&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;invest in lifecycle funds to be completely hands off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramit goes into more details on each one of these here and explains why he gives the advice he does. It’s solid financial advice and worth reading more into if you’re fresh to personal finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-personal-finance-tips&quot;&gt;Final Personal Finance Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;try and invest as much as you can, as early as you can&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;if your income increases, look to increase how much you allocate to savings first&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ignore the noise of the financial industry, it can cause you to get emotional and make bad decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t worry about tricks to avoid taxes or seeing a financial advisor until your investments total $100k+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;create an emergency fund to protect against job loss or unexpected, expensive bills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Unlike other people, who worry about money (because they never learned how it works), you get to focus on the things you love.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">It’s unfortunate I Will Teach You To Be Rich has an off-putting title because it’s a fantastic introduction to personal finance.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ramit-sethi-i-will-teach-you-to-be-rich.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Free Will Doesn’t Exist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/free-will-doesnt-exist" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Will Doesn’t Exist" /><published>2020-01-06T06:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-06T06:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/free-will-doesnt-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/free-will-doesnt-exist">&lt;p&gt;It seems we have control of our actions. It seems we make our own choices. It seems we choose our beliefs. It seems we can think about what we want, when we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems everything we do is of our own free will and this all seems quite obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there does exist the opposite belief that we don’t have free will to choose all those things ourselves and rather our thoughts, beliefs, choices, and actions are determined only by a result of previous causes that could not have resulted in any other outcome. &lt;strong&gt;This philosophical belief is called determinism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about determinism from Sam Harris and my first reaction was &lt;em&gt;no way that’s even close to being right, of course we have free will&lt;/em&gt;. But after listening to his arguments and doing my own research on determinism, I can’t help but be convinced it’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This realization had such a profound effect on me it has fundamentally changed the way I think about myself, other people, and the world around me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is an examination into determinism versus free will, thought exercises to illustrate the lack of free will in our thoughts, beliefs, choices, and actions, and finally the implications of it in our daily lives and society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;free-will-vs-determinism&quot;&gt;Free Will vs Determinism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Determinism#History&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Determinism&lt;/a&gt; is the philosophical belief that any thought you have, belief you uphold, choice you make, and action you take is determined by a chain of previous causes that could not be otherwise because of those causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_will&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Free will&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, is the belief we have the unimpeded ability to control our thoughts, choose our beliefs, make choices, and take actions between different possible options. &lt;strong&gt;The key question that differentiates determinism and free will is &lt;em&gt;are you capable to have done otherwise?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/w8Q6CWv7IXo?t=8106&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;great thought exercise on the Joe Rogan Experience&lt;/a&gt; to illustrate the difference. It goes like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of a city - any city in the world. &lt;em&gt;Now say it out loud.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have chosen any of the hundreds of cities you know the name of, &lt;em&gt;but you chose that one.&lt;/em&gt; Some other cities might have run through your head right before you answered, but there were hundreds that didn’t even occur to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the hundreds of possible options, this seems like an example of one of the freest choices you can make. But if we go back in time right to the moment where I first asked you to say the city out loud, &lt;em&gt;could you have chosen a different city?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you examine your thought process leading to your city of choice, you’ll find reasons that caused you to choose that city - fond memories, something you saw today, or simply how you were feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a universe with free will, you’d be capable of using those inputs to choose one city and you could have easily chosen a different city. But in a deterministic universe, we could go back 1,000 times right to the start of this thought exercise and you’d go through that same exact thought process and you’d choose that same city every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s the difference between free will and determinism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arguments-for-determinism&quot;&gt;Arguments for Determinism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are thought exercises to reveal how much of who we are, our thoughts, beliefs, choices, and actions are the product of causes rather than choices from our own free will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-didnt-choose-our-genetics-or-upbringing&quot;&gt;We didn’t choose our genetics or upbringing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, we’re alive. And it wasn’t by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t get to choose the country or city we were born and raised in. We didn’t choose the culture. We didn’t choose the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t get to choose our genetic code, how tall we’d become, how attractive or unattractive we are, the sound of our voice, the color of our skin, the language we speak, our natural talents, our gender or sex, or the diseases we’re susceptible to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t get to choose our parents, how much or how little money they had to raise us with, their relationship between each other, the religion, values, and politics they ingrained in us, or how much or how little they pushed us in sports, music, or academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How our parents raised us (or the people who did), heavily influence our identity, character, values, beliefs, and future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you’re a parent, you already know this is true or you wouldn’t have read all those books or watched all those videos on how to become a great parent. You wouldn’t have tried as hard as you did to create the best possible life for your children if you knew it wouldn’t make a difference.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to think about your upbringing. How much has it made you who you are today? How much of that was your choice? How much of that was determined and out of your control?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-choose-our-own-thoughts&quot;&gt;We don’t choose our own thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the part of us that feels closest to our sense of free will, our thoughts seem to be the element we have complete control of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we are in complete control of our thoughts, &lt;strong&gt;why do we struggle with staying focused and distractions? It’s not that we choose to be distracted. It happens “against our will” because we don’t have the control to choose what we think about.&lt;/strong&gt; If you’ve ever practiced meditation, you already know how frequently random thoughts surface themselves, completely outside of our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only do we not choose what and when we think about things, we don’t choose our opinion of things either. &lt;strong&gt;If we did have free will and complete control of choosing our opinions, marketing and advertising wouldn’t be a multi billion dollar industry fighting for our attention,&lt;/strong&gt; we wouldn’t be the average of the five people we surround ourselves with, &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;social media wouldn’t affect our mental health&lt;/a&gt;, and good and bad influences wouldn’t make a difference to our character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few of the many things that influence every thought and opinion we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we don’t choose the things we think about, when we think about them, and our opinions of them, how can we possibly ever have a thought or opinion formed purely from our choice alone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-choose-our-own-beliefs&quot;&gt;We don’t choose our own beliefs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to think of a strong belief you have, such as a religious belief or political position. What is your best reason for believing your belief or position is right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever your best reason was, it wasn’t &lt;em&gt;because I chose to believe it,&lt;/em&gt; was it? &lt;strong&gt;That’s because we don’t choose our beliefs. We’re convinced of them. It’s only until we’re convinced of a belief that we can uphold that belief with conviction.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate this is true, see if you’re capable of choosing to believe the opposite view of the belief or position you were just thinking of. Could you do it? If you believe the Earth is a sphere, can you choose to believe right now, with complete conviction, that it’s flat? The reason why you can’t is because you’ve already been presented with good reasons why it’s a sphere and good reasons why it’s not flat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need good reasons to believe something, and making a choice to believe something is never a good enough reason for a strong belief to form.&lt;/strong&gt; So what is a good enough reason?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To our detriment, a good enough reason is anything that sounds more convincing to us than what we knew before and it’s here wherein lies the problem. We can be convinced to uphold false beliefs for objectively bad reasons. These bad, but convincing, reasons are often &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourlogicalfallacyis.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;logical fallacies&lt;/a&gt; strengthened through &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourbias.is/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt;. And it’s why some people do believe the Earth is flat with complete conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And consider for a moment why we even have the beliefs we do in the first place. Beliefs are pushed onto us from every angle since birth from our parents, teachers and textbooks, church and church leaders, community and culture, the news media, and on and on. &lt;strong&gt;Then we have social media that exacerbates the problem by isolating us into echo chambers that feed into our confirmation bias.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, because we don’t choose which beliefs are up for consideration in the first place and we can’t choose which to uphold, it’s clear our beliefs are determined, not chosen by our own free will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-make-our-own-choices&quot;&gt;We don’t make our own choices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris’s ‘pick a city’ thought exercise is a demonstration of how we use previous causes to make a choice. Although this is an example of one of the freest choices you can make, it is an inconsequential choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely life’s more consequential choices where we spend weeks reflecting and deliberating over the pros and cons of that choice has to be an example of using free will to make a choice, right? Let’s explore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you’re deciding which college to go to for your bachelor’s degree. The pros and cons you might be deliberating over are the schools’ prestiges, quality of major programs, how much fun you’ll have, and where your parents want you to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your genetics, upbringing, thoughts, opinions, and beliefs will determine your final assessment for each of these considerations. &lt;strong&gt;These are the tools we use to make decisions and if our decision making tools are determined, then the choices we end up making from them are determined.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, neither the time it takes to make a choice or the level of consequence in a choice’s outcome changes the fact that our choices are determined. We’re still capable of making choices in a deterministic universe, but we are never capable of choosing something else than what we do end up choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Virtue is a Better Goal Than Legacy&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;The Stoics saw virtue as life&amp;#39;s highest objective. I&amp;#39;m starting to see why.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/moral-virtue-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/moral-virtue-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/moral-virtue-250.jpg 250w,
                                /assets/images/moral-virtue-572.jpg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/moral-virtue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Virtue is its own reward&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-dont-control-our-own-actions&quot;&gt;We don’t control our own actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions can occur either unconsciously or consciously. Unconscious actions like scratching an itch, sighing, or bouncing your leg up and down while sitting are actions that occur, without a doubt, from a cause, not by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conscious actions require a choice to act. And if choices are determined, then actions are determined.&lt;/strong&gt; We can even make a choice to act and still fail to complete that act because causes are more powerful than our choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we don’t have complete control of our actions or body. If we did, we wouldn’t choose to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;break a bad habit&lt;/a&gt; and fail. We wouldn’t choose to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;start a good habit&lt;/a&gt; and fail. We wouldn’t need to read a &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;book on habits&lt;/a&gt; at all. If we had free will and control of our actions, we could simply choose to do something and do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we don’t have control of our actions because we don’t have control of our choices. We don’t have control of our choices because we don’t have control of our beliefs. We don’t have control of our beliefs because we don’t have control of our thoughts, opinions, genetics, or how we were raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/atomic-habits-summary-review-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/atomic-habits-summary-review-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic-habits-summary-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-the-lack-of-free-will-matter&quot;&gt;Does the Lack of Free Will Matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining whether we have free will or not matters because if we do have free will, that means we should have full, moral responsibility for our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t have free will, how much moral responsibility should we bear for actions we could not have done otherwise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Admitting that free will is an illusion actually does have some important consequences. They’re not the kind of consequences that people worry about. It’s not that you have no basis to be a better person or to change your life or to make efforts to improve yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“That all remains intact, but it does change our ethical views of good and evil in some important ways.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sam Harris, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/w8Q6CWv7IXo?t=8319&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joe Rogan Experience #543 2:18:39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let’s look at what the lack of free will means for our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-be-too-hard-on-yourself&quot;&gt;Don’t be too hard on yourself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be disappointed with the way you look, how much money you make, or how many followers you have. You might &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;compare yourself to others&lt;/a&gt; and be disappointed with how ordinary or inadequate you are compared to them. I’ve been there and I think we’ve all been there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By understanding that we don’t have control over the causes that determine our looks, income, popularity, or status, it becomes possible to accept who we are and be grateful for what we have.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Stop Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why these comparisons don&amp;#39;t make sense and how it improved my mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others.png&quot; alt=&quot;stop comparing yourself to others&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most empowering tenets of Stoicism and why I’ve fully embraced its philosophy into my life is about identifying and separating the things that are up to us from what’s not. If something is not up to us and is out of our control, then we shouldn’t get angry, scared, or grieve about it because there’s nothing we could have done to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When a slave runs away from his master, we call him a fugitive slave. But the law of nature is a master too, and to break it is to become a fugitive.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“To feel grief, anger, or fear is to try to escape from something decreed by the ruler of all things, now or in the past or in the future. And that ruler is law [fate], which governs what happens to each of us. To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive — a fugitive from justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 10.25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infusing determinism and Stoicism into my perspective has shown me that getting angry, sad, and frustrated with who and where I am today would be denying that my previous causes could not have been anything else than what they were.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, these negative emotions are unnecessary. All they do is bring extra harm for no rational reason. Identifying the things that are outside of my control has &lt;a href=&quot;/virtue-is-its-own-reward&quot;&gt;ultimately brought tranquility into my life.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-good-to-other-people&quot;&gt;Be good to other people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just as you recognize the things you can’t control about yourself, it’s just as powerful to recognize other people are the way they are and do the things they do because of causes outside of their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So think about that the next time your significant other, a family member, friend, or coworker does something you find weird or wrong. It doesn’t seem weird or wrong to them because of their previous causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel affection for people even when they make mistakes is uniquely human. You can do it, if you simply recognize: that they’re human too, that they act out of ignorance, against their will, and that you’ll both be dead before long. And, above all, that they haven’t really hurt you. They haven’t diminished your ability to choose [how to react].”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 7.22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you have objectively good reasons for thinking whatever they’re doing is weird or wrong, they may just not know better and that’s okay. If you’re able to, try and steer them in the right direction. &lt;strong&gt;The worst thing you can do for your relationship and your own well-being, is pass blame.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If it’s in your control, why do you do it? If it’s in someone else’s, then who are you blaming? Atoms? The gods? Stupid either way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Blame no one. Set people straight, if you can. If not, just repair the damage. And suppose you can’t do that either. Then where does blaming people get you?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 8.17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeing the universe, yourself, and other people through a lens of determinism and Stoicism adds a priceless attribute to your character: empathy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius—Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-250.png 250w,
                                /assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2-572.png 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/png&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations-marcus-aurelius-summary2.png&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-more-aware-of-what-influences-you&quot;&gt;Be more aware of what influences you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally everything and everyone around us is influencing our thoughts, beliefs, and behavior in every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pay attention to your thoughts and emotions throughout the day. Try to understand what made you think and feel that way.&lt;/em&gt; By being able to identify the cause, we can cut out the negative influences and increase the positive ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius often draws a comparison between being unaware of your influences to “being jerked like a puppet by our own impulses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s time you realized that you have something in you more powerful and miraculous than the things that affect you and make you dance like a puppet.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“What’s in my thoughts at this moment? Fear? Jealousy? Desire? Feelings like that?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius,  &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations 12.19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “power” he’s referring to is our ability to be aware of these influences and how we choose to react to them. This is a skill that takes practice. Meditation is the most popular method to get better at it, but I’ve found &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;daily journaling&lt;/a&gt; to work better for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly realized social media and video games were some of my biggest negative influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the expense of losing touch with some friends, I deleted Snapchat and Instagram because it made me &lt;a href=&quot;/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others&quot;&gt;care too much about what other people think of me&lt;/a&gt;, envy the lives other people live and the things they have, and lose gratitude for who I am and what I have in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sold my Playstation because all I wanted to do was game when I got off work. I realized it was an unproductive use of time and losing online games would leave me annoyed and frustrated (FIFA players understand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;23 Stoic Journal Prompts for Self-Development&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Inspired by the journal method of Marcus Aurelius, these journal prompts will help you improve your character, acquire tranquility, and be more of a Stoic.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;picture&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/webp/stoic-journal-topics-250.webp 250w,
                                /assets/images/webp/stoic-journal-topics-572.webp 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;source sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 274px, 198px&quot; srcset=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics-250.jpeg 250w,
                                /assets/images/stoic-journal-topics-572.jpeg 572w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;stoic journal topics&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;/picture&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-on-politics-and-society&quot;&gt;Impact on politics and society&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This perspective of empathy through determinism and Stoicism can be extended to people who live on the opposite side of the globe, who we don’t understand, and who society deems bad. Through practicing this perspective, it’s possible to develop empathy for these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, people in jail for committing crimes have previous causes that led them to do so, whether those crimes are theft, drug related, or assault. While determinism doesn’t mean our society must rid all fault and responsibility from those who commit crimes, but maybe we should emphasize an approach of rehabilitation more than punishment in our criminal justice system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe we should be more empathetic to people who were born in a third world country through no choice of their own. Maybe we should be more empathetic to people who have different religious beliefs and political positions due to causes outside of their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although some critics say there isn’t much of a practical difference between free will and the illusion of it, there are clear implications to the understanding of ourselves, other people, and the world around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge yourself to be aware of the influences on your thoughts, beliefs, and behavior. Challenge yourself to accept and be grateful for who you are, what you have, and what you’ve accomplished. Challenge yourself to feel affection for other people even when they make mistakes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><category term="[&quot;all&quot;]" /><summary type="html">It seems we have control of our actions. It seems we make our own choices. It seems we choose our beliefs. It seems we can think about what we want, when we want.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/sam-harris-free-will.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/sam-harris-free-will.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>