<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-31T12:29:42-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">regpaq</title><subtitle>B2B Marketer. Avid reader &amp; writer.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;regpaq&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Effective Executive — Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Effective Executive — Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2019-08-12T07:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-12T07:30:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/effective-executive-summary-quotes-peter-drucker">&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Drucker&quot;&gt;Peter Drucker&lt;/a&gt;, there are eight practices that make effective executives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “what needs to be done?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “what is right for the company?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop action plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take responsibility for decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take responsibility for communicating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on opportunities rather than problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run productive meetings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think and say “we” rather than “I”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two give you the knowledge you need. The next four convert that knowledge into effective action. The last two gets your team to feel responsible and inspired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Effective Executive, Drucker explains what an effective executive is and how to become one. He believed being an effective executive could be learned and this book served as a handbook to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Executives are doers; they execute. Knowledge is useless to executives until it has been translated into deeds. But before springing into action, the executive needs to plan his course. He needs to think about desired results, probable restraints, future revisions, check-in points, and implications for how he’ll spend his time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-an-executive-effective&quot;&gt;What Makes an Executive Effective?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking “what do I want to do?” ask “what has to be done?” This is crucial for managerial success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The answer to this question “…almost always contains more than one urgent task. But effective executives do not splinter themselves. They concentrate on one task if at all possible. […] I have never encountered an executive who remains effective while tackling more than two tasks at a time. Hence, after asking what needs to be done, the effective executive sets priorities and sticks to them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the top initiatives prioritized, you need to choose which you are especially good at undertaking and then delegate the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives try to focus on jobs they’ll do especially well. They know that enterprises perform if top management performs—and don’t if it doesn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-is-the-beginning-of-your-action-plan&quot;&gt;This is the beginning of your action plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your action plan is a prioritized list of initiatives and tasks for you and your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The action plan is a statement of intentions rather than a commitment. It must not become a straitjacket. It should be revised often, because every success creates new opportunities. So does every failure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Develop the plan in a tool that makes it easy to check-in, provide updates, and move items around as it progresses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Napoleon allegedly said that no successful battle ever followed its plan. Yet Napoleon also planned every one of his battles, far more meticulously than any earlier general had done. Without an action plan, the executive becomes a prisoner of events. And without check-ins to reexamine the plan as events unfold, the executive has no way of knowing which events really matter and which are only noise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And an action plan is useless unless it’s communicated and understood by your teams.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decision has not really been made until people know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is accountable for delivering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the deadline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who and which teams are affected by the decision and therefore have to understand and approve it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who else should be informed of the decision, even if not directly affected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action plan shouldn’t be given as an order from the top. Get and incorporate feedback. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives make sure that both their action plans and their information needs are understood. Specifically, this means that they share their plans with and ask for comments from all their colleagues—superiors, subordinates, and peers. At the same time, they let each person know what information they’ll need to get the job done. The information flow from subordinate to boss is usually what gets the most attention. But executives need to pay equal attention to peers’ and superiors’ information needs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Although problems stick out like a nail begging to be hammered, don’t make fixing a problem a top priority.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Good executives focus on opportunities rather than problems. Problems have to be taken care of, of course; they must not be swept under the rug. But problem solving, however necessary, does not produce results. It prevents damage. Exploiting opportunities produces results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when delegating tasks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives put their best people on opportunities rather than on problems.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When Drucker recalls how an effective executive would run a meeting, he thinks back on an old colleague of his.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“At the beginning of a formal meeting, Sloan announced the meeting’s purpose. He then listened. He never took notes and he rarely spoke except to clarify a confusing point. At the end he summed up, thanked the participants, and left. Then he immediately wrote a short memo addressed to one attendee of the meeting. In that note, he summarized the discussion and its conclusions and spelled out any work assignment decided upon in the meeting (including a decision to hold another meeting on the subject or to study an issue). He specified the deadline and the executive who was to be accountable for the assignment. He sent a copy of the memo to everyone who’d been present at the meeting. It was through these memos—each a small masterpiece—that Sloan made himself into an outstandingly effective executive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;effectiveness-can-be-learned&quot;&gt;Effectiveness Can Be Learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one thing to come up with a good idea. It’s another thing all together to execute that idea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Brilliant men are often strikingly ineffectual; they fail to realize that the brilliant insight is not by itself achievement. […] Intelligence, imagination, and knowledge are essential resources, but only effectiveness converts them into results. By themselves, they only set limits to what can be attained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effective-executive-are-masters-of-their-time&quot;&gt;Effective Executive Are Masters of Their Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the most out of your time and your team’s time is an essential first step to becoming effecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[Effective executives] start with their time. And they do not start out with planning. They start by finding out where their time actually goes. Then they attempt to manage their time and to cut back unproductive demands on their time. Finally they consolidate their “discretionary” time into the largest possible continuing units.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To master your time, follow this three step process:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record your time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;manage your time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consolidate your time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The first step toward executive effectiveness is therefore to record actual time-use.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-on-recording-time&quot;&gt;Tips on Recording Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measure it in real-time, not later from memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recording time is a habit that can improve with constant effort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figure out how to make time management systematic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve been recording your time, you can analyze it and see what the time wasters are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To find these time-wastes, one asks of all activities in the time records: ‘What would happen if this were not done at all?’ And if the answer is, ‘Nothing would happen,’ then obviously the conclusion is to stop doing it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then determine which of the activities left can be delegated to some else. Now you can see how much time you have for important tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The executive who records and analyzes his time and then attempts to manage it can determine how much he has for his important tasks. How much time is there that is “discretionary,” that is, available for the big tasks that will really make a contribution? It is not going to be a great deal, no matter how ruthlessly the executive prunes time-wasters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker discovered that it’s much more effective to block open time in as large of chunks as possible to get into deep work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The effective executive therefore knows that he has to consolidate his [open] time. He knows that he needs large chunks of time and that small driblets are no time at all. Even one quarter of the working day, if consolidated in large time units, is usually enough to get the important things done. But even three quarters of the working day are useless if they are only available as fifteen minutes here or half an hour there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Time is the scarcest resource, and unless it is managed, nothing else can be managed. The analysis of one’s time, moreover, is the one easily accessible and yet systematic way to analyze one’s work and to think through what really matters in it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;executives-are-also-responsible-for-their-teams-time&quot;&gt;Executives are Also Responsible for Their Team’s Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common time waste is when the executive wastes his individual team members’ time. To overcome this, Drucker advises executives to directly as their team if and how he/she wastes their time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives have learned to ask systematically and without coyness: “What do I do that wastes your time without contributing to your effectiveness?” To ask this question, and to ask it without being afraid of the truth, is a mark of the effective executive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-on-managing-meetings&quot;&gt;Tips on Managing Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like to be “in the know” and aware of what’s going on. Effective executives should let the whole team know when a meeting will take place and on what topic. Make it optional for people to join so they don’t feel left out. In any case, summarize the meeting notes, send to the team, and allow for questions and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Meetings are by definition a concession to deficient organization for one either meets or one works. One cannot do both at the same time. In an ideally designed structure (which in a changing world is of course only a dream) there would be no meetings. Everybody would know what he needs to know to do his job. Everyone would have the resources available to him to do his job. We meet because people holding different jobs have to cooperate to get a specific task done. We meet because the knowledge and experience needed in a specific situation are not available in one head, but have to be pieced together out of the experience and knowledge of several people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to run meetings effectively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The effective man always states at the outset of a meeting the specific purpose and contribution it is to achieve. He makes sure that the meeting addresses itself to this purpose. He does not allow a meeting called to inform to degenerate into a “bull session” in which everyone has bright ideas. But a meeting called by him to stimulate thinking and ideas also does not become simply a presentation on the part of one of the members, but is run to challenge and stimulate everybody in the room. He always, at the end of his meetings, goes back to the opening statement and relates the final conclusions to the original intent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-effective-executive-focuses-on-contribution&quot;&gt;The Effective Executive Focuses on Contribution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective executive are always focusing on contribution that makes a positive impact on the company’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The man who focuses on efforts and who stresses his downward authority is a subordinate no matter how exalted his title and rank. But the man who focuses on contribution and who takes responsibility for results, no matter how junior, is in the most literal sense of the phrase, “top management.” He holds himself accountable for the performance of the whole.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to achieve that, you can’t only look inward to what you want to do and what you think you can do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The focus on contribution turns the executive’s attention away from his own specialty, his own narrow skills, his own department, and toward the performance of the whole. It turns his attention to the outside, the only place where there are results. He is likely to have to think through what relationships his skills, his specialty, his function, or his department have to the entire organization and its purpose. He therefore will also come to think in terms of the customer, the client, or the patient, who is the ultimate reason for whatever the organization produces, whether it be economic goods, governmental policies, or health services. As a result, what he does and how he does it will be materially different.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-areas-of-contribution&quot;&gt;Three Areas of Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value building and reaffirmation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If deprived of performance in any one of these areas, it will decay and die. All three therefore have to be built into the contribution of every executive. But their relative importance varies greatly with the personality and the position of the executive as well as with the needs of the organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you focus on contribution, it will help you fulfill the four basic requirements of effective human relations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;communications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;teamwork&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;development of others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helping others be successful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Effective executives find themselves asking other people in the organization, their superiors, their subordinates, but above all, their colleagues in other areas: ‘What contribution from me do you require to make your contribution to the organization? When do you need this, how do you need it, and in what form?’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of all, the biggest benefit of focusing on contribution is it counteracts chaos and highlights what’s important to spend time on versus what’s noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The focus on contribution imposes an organizing principle. It imposes relevance on events. Focusing on contribution turns one of the inherent weaknesses of the executive’s situation—his dependence on other people, his being within the organization—into a source of strength. It creates a team. Finally, focusing on contribution fights the temptation to stay within the organization. It leads the executive—especially the top-level man—to lift his eyes from the inside of efforts, work, and relationships, to the outside; that is, to the results of the organization. It makes him try hard to have direct contact with the outside—whether markets and customers, patients in a community, or the various “publics” which are the outside of a government agency. To focus on contribution is to focus on effectiveness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-strengths-productive&quot;&gt;Making Strengths Productive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker makes the argument that it’s best to build on strengths to achieve results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The effective executive fills positions and promotes on the basis of what a man can do. He does not make staffing decisions to minimize weaknesses but to maximize strength.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;staffing-for-strength&quot;&gt;Staffing for Strength&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two rules to staff for strengths:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for strength in one major area. Ask, ‘what can this person do uncommonly well?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make each job demanding with a deep scope so their strengths can produce significant results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…every people-decision is a gamble. By basing it on what a man can do, it becomes at least a rational gamble.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spotting-team-members-not-using-their-strengths&quot;&gt;Spotting Team Members Not Using Their Strengths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your responsibility to spot and guide those on your team who aren’t making their strength’s productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The ones who are enthusiastic and who, in turn, have results to show for their work, are the ones whose abilities are being challenged and used. Those that are deeply frustrated all say, in one way or another: ‘My abilities are not being put to use.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your job to know when this is happening, correct it, and be ahead of it so it’s unlikely to occur again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The assertion that “somebody else will not let me do anything” should always be suspected as a cover-up for inertia. But even where the situation does set limitations—and everyone lives and works within rather stringent limitations—there are usually important, meaningful, pertinent things that can be done. The effective executive looks for them. If he starts out with the question: “What can I do?” he is almost certain to find that he can actually do much more than he has time and resources for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-things-first&quot;&gt;First Things First&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effectiveness is reached by focusing on one thing at time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Concentration is necessary precisely because the executive faces so many tasks clamoring to be done. For doing one thing at a time means doing it fast. The more one can concentrate time, effort, and resources, the greater the number and diversity of tasks one can actually perform.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you don’t focus on one thing at a time, you end up working harder and at the same time get nothing done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The people who get nothing done often work a great deal harder. In the first place, they underestimate the time for any one task. They always expect that everything will go right. Yet, as every executive knows, nothing ever goes right. The unexpected always happens—the unexpected is indeed the only thing one can confidently expect. And almost never is it a pleasant surprise. Effective executives therefore allow a fair margin of time beyond what is actually needed. In the second place, the typical (that is, the more or less ineffectual) executive tries to hurry—and that only puts him further behind. Effective executives do not race. They set an easy pace but keep going steadily. Finally, the typical executive tries to do several things at once. Therefore, he never has the minimum time quantum for any of the tasks in his program. If any one of them runs into trouble, his entire program collapses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always stay updated to the current programs, activities, and tasks. If something isn’t worth doing anymore, it’s better to stop it sooner than later and refocus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Systematic sloughing off of the old is the one and only way to force the new. There is no lack of ideas in any organization I know. “Creativity” is not our problem. But few organizations ever get going on their own good ideas. Everybody is much too busy on the tasks of yesterday. Putting all programs and activities regularly on trial for their lives and getting rid of those that cannot prove their productivity work wonders in stimulating creativity even in the most hidebound bureaucracy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Concentration—that is, the courage to impose on time and events his own decision as to what really matters and comes first—is the executive’s only hope of becoming the master of time and events instead of their whipping boy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-elements-of-decision-making&quot;&gt;The Elements of Decision-Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker has a lot to say on decision making and how to do it effecively. I found these two sections way too long and verbose for my attention span. Although, I really like the below quote about how data-driven decisions should be seen as having a degree of risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Finding the appropriate measurement is thus not a mathematical exercise. It is a risk-taking judgment. Whenever one has to judge, one must have alternatives among which one can choose. A judgment in which one can only say “yes” or “no” is no judgment at all. Only if there are alternatives can one hope to get insight into what is truly at stake. Effective executives therefore insist on alternatives of measurement—so that they can choose the one appropriate one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-topics-on-effectiveness-that-stood-out-to-me&quot;&gt;Other Topics on Effectiveness that Stood Out to Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;generalist-vs-specialist&quot;&gt;Generalist vs specialist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The only meaningful definition of a “generalist” is a specialist who can relate his own small area to the universe of knowledge. Maybe a few people have knowledge in more than a few small areas. But that does not make them generalists; it makes them specialists in several areas. And one can be just as bigoted in three areas as in one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;allowing-people-to-take-risks&quot;&gt;Allowing people to take risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Executives also owe it to the organization and to their fellow workers not to tolerate nonperforming individuals in important jobs. It may not be the employees’ fault that they are underperforming, but even so, they have to be removed. People who have failed in a new job should be given the choice to go back to a job at their former level and salary. This option is rarely exercised; such people, as a rule, leave voluntarily, at least when their employers are U.S. firms. But the very existence of the option can have a powerful effect, encouraging people to leave safe, comfortable jobs and take risky new assignments. The organization’s performance depends on employees’ willingness to take such chances.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-people&quot;&gt;Developing people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“An executive’s focus on contribution by itself is a powerful force in developing people. People adjust to the level of the demands made on them. The executive who sets his sights on contribution raises the sights and standards of everyone with whom he works.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…executives who take responsibility for contribution in their own work will as a rule demand that their subordinates take responsibility too. They will tend to ask their men: “What are the contributions for which this organization and I, your superior, should hold you accountable? What should we expect of you? What is the best utilization of your knowledge and your ability?” And then communication becomes possible, becomes indeed easy. Once the subordinate has thought through what contribution should be expected of him, the superior has, of course, both the right and the responsibility to judge the validity of the proposed contribution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A superior has responsibility for the work of others. He also has power over the careers of others. Making strengths productive is therefore much more than an essential of effectiveness. It is a moral imperative, a responsibility of authority and position. To focus on weakness is not only foolish; it is irresponsible. A superior owes it to his organization to make the strength of every one of his subordinates as productive as it can be. But even more does he owe it to the human beings over whom he exercises authority to help them get the most out of whatever strength they may have.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">According to Peter Drucker, there are eight practices that make effective executives:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/peter-drucker.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Netlify Analytics Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/netlify-analytics-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Netlify Analytics Review" /><published>2019-07-24T18:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T18:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/netlify-analytics-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/netlify-analytics-review">&lt;p&gt;Netlify Analytics is a server side analytics tool that doesn’t slow down your website, protects the privacy of your users, and is GDPR compliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released in July 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/products/analytics/&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics&lt;/a&gt; is a new add-on to Netlify’s popular hosting and deployment platform. Starting at $9/month, it’s an “expensive” alternative to the analytics king, Google Analytics, which is free. But is it worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought it to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-good-about-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;What is Good About Netlify Analytics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netlify Analytics doesn’t slow down your website at all since you don’t need to add any code to your site. Installation was as easy as clicking a button in my Netlify backend. And since it’s anonymous and doesn’t use javascript or cookies, users with adblock are still counted and I didn’t need to add any cookie warnings on my site for GDPR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-can-see-in-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;What You Can See in Netlify Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pageviews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unique visitors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top viewed pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top pages/resources not found&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top sources/referrers (with path)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bandwidth used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-cant-you-see-in-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;What Can’t You See in Netlify Analytics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;you can’t see beyond the last 30 days&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t filter by page or change the date range&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t look at the top sources for an individual page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t see the bounce rate or average time on site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-netlify-analytics-worth-it&quot;&gt;Is Netlify Analytics Worth It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Not right now. At $9/month for a product whose competitors are free and more capable, everyone was expecting more from this release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics-pricing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Netlify Analytics starts at $9/month.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics starts at $9/month.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You only have one “screen” without a single filter to segment your data.&lt;/strong&gt; Most egregious though is they delete data older than 30 days (or at least it’s not accessible). Second, I need to be able to break down referrer and pageviews by URL so I can see from where and how much traffic specific pages are getting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it is now, Netlify Analytics is a great product for people who have a simple curiosity for a site or project’s stats. And if you really care about shaving milliseconds off load times or capturing ad block users, Netlify Analytics could be for you. But if you just casually need analytics, are you going to pay $9/month for it? I’m not sure it’s worth it, but many people are happy to give Netlify $9/month for Analytics because their free hosting and deployment platform is so good that they just want to support them. It’s not all bad news for Netlify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But remember, this is version one of Netlify Analytics. If Netlify can improve the product by adding the above features, it very well could be a game changer - something I’m eagerly anticipating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives-to-netlify-analytics&quot;&gt;Alternatives to Netlify Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://usefathom.com/&quot;&gt;Fathom Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://simpleanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Simple Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although both Fathom and Simple Analytics are not server-side analytics, they are both GDPR compliant and focused on user privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just signed up for Fathom and will do a review soon to see how it compares to Netlify Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Why I stopped blogging on Medium and moved to a static, self hosted blog.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;medium vs self hosted blog&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Netlify Analytics is a server side analytics tool that doesn’t slow down your website, protects the privacy of your users, and is GDPR compliant.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Grew Organic Inbound Monthly Recurring Revenue with SEO by 130%</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/servicetitan-seo-case-study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grew Organic Inbound Monthly Recurring Revenue with SEO by 130%" /><published>2019-07-23T19:37:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-23T19:37:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/servicetitan-seo-case-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/servicetitan-seo-case-study">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, most of our customers acquired from marketing efforts were from paid channels. My goal was to increase leads and revenue generated with content and SEO. Our website was very thin on content and most of our visitors were from branded search queries. We weren’t generating any new demand. &lt;strong&gt;We were only capturing existing demand.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below was our very simple website structure. My challenge was to build and expand on this content in order to rank for more bottom-of-funnel (BOFU) search queries and therefore generate more leads without increasing marketing spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-seo-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Original ServiceTitan sitemap.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Original ServiceTitan sitemap.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To generate more leads and new customer organically, my solution was to create more BOFU content to rank for more BOFU search queries. Rather than prioritizing top-of-funnel (TOFU) such as blog posts on wider industry related topics, I prioritized creating content and ranking for buyer-centric search queries. Although these search queries are generally harder to rank for, it would quickly and directly lead to more leads and new customers. Below is the process my team and I used to accomplish this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-icreating-new-pages&quot;&gt;Part I — Creating New Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1keyword-research&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Keyword Research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we started planning the new pages to create, we first needed data. This is where keyword research came in. We started with Google Search Console (GSC) and uncovered the non-brand keywords/queries people were already using to find our site. Since Google Ads was already a consistent channel, we also looked at our top performing non-brand queries. Then, we looked at the main pages our competitors created and the queries they were going after. After gathering a list of potential queries, we prioritized them based on simple criteria: search volume, stage in funnel, and relatedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2plan-new-sitemap&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Plan New Sitemap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we knew what queries to go after, we planned what pages to create and where they would fit on our site. Here’s the new sitemap we came up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-seo-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;New ServiceTitan sitemap.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New ServiceTitan sitemap.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Product Tour would expand from a single page to nine pages. An all new section for the Industries we serve allowed us to create four more pages to go after more target queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3getting-the-team-onboard&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Getting the Team Onboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating 13 new pages is not a simple task. We needed many people involved to make sure the pages were more than just new content for SEO. They needed to correctly and thoroughly explain the product. They needed to entice the reader with good copy. They needed to be designed well and reflect our brand appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled in our Head of Creative to discuss the scope of the project. He led the designers and developers and we pulled in the Product Marketing team to create the initial copy. Our SEO Specialist on my team reviewed the copy and made sure we were optimizing for our target queries and had enough content. He also wrote the new page URLs and meta data for each page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4publishing-the-pages&quot;&gt;Step 4 — Publishing the Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first published the Industry pages, because they had the highest ROI potential and were quicker to create. Here’s what they looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-hvac-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the live pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-electrical-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the live pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-plumbing-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the live pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/hvac-software&quot;&gt;Click here to view the live pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then after much revisions and improvements, we published the new Product Tour. The old, single page Product Tour looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-old-product-tour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the live page. Note: Page may have been deleted since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/solutions&quot;&gt;Click here to view the live page. Note: Page may have been deleted since the publishing of this case study.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had only one section for each major function of the product. From a brand and web experience point-of-view, it would not be beneficial to the user to only expand on the functions that had opportunity in search. Therefore we expanded on all the main product functions into their own pages. And here’s what they looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-dispatch-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-scheduling-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-call-booking-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-marketing-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-field-reporting-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-mobile-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-financing-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the lives pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-field-reporting-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the lives pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-quickbooks-software.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click here to view the lives pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/dispatch-software&quot;&gt;Click here to view the lives pages. Note: Design on live pages may have changed since the publishing of this case study.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iionsite-seo&quot;&gt;Part II — Onsite SEO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we published the pages, I directed our SEO Specialist to fine tune each page for better rankings. This included the meta title and description, the heading tags on the page, the keyword density, and proper schema and HTML markup. To increase our click-through-rate (CTR) in the search engine result pages (SERPs), we used the review schema:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-schema.png&quot; alt=&quot;Review data used from Capterra.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.capterra.com/p/150053/ServiceTitan/&quot;&gt;Review data used from Capterra.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to let Google know these new pages are important, we added a new section on our homepage to spread some “link juice” to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-homepage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Links on the homepage to the new Industry pages.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.servicetitan.com/&quot;&gt;Links on the homepage to the new Industry pages.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we went through our best blog posts and added internal links to our new Industry and Product Tour pages where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iiilinkbuilding&quot;&gt;Part III — Linkbuilding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were already doing regular press releases, we sprinkled in some links to our new pages. Second, we hired a linkbuilding agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of marketers will say this is not a smart move, but here’s how we made it work. The links being built had to be through content. That content had to actually be good. The sites we submitted content to did not sell guest posts or allow self submissions — we had to work with them. The sites had to be related to our industry or tech. They most definitely can’t be in a private blog network (PBN). With these standards in place, we found an agency who could do this for us. They acted more like a PR firm than a linkbuilding agency and that’s exactly what we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We published the Industry pages in early Q2 of 2018 and the new Product Tour in Q3. For each Industry page’s primary keyword, we achieved a rank of either #3 or #2 in the SERPs. While the new Product Tour’s rankings are still improving, the primary query for those pages have less volume and are less lucrative. Every week we exported a search performance report from GSC. Using REGEXMATCH formulas in Google Sheets, we bucketed queries into segments to track performance in the SERPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-serp-performance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Growth of impressions and clicks from Google Search Console.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Growth of impressions and clicks from Google Search Console.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-brand BOFU organic clicks grew 260% by the beginning of Q4 ‘18 compared to the average month in Q1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To attribute down funnel metrics to organic search, we used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bizible.com/&quot;&gt;Bizible&lt;/a&gt;. With Bizible’s integration into Salesforce, we could see all the booked meetings, pipeline, and revenue generated from organic search and which page they started their session on. And because we knew which pages were ranking for which queries, we could infer how much revenue a segment of search queries were generating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/servicetitan-seo-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;Growth of attributable pipeline and revenue from organic search in 2018.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Growth of attributable pipeline and revenue from organic search in 2018.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New customer monthly recurring revenue from organic search grew 130% by the beginning of Q4 ‘18 compared to the average month in Q1. As more links are built and more content added over time, the rankings, leads, and customers generated will continue to improve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/servicetitan-seo-1.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blogging on Medium vs Self Hosted Blog" /><published>2019-07-19T11:02:48-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-19T11:02:48-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blogging-on-medium-vs-self-hosted-blog">&lt;p&gt;Most people stop blogging on Medium because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t “own” your traffic because your blog is on medium.com&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have less control of converting traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medium promotes other peoples’ articles on your own articles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More readers are dedicated to Medium than dedicated to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the switch wasn’t about the “building a house on rented land” aspect. I was early to Medium publications so I could use my custom domain (regpaq.com) on Medium. Thankfully I got in before they removed this feature so I shouldn’t lose any rankings since I’m still on the same domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what made me want to stop blogging on Medium? The stats.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium’s stats are broken and very limited. I want to be able to see three things for a given period of my choosing. How much is my traffic growing? What’s the distribution of traffic between pages? Where is that traffic coming from? This isn’t possible on Medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problems-with-medium-stats&quot;&gt;The Problems with Medium Stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one huge problem with Medium stats. &lt;strong&gt;They include views of your comments on other people’s articles in your view count!&lt;/strong&gt; And there is no way to filter them out. So no, you can’t see how many total views just your articles received over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-stats.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My last 30 days blogging on Medium for all articles... and comments.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My last 30 days blogging on Medium for all articles... and comments.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The other major problem is you can only view your traffic in 30 day windows.&lt;/strong&gt; If you got a lot of views one day, you can’t look at just that day’s traffic and see what pages got the most views or where that traffic came from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above the graph, Medium suggests you can click a story to see stats for just that story. Unfortunately, when you click on a story it loads a new page and takes five seconds to load. &lt;strong&gt;So you have to click each individual story one by one to uncover which story went “viral” and racked up the most views on a big traffic day.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-referrers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Limited referrer data for a blog post on Medium.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Limited referrer data for a blog post on Medium.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inside an individual story’s stats, you can see the list of referrers. But only the domain.&lt;/strong&gt; In the above example, I can’t see which Reddit threads are talking about my article! Which means I can’t see what people are saying and jump in the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started blogging on Medium, I knew the stats were limited, but I didn’t know by how much. The reason I moved to Medium in the first place was because I wanted simplicity. I wanted simple metrics. I didn’t want to fiddle with the design. I didn’t want to mess with plugins. I wanted a better editor than WordPress. I just wanted to write. But now things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limited-customization-on-medium&quot;&gt;Limited Customization on Medium&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest pros of blogging on Medium is that the design is all done for you. You don’t have to worry about it. It’s always better to write and publish more than to fiddle with the design. What changed for me was a massive increase in interest in learning HTML and CSS. &lt;strong&gt;By moving off of Medium, my blog is now a showcase for my design and dev skills.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I didn’t go back to WordPress and instead used &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator. It was a much bigger process than I anticipated. I designed the site in Adobe XD then developed it. &lt;strong&gt;The end result is a blog I designed and I developed with articles I wrote and I illustrated. It’s a culmination of many of my skills in a single project.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-sites-are-fast&quot;&gt;Static Sites are Fast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit to a static site is the speed. Because WordPress and Medium use a database, it loads much slower. Here is the Pingdom page speed and Google score comparison of the same article on Medium versus the current static site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-pingdom-old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medium article page speed from Pingdom.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Medium article page speed from Pingdom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-google-old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medium article page speed score from Google.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Medium article page speed score from Google.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-pingdom-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Static article page speed from Pingdom.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Static article page speed from Pingdom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/medium-google-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Static article page speed score from Google.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Static article page speed score from Google.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The static site is a massive improvement for speed&lt;/strong&gt; - even without any image optimization. This should improve the bounce rate and thus increase organic rankings. But because people know what to expect when they land on a Medium-designed article, it’s possible the new design increases the bounce rate. I’ll never know for certain because you can’t measure the bounce rate on Medium. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one catch here about the speed of my site. I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;Netlify’s new Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, which is a server side analytics solution. It measures at the server level so it’s not adding an extra request to the page, like Google Analytics would. The problem is Netlify’s Analytics is even worse than Medium’s so I’ll be switching to Google Analytics or Clicky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics Review&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Is it everything the industry has been waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;netlify analytics review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ill-miss-about-blogging-on-medium&quot;&gt;What I’ll Miss About Blogging on Medium&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium’s coolest social feature is “claps.” If people like your article, they can clap for it up to 50 times. It’s nice to get and give claps, but it does have a downside. Medium syndicates and recommends articles to other users based on how many claps it gets. &lt;strong&gt;This made me too focused on claps. I even joined three Facebook groups where people just clap for each others’ articles. It’s a stupid game.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also miss comments until I can figure out a solution. Because static sites don’t have databases, comments are difficult to add. I don’t want to use something like Disqus, which increases load time and prevents me from “owning” the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I won’t miss Medium’s distribution. I never got any meaningful distribution. I could have written more content for more claps, but I didn’t want to play that game.&lt;/strong&gt; I want to write what I want to write about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now onto finding which analytics tool I’m going to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/netlify-analytics-review&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;        
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;Netlify Analytics Review&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;post-desc&quot;&gt;Is it everything the industry has been waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/netlify-analytics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;netlify analytics review&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;        
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Most people stop blogging on Medium because:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/medium-vs-self-hosted-blog.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Increased Cold Outbound Booked Meetings by 49% in Q1 ’19 Over Q4 ‘18</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/helped-increase-cold-outbound-booked-meetings-by-49-in-q1-19-over-q4-18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Increased Cold Outbound Booked Meetings by 49% in Q1 ’19 Over Q4 ‘18" /><published>2019-06-10T19:37:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-10T19:37:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/helped-increase-cold-outbound-booked-meetings-by-49-in-q1-19-over-q4-18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/helped-increase-cold-outbound-booked-meetings-by-49-in-q1-19-over-q4-18">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined Chili Piper, we had just one full cycle account executive (AE) on the sales team and the plan was to hire eight more in seven months. The challenge was to (1) develop instrumentation to determine what part of our outreach was working, (2) reliably scale it to other sales reps as they joined the team, and (3) improve the conversion rate of accounts worked to meetings booked so we wouldn’t burn through our target accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1build-instrumentation-to-measure-cadence-performance&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Build Instrumentation to Measure Cadence Performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we were using SalesLoft and it integrates with Salesforce (SFDC), I was able to build automated dashboards that tracked over 140 different metrics for each cadence. Read about how I did this &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-salesloft-cadence-metrics-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Now I could look at our cold outbound performance and see exactly which meetings were booked from what cadences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2figure-out-whatworks&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Figure Out What Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;measure-content-and-messaging&quot;&gt;Measure content and messaging&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the instrumentation in place, I started making new cadences and adding keywords to our email step names which we could use to break out performance. For example, we started with persuasion factors (liking, consistency, social proof, etc). Then I started adding keywords for content that we’d include — a certain GIF, an image, etc. From this, I determined what type of approach worked best and what content was most effective at getting our value across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optimize-strategy-and-approach-to-target-accounts&quot;&gt;Optimize strategy and approach to target accounts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I looked at our strategy of which accounts to target. We previously were just working accounts our AE had found on online lists like the Cloud 100. Because we had Clearbit Enrichment, I wanted to use some of the data it provided on accounts we had in SFDC. First, I made a list of target accounts that were using Drift. The logic here was that if they were using Drift, they have already bought into the idea that they need to empower their buyers and make it easier for them to connect with sales (which aligned very closely with Chili Piper). I wrote a cadence piggybacking on this belief and positioned our product as an additional way to make it easier for their buyers to connect with them. I did the same for target accounts using intercom and we saw a 71% increase in the rate of accounts worked to meetings booked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In attempt to replicate this strategy, I wrote a cadence targeting accounts who had a conversion rate optimization tool (VWO, Optimizely, etc). This time, I piggybacked on the idea that if they care about their conversion rate on their website and landing pages, they should also care about the conversion rate after the form submission to a closed deal. As expected, this didn’t perform as well as piggybacking off a chat tool, but still better than our original cadence by 22%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;customize-cadences-to-the-account&quot;&gt;Customize cadences to the account&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with these types of cadences were we couldn’t scale them, but they remained in our back pocket when we could use them. For accounts that weren’t using either of these identified tools, we needed a different approach. Since we were signing new accounts who are vertical leaders, we customized which customers we name dropped as social proof by aligning them as much as possible to the prospect’s industry. Additionally, I had our reps take a screenshot of the prospect’s lead/demo form to put in the first email. This account personalized cadence was a huge 107% improvement over our original cadence and we scaled this to rest of the team and our new hires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a team, we were able to increase productivity and efficiency that resulted in a 49% increase in cold outbound booked meetings in Q1 ’19 compared to Q4 ’18 and a 118% jump in pipeline generated. We were trending to improve booked meetings in Q2 ’19 by another 18% and pipeline by 9%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-cold-outbound-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Cold outbound booked meeting and pipeline improvement.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cold outbound booked meeting and pipeline improvement.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/chili-cold-outbound-1.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Grew Revenue From Inbound 282% in Q2 ’19 Over Q1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/grew-revenue-from-inbound-282-in-q2-19-over-q1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grew Revenue From Inbound 282% in Q2 ’19 Over Q1" /><published>2019-06-10T11:42:47-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-10T11:42:47-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/grew-revenue-from-inbound-282-in-q2-19-over-q1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/grew-revenue-from-inbound-282-in-q2-19-over-q1">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;goal to double new business monthly revenue&lt;/a&gt; in less than 12 months and it was going to take massive effort from both our cold prospecting and demand gen efforts. Additionally, we wanted to increase market awareness of our flagship product, Concierge, which allowed qualified leads to schedule their own sales meeting while filling out a demo request form — a step toward being more self-serve for B2B companies that require prospects to go through sales to become a customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1refresh-linkedinads&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Refresh LinkedIn Ads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started LinkedIn ads with great success in the last two quarters of 2018, but we began to experience some audience decay as costs-per-click and costs-per-booked meeting started to rise dramatically. What was once a fresh product for a new audience became a stale product for an audience who’s seen our ads and product several dozen times — if they didn’t convert already, we would need to do something different to convert them now. Here’s the type of ads we had ran when first starting LinkedIn Ads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Chili Piper LinkedIn ads that worked when first starting the channel.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Old Chili Piper LinkedIn ads that worked when first starting the channel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were spending ~$10k+ on LinkedIn to reach our audience every month, I decided our next move was to run more visually engaging ads that showed and explained the product so even if people didn’t click through, they could see what our product had to offer. The “secret weapon” would now be revealed into their news feeds, which also made impressions much more valuable. Here’s what they looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New image ads.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New image ads.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New LinkedIn carousel ad to increase engagement and show how Concierge works.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New LinkedIn carousel ad to increase engagement and show how Concierge works.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-4.gif&quot; alt=&quot;New video ad.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New video ad.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I tested video ads showing how it works right on the landing page this ad led to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested several different messaging to each of our main personas and kept a log of what type of messaging (e.g. pain points, value benefits) resonated with our different personas the best. The plan was to take these learnings and apply them to all of our marketing and messaging across our teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2new-landingpages&quot;&gt;Step 2 — New Landing Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to increasing the value of ad impressions on LinkedIn, I also overhauled our landing page with improved copy, branding, and design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Old landing page on the left; new on the right.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Old landing page on the left; new on the right.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new landing page converted 84% better (4.94% vs 2.68%) than the old one. A big reason for this improvement was the new ads were sending less clicks than the old ads, but the traffic was higher quality because the new ads showed what the product was about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3launch-google-ads-search-and-retargeting&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Launch Google Ads Search and Retargeting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up until this point, we never had invested a lot of resources into developing our Google Ads program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;search-campaigns&quot;&gt;Search Campaigns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with 3 core search campaigns: competitors, non-brand, and brand. The competitors campaign bid on several queries like “{alternatives, competitors, similar to, like} [competitor name]”. To grab the attention of our target market, we made sure to include “B2B” in our ad copy at least once in every ad. The non-brand campaign consisted of targeting search queries around “scheduling for B2B” or “scheduling for sales.” In the brand campaign, we bid on keywords that included our brand name, but which we weren’t ranking #1 in Google for, such as “Chili Piper Reviews”, “Chili Piper plugin”, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;retargeting-campaigns&quot;&gt;Retargeting Campaigns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I set up a retargeting campaign to all website visitors, including those who visited our landing pages from LinkedIn and AdWords. The ads looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Chili Piper Google retargeting ads.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New Chili Piper Google retargeting ads.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now anyone who visited our website or our landing pages and didn’t convert would see our product, branding, and main value prop. Anyone who visited our website and is in the sales process with an account executive would see these ads, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closed-won revenue from inbound demo requests jumped 155% in April and May ’19 compared to all of Q1. Using an average of April and May’19 for a simple June forecast, revenue growth will increase to 282%.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/chili-inbound-2.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Built Forecast Growth Model to Double Customer Acquisition Growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Built Forecast Growth Model to Double Customer Acquisition Growth" /><published>2019-06-09T11:01:47-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T11:01:47-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a goal to double new business monthly revenue, but not a clear path or timeline to get there. We were only looking in the rear view mirror and monthly reviews ended with us saying, “we did well, but we need to get to x (somehow).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without clear targets for each team and individual in the customer acquisition org, we couldn’t motivate the team, forecast growth, or determine which channels and initiatives to prioritize to hit our target in the shortest amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the previous 12 month performance by major customer acquisition (CA) function (Outbound, Events, Paid Inbound, and Earned Inbound), we could find the best opportunities for growth while giving clear targets to each team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, it’s essential to have reliable data. Since I previously built a &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;Revenue Dashboard&lt;/a&gt; that detailed our funnel metrics by major CA function already, I could begin to do some estimations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wrong way to forecast is to start with saying “Okay, we need to get to x in 12 months. What do we need to do to get there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I‘ve learned to to start with from the bottom up by identifying the inputs and levers that are in your control and what the results could be if you increased those inputs and pulled those levers over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1start-with-previousresults&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Start With Previous Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a new spreadsheet, I started with previous data broken down by the major CA functions I wanted to forecast by: Outbound, Events, Paid Inbound, Earned Inbound, and a total that rolls up all four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2define-your-inputs-and-levers-for-eachfunction&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Define Your Inputs and Levers for Each Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different functions will have different inputs and levers and you’ll have to determine what those are. Here’s what I went with at Chili Piper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;outbound&quot;&gt;Outbound&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inputs for cold Outbound were the (1) number of sales development reps (SDRs) and full-cycle account executives (AEs) and (2) the number of booked meetings we could reasonably expect each rep to book at full efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I knew how many reps we needed to hit a particular Outbound meeting goal and closed won revenue goal. Then we added an estimated ramp period and figured out what was possible with cold Outbound based on when and how many people we could afford to hire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cold outbound hiring plan and forecast.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cold outbound hiring plan and forecast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cold Outbound hiring plan and booked meeting forecast to hit goal in December ‘19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I knew what we could expect in Outbound meetings per month based on the number of each type of sales reps we had and if they were running at full efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next was to look at the levers, which I concluded to be (1) our conversion rates of each part of the funnel and (2) our average customer value (ACV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Levers can be adjusted for a ground up forecast.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Levers can be adjusted for a ground up forecast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue numbers are the levers. By pulling these levers, we could improve efficiency over time. Number of Goal Booked Meetings roll up from the inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why conversion rates and ACV? It’s what our sales team has most control of. For example, in April, I estimated our team would convert 75% of Outbound booked meetings into opportunities. The SDR is in control of setting qualified meetings and in control of the cadence and messaging to increase likelihood the prospect will attend the meeting. Next was estimating improvement in opportunity to closed-won conversion rates. It’s 16% in April and grows to 20% by June. We estimated this 25% improvement in just two months because we had already recognized this as an opportunity for improvement and implemented weekly training and call coaching to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Chili Piper’s product can be used by many different teams at a company and we have a variety of products, it’s difficult to estimate the potential value of an account. In the past, AEs have closed good-size companies in just a $300 deal (one product and one license), and other times deal sizes can be several thousand dollars when selling multiple products and many licenses up front. With training again, we were able to improve the ACV and expected it to continue to grow as skills improve and as we release more products throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing my methodology for Events, the inputs are (1) the number of events and (2) the number of expected meetings from each event. Working with our Events Manager, we were able to roughly plan out the rest of the year and set meeting goals for each event and attending sales rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Event booked meeting goals by sales rep. Meetings booked by “Other” are from non Sales team members.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Event booked meeting goals by sales rep. Meetings booked by “Other” are from non Sales team members.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The levers for Events are the same as Outbound, conversion rates and ACV; however, we didn’t forecast any change here since we already converted well from events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Goal Booked Meetings roll up from the inputs.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Number of Goal Booked Meetings roll up from the inputs.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paid-inbound&quot;&gt;Paid Inbound&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forecasting and goal setting for Paid Inbound is a bit tricky because the only true input fully in my control is spend, however with limited historical data, spend and cost-per-lead (CPL) by channel wasn’t the best place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, my inputs were the number of leads I could reasonably expect from each of the channels we’re currently using and plan to use in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inbound lead goal by channel for Paid Inbound.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Inbound lead goal by channel for Paid Inbound.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The levers for Inbound include conversion rates and ACV, but start with Leads and two additional conversion stages: Lead &amp;gt; Marketing Qualified Lead (MQL) and MQL to Booked Meeting (BM). For spend, I estimated the average total CPL and therefore determined the budget required for paid acquisition for the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Paid forecast broken down by channel.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Paid forecast broken down by channel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we didn’t have historical Paid &amp;amp; Earned Inbound metrics until May, Paid Inbound forecasts start in June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;earned-inbound&quot;&gt;Earned Inbound&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earned Inbound is even more trickier than Paid. For the most part, Earned Inbound is out of my direct control. Results come from a combination of activities done throughout the company. And since we didn’t have a marketing automation platform set up, we couldn’t yet determine the source of non paid leads, which could either be direct, organic, or referral. So unfortunately, there was much more guess work here and I simply estimated a growth in leads over time and the levers being the same as Paid Inbound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Estimated growth in Earned (non paid) leads over time.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Estimated growth in Earned (non paid) leads over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3making-thisuseful&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Making This Useful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each function’s goals had two tables below: (1) an auto updating “Actuals” table and (2) a table comparing the differences from Goal to Actual to visually see where we hit and missed goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Everything rolls up for a total customer acquisition forecast.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Everything rolls up for a total customer acquisition forecast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having all this data in one place was great for the leadership team to get a pulse check on all the teams in CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then because I built dashboards for &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;New Business Revenue&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/building-the-marketing-dashboard&quot;&gt;Marketing&lt;/a&gt;, and Outbound Sales, I could put an auto updating Trend and Goal column where each team could see what they were currently trending to as a team and individually and how that compared to the month’s Goal. This made it easy to see at any point during the month where we had to step up in order to hit goal. Here’s an example of what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Forecast and goals by channel were added to each channel's dashboards.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Forecast and goals by channel were added to each channel's dashboards.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this was created, each team and individual now had goals and targets to hit every month that they could easily find on the dashboards they already used. This made it more simple to set everyone’s monthly OKRs, motivate the team, and let us rest easy by knowing that if we hit the month’s goal we were on our way to double growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/chili-forecast-8.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Created an Automated Marketing Dashboard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/building-the-marketing-dashboard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Created an Automated Marketing Dashboard" /><published>2019-05-31T23:33:12-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-31T23:33:12-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/building-the-marketing-dashboard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/building-the-marketing-dashboard">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We weren’t tracking at a holistic level how much marketing was contributing to the business. We only had detailed marketing metrics for our main customer acquisition channel, LinkedIn. We couldn’t see all at once how many earned versus paid leads were generated month over month and all the down funnel metrics there after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made it impossible to &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;forecast and set goals&lt;/a&gt; realistically and on a per channel basis. Additionally, we couldn’t see down a level in detail how each individual paid channel was performing month over month, what each channel’s conversion rates were, and many other metrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After implementing a &lt;a href=&quot;/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system&quot;&gt;marketing attribution system&lt;/a&gt;, the next step was to build a marketing dashboard to segment leads and opportunities by channel. I wanted to build two main dashboards for marketing: point-in-time for goal setting and cohort (based on demo request date) for precisely measuring conversion rates and cost per win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what it looked like and what I wanted to measure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-mktg-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Chili Piper Marketing Dashboard.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New Chili Piper Marketing Dashboard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;Building The Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I could start writing formulas into a spreadsheet, I had to make sure we had accurate and complete data in Salesforce (SFDC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1redefining-salesstages&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Redefining Sales Stages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done when I first built a &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;new business revenue dashboard&lt;/a&gt; for Chili Piper. I more clearly defined what our sales funnel stages were and set up date stamp process builders in SFDC for the important stage changes: demo request date, booked meeting data, and became an opportunity (opp) date (I used the native close date in SFDC). These dates are critical to record &lt;strong&gt;when&lt;/strong&gt; things actually happen, especially for when a deal became an ‘official’ opp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Chili Piper, we created an Opportunity object when a booked meeting had been set, therefore the SFDC Opportunity create date reflects the date a meeting was set and accepted, not when a true opp was reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided not to count a deal as an opp in our sales funnel until the prospect 1) showed up to their demo and 2) was qualified. Doing it this way helped us better understand the quality and give more meaning to an opp while also providing a more accurate AE conversion rates by eliminating no shows and disqualifieds — prospects that are impossible for an AE to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2setting-up-marketing-attribution-system&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Setting Up Marketing Attribution System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system&quot;&gt;creating an attribution system&lt;/a&gt; and implementing it for future leads across all channels, I updated our old leads and opps with the new format to make reporting easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3creating-the-salesforce-reports-and-importing-them-automatically-into-a-googlesheet&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Creating the Salesforce Reports and Importing Them Automatically into a Google Sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the formulas easier, I created two Opportunity, Lead, and Contact object reports for earned and paid. Then I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/gconnector_for_salesforce/971770431958&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;G-Connector&lt;/a&gt; to automatically import the reports into data tabs in the spreadsheet and refresh the data daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the data was in there, I could build the point-in-time and cohort views of our marketing performance and isolate performance between earned and paid and roll it up to a total. So now I could see how much pipeline and revenue earned and paid was generating in any given month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4creating-dashboards-for-each-marketing-channel&quot;&gt;Step 4 — Creating Dashboards for Each Marketing Channel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the marketing attribution naming conventions were standardized, it was easy to build separate dashboards for each channel, including an overall funnel view and one broken up by campaign, audience, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what that looked like for our biggest audience on LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-mktg-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Marketing attribution channel breadk down for LinkedIn ads&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Marketing attribution channel breadk down for LinkedIn ads&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran campaigns targeting specific titles in all marketing, sales, and customer success. I built another dashboard for each of these audiences broken down by individual titles. So for marketing for example, we had a full breakdown from spend to close won revenue for VP of Marketing, CMO, Director of Marketing, Demand Gen Marketers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This level of detail was also done for our other channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some of the action items this data helped drive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set goals:&lt;/strong&gt; I had pretty accurate historical customer acquisition performance by outbound, events, earned inbound, and paid inbound. Now I could &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;set a reasonable plan and forecast to double revenue&lt;/a&gt;. Then I dynamically populated the goal data by stage (column AE above) and measured how the current month was trending to our goals, giving us a heads up in the middle of the month where we needed to take action the most to hit our monthly goal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spot weak parts in the funnel:&lt;/strong&gt; It became immediately clear what channels were converting better than others. Then I listened to AE calls to get an understanding of why prospects weren’t converting as well as other channels. Earned inbound converted the best because they had previous knowledge of the product / company and had intent. Outbound and paid acquisition didn’t close as strong and we created more marketing collateral for sales to improve pain identification and value props of our products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimize spend:&lt;/strong&gt; Now that I could see how our advertising budget was performing by each campaign and audience with down funnel metrics, it became much easier to spot losing and winning audiences and optimize our spend for the biggest ROI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimize messaging:&lt;/strong&gt; So while making dashboards is great for high level analysis and reporting, it’s too time consuming to make reports on the fly. However, all of this data is in SFDC so it’s very fast to make ad-hoc reports in SFDC. For example, if I wanted to see how well a certain vale prop was performing in one channel, across all channels, or by persona, it could be done in minutes in SFDC. This helped drive which value props resonated the most with which personas which we drove our brand, content, and product messaging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/chili-mktg-1.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Implemented Marketing Attribution Infrastructure (Last Touch)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Implemented Marketing Attribution Infrastructure (Last Touch)" /><published>2019-05-27T18:10:51-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T18:10:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first came onboard, we were running paid acquisition campaigns on just LinkedIn and Capterra. To measure their performance, we were using a separate form for each channel and just three URL tracking parameters: ppc_campaign, ppc_ad, and ppc_keyword without any kind of naming conventions in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using multiple forms is an easy way to separate channel performance easily, but the upkeep of them as more channels are added is cumbersome and becomes unnecessary with a proper attribution system in place. And without standard naming conventions for campaigns, content, and term, it can be difficult to scale tracking and measuring performance of content and angles across channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upgrading ppc_campaign, ppc_ad, and ppc_keyword to the full main five tracking parameters used in Google Analytics (source, medium, campaign, content, and term) provided us with a standardized attribution system we could use across channels. Then we just needed one form we could use on all of our landing pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we didn’t have a marketing automation platform or a marketing attribution platform, we decided to move forward with a simple last-touch attribution system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1create-marketing-attribution-fields-in-salesforce&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Create Marketing Attribution Fields in Salesforce&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we changed the three existing tracking fields to ‘Marketing Campaign,’ ‘Marketing Content,’ and ‘Marketing Term’. Then we added ‘Marketing Source’ and ‘Marketing Medium’. For marketing reporting purposes, we also added ‘Latest Demo Request Date’ and a ‘Demo Requested’ toggle we use to fire other automation. These fields were created on the Lead object in Salesforce (SFDC), the Contact, and the Opportunity (Opp).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-attribution-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;New marketing attribution fields in Salesforce.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New marketing attribution fields in Salesforce.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2creating-the-form-and-capturing-url-parameters&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Creating the Form and Capturing URL Parameters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using Clearbit Forms, which allow us to capture values from URL parameters natively. All I needed to do was create the hidden fields and map them to the parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-automating-the-data-flow-in-salesforce&quot;&gt;Step 3— Automating the Data Flow in Salesforce&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Lead is converted to a Contact and Account, we set up the attribution fields to be carried over to the Contact. When converted to an Opp, they also flow to the Opp where once created are frozen so they can’t be overwritten by a subsequent form submissions. This was set up because we wanted to credit the last marketing campaign that generated the Opp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4standardizing-naming-conventions-in-a-urlbuilder&quot;&gt;Step 4 — Standardizing Naming Conventions in a URL Builder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the foundation has been built, I could build a URL Builder tool in a Google Sheet and standardize naming conventions used for channels, campaigns, content, audiences etc. This is essential for being able to uncover what’s working what isn’t within a single channel over time and across channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one tab (data tab) was columns for source, medium, campaign, and term. I broke content up into five sub data points that all combined into one that was to be used for content. They were product, value/benefit, audience, media, and copy/ad variant. In the rows under each column were a list of values. For example, under source was google, linkedin, capterra, etc. Under value/benefit was connecting, conversion-rate, speed-to-lead. That way, in any future campaign in any channel, we could come back to using these naming conventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On another tab was the actual URL Builder. Each column used data validation from the data tab so my team and I could build tracking URLs using a series of dropdown menus and if something didn’t match it threw an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked liked this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-attribution-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;URL Builder in a spreadsheet for Chili Piper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;URL Builder in a spreadsheet for Chili Piper&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final cell combined all the data using simple CONCATENATE formulas and resulted in a tracking URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every campaign started was built using this URL builder that ensured consistent naming conventions for marketing attributions. This allowed us to build accurate marketing reports broken down by channel, audience, and campaign. It allowed us to view the success specific pieces of content, ads, media type, or angles across channels. And because it’s all in SFDC, we could do quick ad-hoc analysis using any combination of these parameters to see what’s working or not and drive strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/chili-attribution-2.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Automated Customer Acquisition Funnel and Revenue Reporting from SFDC to Google Sheets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automated Customer Acquisition Funnel and Revenue Reporting from SFDC to Google Sheets" /><published>2019-05-27T09:58:23-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T09:58:23-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tended to view whether we had a good month or not on the customer acquisition (CA) side based purely on how much healthy open pipeline we had at the end of the month and how much revenue from new logos was generated. We didn’t really review (or set goals to) all the metrics in the funnel, such as leads, MQLs, booked meetings, opportunities, pipeline, disqualified, no show, closed-won, etc and broken down by the three major CA functions: inbound, outbound, and events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made it difficult to &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;set goals and forecast&lt;/a&gt;, and know by mid month what we were trending to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution was to build a spreadsheet that recorded each stage of the funnel for each CA function in both a point-in-time and a cohort view all updated automatically. With all the numbers available in one view, it became much easier to see how well each function of CA performed compared to previous months, spot low converting stages in our funnel, and find new opportunities to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-idata-cleanliness-in-salesforce&quot;&gt;Part I — Data Cleanliness in Salesforce&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1documenting-processes-for-opportunities&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Documenting Processes for Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the data needed to make this dashboard would be from the Opportunity (Opp) object in Salesforce (SFDC). We needed to enforce through documented processes when sales reps should be creating Opps (and when they shouldn’t), how to properly update Opps, and build in rules to make certain fields required depending on the Opp stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2redefining-sales-funnelstages&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Redefining Sales Funnel Stages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started out with a very simple sales funnel: leads &amp;gt; opportunities &amp;gt; close. We added an additional stage between leads and opportunities we called ‘Booked Meeting,’ which signified that the initial discovery call/demo was booked by a sales rep and is scheduled to run, but hasn’t yet. This is the first stage on the Opp we called ‘Demo.’ Even though it was an Opp object, we didn’t call it a true opportunity because the prospect could still no show or be disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This now meant when something was an opportunity, it means the prospect is qualified and had a successful discovery call/demo. Plus, the conversion rate of opportunity to closed-won/lost was now a much better indicator for an AE’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-creating-point-in-time-stage-changedates&quot;&gt;Step 3— Creating Point-in-Time Stage Change Dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, SFDC records the Opp creation date and close date, but this limits our flexibility and reporting options. We created a few process builders to record the Opp creation date into a separate field on the Opp called ‘Became a Booked Meeting On,’ which allowed us to change it if needed. Once an Opp moved from the initial stage of ‘Demo’ to a positive next stage, we time stamped the date to a field called “Became an Opportunity On.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-revenue-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Salesforce view of stage change date stamps.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Salesforce view of stage change date stamps.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iibuilding-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;Part II — Building the Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have good data on our Opp objects, I built dashboards in a Google Sheet to measure CA performance both by point-in-time (what happened during this month) and cohort (what happened to Opps created during this month).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1automating-data-into-googlesheets&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Automating Data Into Google Sheets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/gconnector_for_salesforce/971770431958&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;G-Connector&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to login to SFDC from a Google Sheet, find our Opp report, and schedule a daily import into a separate tab in the spreadsheet. I scheduled it to update once a night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2building-the-point-in-time-dashboard&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Building the Point-In-Time Dashboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the data is in the spreadsheet, building the layout of the spreadsheet and adding the formulas were pretty straightforward. On the point-in-tab view, I created a simple linear trend to predict where we’d be at the end of the month if our current pace continued then compared that trend tour goals. With visual formatting, this helped show where we need to pick up the pace at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the point-in-time view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-revenue-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Chili Piper Revenue Dashboard.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Chili Piper Revenue Dashboard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3building-the-cohortview&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Building the Cohort View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, the cohort view is the same as the point-in-time view, but instead of using our new ‘Became an Opportunity On’ and close date fields, we stuck with the our new ‘Became a Booked Meeting On’ field throughout the funnel. So this view would answer questions like, “of all the booked meetings generated in April 2019, how much pipeline and revenue did we generate from them?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the dashboard is complete and auto updating everyday, we have a very concise, high-level view of how each CA function is doing. Here’s three example scenarios our new revenue dashboard helped us understand instantly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When revenue is down one month, why?&lt;/strong&gt; We can check which CA function (inbound, outbound, events) had low revenue and find out answer there. Or perhaps it was down across the board, and we can see that our AE conversion rates are down. We could then implement extra training to help address this issue and get feedback from the AEs about what supporting collateral they could use to help close more deals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pipeline from inbound was low one month, why?&lt;/strong&gt; Since leads and booked meetings are the direct driver of pipeline for inbound, we can check whether booked meetings were down and if leads were down. If leads weren’t down, perhaps it was a lead quality issue we could look into. If leads were down, we could look at our &lt;a href=&quot;building-the-marketing-dashboard&quot;&gt;marketing dashboard&lt;/a&gt; to see which channels were down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re trending 10% above our pipeline goal this month, what’s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; By pulling in the current month’s &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;goal numbers from our plan and forecast&lt;/a&gt;, we could see how well we’re doing compared to goal. This could be answered by looking at which function is over achieving on pipeline generation and figure out why from there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/chili-revenue-2.jpeg" /></entry></feed>