<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-18T15:28:21-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">regpaq</title><subtitle>B2B Marketer. Avid reader &amp; writer.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Increased Cold Outbound Booked Meetings by 49% in Q1 ’19 Over Q4 ‘18</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/helped-increase-cold-outbound-booked-meetings-by-49-in-q1-19-over-q4-18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Increased Cold Outbound Booked Meetings by 49% in Q1 ’19 Over Q4 ‘18" /><published>2019-06-10T19:37:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-10T19:37:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/helped-increase-cold-outbound-booked-meetings-by-49-in-q1-19-over-q4-18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/helped-increase-cold-outbound-booked-meetings-by-49-in-q1-19-over-q4-18">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined Chili Piper, we had just one full cycle account executive (AE) on the sales team and the plan was to hire eight more in seven months. The challenge was to (1) develop instrumentation to determine what part of our outreach was working, (2) reliably scale it to other sales reps as they joined the team, and (3) improve the conversion rate of accounts worked to meetings booked so we wouldn’t burn through our target accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1build-instrumentation-to-measure-cadence-performance&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Build Instrumentation to Measure Cadence Performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we were using SalesLoft and it integrates with Salesforce (SFDC), I was able to build automated dashboards that tracked over 140 different metrics for each cadence. Read about how I did this &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-salesloft-cadence-metrics-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Now I could look at our cold outbound performance and see exactly which meetings were booked from what cadences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2figure-out-whatworks&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Figure Out What Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;measure-content-and-messaging&quot;&gt;Measure content and messaging&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the instrumentation in place, I started making new cadences and adding keywords to our email step names which we could use to break out performance. For example, we started with persuasion factors (liking, consistency, social proof, etc). Then I started adding keywords for content that we’d include — a certain GIF, an image, etc. From this, I determined what type of approach worked best and what content was most effective at getting our value across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optimize-strategy-and-approach-to-target-accounts&quot;&gt;Optimize strategy and approach to target accounts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I looked at our strategy of which accounts to target. We previously were just working accounts our AE had found on online lists like the Cloud 100. Because we had Clearbit Enrichment, I wanted to use some of the data it provided on accounts we had in SFDC. First, I made a list of target accounts that were using Drift. The logic here was that if they were using Drift, they have already bought into the idea that they need to empower their buyers and make it easier for them to connect with sales (which aligned very closely with Chili Piper). I wrote a cadence piggybacking on this belief and positioned our product as an additional way to make it easier for their buyers to connect with them. I did the same for target accounts using intercom and we saw a 71% increase in the rate of accounts worked to meetings booked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In attempt to replicate this strategy, I wrote a cadence targeting accounts who had a conversion rate optimization tool (VWO, Optimizely, etc). This time, I piggybacked on the idea that if they care about their conversion rate on their website and landing pages, they should also care about the conversion rate after the form submission to a closed deal. As expected, this didn’t perform as well as piggybacking off a chat tool, but still better than our original cadence by 22%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;customize-cadences-to-the-account&quot;&gt;Customize cadences to the account&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with these types of cadences were we couldn’t scale them, but they remained in our back pocket when we could use them. For accounts that weren’t using either of these identified tools, we needed a different approach. Since we were signing new accounts who are vertical leaders, we customized which customers we name dropped as social proof by aligning them as much as possible to the prospect’s industry. Additionally, I had our reps take a screenshot of the prospect’s lead/demo form to put in the first email. This account personalized cadence was a huge 107% improvement over our original cadence and we scaled this to rest of the team and our new hires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a team, we were able to increase productivity and efficiency that resulted in a 49% increase in cold outbound booked meetings in Q1 ’19 compared to Q4 ’18 and a 118% jump in pipeline generated. We were trending to improve booked meetings in Q2 ’19 by another 18% and pipeline by 9%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-cold-outbound-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Cold outbound booked meeting and pipeline improvement.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cold outbound booked meeting and pipeline improvement.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grew Revenue From Inbound 282% in Q2 ’19 Over Q1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/grew-revenue-from-inbound-282-in-q2-19-over-q1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grew Revenue From Inbound 282% in Q2 ’19 Over Q1" /><published>2019-06-10T11:42:47-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-10T11:42:47-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/grew-revenue-from-inbound-282-in-q2-19-over-q1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/grew-revenue-from-inbound-282-in-q2-19-over-q1">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;goal to double new business monthly revenue&lt;/a&gt; in less than 12 months and it was going to take massive effort from both our cold prospecting and demand gen efforts. Additionally, we wanted to increase market awareness of our flagship product, Concierge, which allowed qualified leads to schedule their own sales meeting while filling out a demo request form — a step toward being more self-serve for B2B companies that require prospects to go through sales to become a customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1refresh-linkedinads&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Refresh LinkedIn Ads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started LinkedIn ads with great success in the last two quarters of 2018, but we began to experience some audience decay as costs-per-click and costs-per-booked meeting started to rise dramatically. What was once a fresh product for a new audience became a stale product for an audience who’s seen our ads and product several dozen times — if they didn’t convert already, we would need to do something different to convert them now. Here’s the type of ads we had ran when first starting LinkedIn Ads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Chili Piper LinkedIn ads that worked when first starting the channel.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Old Chili Piper LinkedIn ads that worked when first starting the channel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were spending ~$10k+ on LinkedIn to reach our audience every month, I decided our next move was to run more visually engaging ads that showed and explained the product so even if people didn’t click through, they could see what our product had to offer. The “secret weapon” would now be revealed into their news feeds, which also made impressions much more valuable. Here’s what they looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New image ads.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New image ads.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New LinkedIn carousel ad to increase engagement and show how Concierge works.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New LinkedIn carousel ad to increase engagement and show how Concierge works.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-4.gif&quot; alt=&quot;New video ad.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New video ad.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I tested video ads showing how it works right on the landing page this ad led to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested several different messaging to each of our main personas and kept a log of what type of messaging (e.g. pain points, value benefits) resonated with our different personas the best. The plan was to take these learnings and apply them to all of our marketing and messaging across our teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2new-landingpages&quot;&gt;Step 2 — New Landing Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to increasing the value of ad impressions on LinkedIn, I also overhauled our landing page with improved copy, branding, and design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Old landing page on the left; new on the right.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Old landing page on the left; new on the right.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new landing page converted 84% better (4.94% vs 2.68%) than the old one. A big reason for this improvement was the new ads were sending less clicks than the old ads, but the traffic was higher quality because the new ads showed what the product was about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3launch-google-ads-search-and-retargeting&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Launch Google Ads Search and Retargeting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up until this point, we never had invested a lot of resources into developing our Google Ads program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;search-campaigns&quot;&gt;Search Campaigns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with 3 core search campaigns: competitors, non-brand, and brand. The competitors campaign bid on several queries like “{alternatives, competitors, similar to, like} [competitor name]”. To grab the attention of our target market, we made sure to include “B2B” in our ad copy at least once in every ad. The non-brand campaign consisted of targeting search queries around “scheduling for B2B” or “scheduling for sales.” In the brand campaign, we bid on keywords that included our brand name, but which we weren’t ranking #1 in Google for, such as “Chili Piper Reviews”, “Chili Piper plugin”, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;retargeting-campaigns&quot;&gt;Retargeting Campaigns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I set up a retargeting campaign to all website visitors, including those who visited our landing pages from LinkedIn and AdWords. The ads looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-inbound-6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Chili Piper Google retargeting ads.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New Chili Piper Google retargeting ads.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now anyone who visited our website or our landing pages and didn’t convert would see our product, branding, and main value prop. Anyone who visited our website and is in the sales process with an account executive would see these ads, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closed-won revenue from inbound demo requests jumped 155% in April and May ’19 compared to all of Q1. Using an average of April and May’19 for a simple June forecast, revenue growth will increase to 282%.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Built Forecast Growth Model to Double Customer Acquisition Growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Built Forecast Growth Model to Double Customer Acquisition Growth" /><published>2019-06-09T11:01:47-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T11:01:47-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a goal to double new business monthly revenue, but not a clear path or timeline to get there. We were only looking in the rear view mirror and monthly reviews ended with us saying, “we did well, but we need to get to x (somehow).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without clear targets for each team and individual in the customer acquisition org, we couldn’t motivate the team, forecast growth, or determine which channels and initiatives to prioritize to hit our target in the shortest amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the previous 12 month performance by major customer acquisition (CA) function (Outbound, Events, Paid Inbound, and Earned Inbound), we could find the best opportunities for growth while giving clear targets to each team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, it’s essential to have reliable data. Since I previously built a &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;Revenue Dashboard&lt;/a&gt; that detailed our funnel metrics by major CA function already, I could begin to do some estimations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wrong way to forecast is to start with saying “Okay, we need to get to x in 12 months. What do we need to do to get there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I‘ve learned to to start with from the bottom up by identifying the inputs and levers that are in your control and what the results could be if you increased those inputs and pulled those levers over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1start-with-previousresults&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Start With Previous Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a new spreadsheet, I started with previous data broken down by the major CA functions I wanted to forecast by: Outbound, Events, Paid Inbound, Earned Inbound, and a total that rolls up all four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2define-your-inputs-and-levers-for-eachfunction&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Define Your Inputs and Levers for Each Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different functions will have different inputs and levers and you’ll have to determine what those are. Here’s what I went with at Chili Piper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;outbound&quot;&gt;Outbound&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inputs for cold Outbound were the (1) number of sales development reps (SDRs) and full-cycle account executives (AEs) and (2) the number of booked meetings we could reasonably expect each rep to book at full efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I knew how many reps we needed to hit a particular Outbound meeting goal and closed won revenue goal. Then we added an estimated ramp period and figured out what was possible with cold Outbound based on when and how many people we could afford to hire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cold outbound hiring plan and forecast.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cold outbound hiring plan and forecast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cold Outbound hiring plan and booked meeting forecast to hit goal in December ‘19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I knew what we could expect in Outbound meetings per month based on the number of each type of sales reps we had and if they were running at full efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next was to look at the levers, which I concluded to be (1) our conversion rates of each part of the funnel and (2) our average customer value (ACV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Levers can be adjusted for a ground up forecast.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Levers can be adjusted for a ground up forecast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue numbers are the levers. By pulling these levers, we could improve efficiency over time. Number of Goal Booked Meetings roll up from the inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why conversion rates and ACV? It’s what our sales team has most control of. For example, in April, I estimated our team would convert 75% of Outbound booked meetings into opportunities. The SDR is in control of setting qualified meetings and in control of the cadence and messaging to increase likelihood the prospect will attend the meeting. Next was estimating improvement in opportunity to closed-won conversion rates. It’s 16% in April and grows to 20% by June. We estimated this 25% improvement in just two months because we had already recognized this as an opportunity for improvement and implemented weekly training and call coaching to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Chili Piper’s product can be used by many different teams at a company and we have a variety of products, it’s difficult to estimate the potential value of an account. In the past, AEs have closed good-size companies in just a $300 deal (one product and one license), and other times deal sizes can be several thousand dollars when selling multiple products and many licenses up front. With training again, we were able to improve the ACV and expected it to continue to grow as skills improve and as we release more products throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing my methodology for Events, the inputs are (1) the number of events and (2) the number of expected meetings from each event. Working with our Events Manager, we were able to roughly plan out the rest of the year and set meeting goals for each event and attending sales rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Event booked meeting goals by sales rep. Meetings booked by “Other” are from non Sales team members.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Event booked meeting goals by sales rep. Meetings booked by “Other” are from non Sales team members.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The levers for Events are the same as Outbound, conversion rates and ACV; however, we didn’t forecast any change here since we already converted well from events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Goal Booked Meetings roll up from the inputs.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Number of Goal Booked Meetings roll up from the inputs.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paid-inbound&quot;&gt;Paid Inbound&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forecasting and goal setting for Paid Inbound is a bit tricky because the only true input fully in my control is spend, however with limited historical data, spend and cost-per-lead (CPL) by channel wasn’t the best place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, my inputs were the number of leads I could reasonably expect from each of the channels we’re currently using and plan to use in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inbound lead goal by channel for Paid Inbound.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Inbound lead goal by channel for Paid Inbound.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The levers for Inbound include conversion rates and ACV, but start with Leads and two additional conversion stages: Lead &amp;gt; Marketing Qualified Lead (MQL) and MQL to Booked Meeting (BM). For spend, I estimated the average total CPL and therefore determined the budget required for paid acquisition for the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Paid forecast broken down by channel.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Paid forecast broken down by channel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we didn’t have historical Paid &amp;amp; Earned Inbound metrics until May, Paid Inbound forecasts start in June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;earned-inbound&quot;&gt;Earned Inbound&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earned Inbound is even more trickier than Paid. For the most part, Earned Inbound is out of my direct control. Results come from a combination of activities done throughout the company. And since we didn’t have a marketing automation platform set up, we couldn’t yet determine the source of non paid leads, which could either be direct, organic, or referral. So unfortunately, there was much more guess work here and I simply estimated a growth in leads over time and the levers being the same as Paid Inbound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Estimated growth in Earned (non paid) leads over time.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Estimated growth in Earned (non paid) leads over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3making-thisuseful&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Making This Useful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each function’s goals had two tables below: (1) an auto updating “Actuals” table and (2) a table comparing the differences from Goal to Actual to visually see where we hit and missed goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Everything rolls up for a total customer acquisition forecast.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Everything rolls up for a total customer acquisition forecast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having all this data in one place was great for the leadership team to get a pulse check on all the teams in CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then because I built dashboards for &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;New Business Revenue&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/building-the-marketing-dashboard&quot;&gt;Marketing&lt;/a&gt;, and Outbound Sales, I could put an auto updating Trend and Goal column where each team could see what they were currently trending to as a team and individually and how that compared to the month’s Goal. This made it easy to see at any point during the month where we had to step up in order to hit goal. Here’s an example of what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-forecast-9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Forecast and goals by channel were added to each channel's dashboards.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Forecast and goals by channel were added to each channel's dashboards.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this was created, each team and individual now had goals and targets to hit every month that they could easily find on the dashboards they already used. This made it more simple to set everyone’s monthly OKRs, motivate the team, and let us rest easy by knowing that if we hit the month’s goal we were on our way to double growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Created an Automated Marketing Dashboard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/building-the-marketing-dashboard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Created an Automated Marketing Dashboard" /><published>2019-05-31T23:33:12-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-31T23:33:12-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/building-the-marketing-dashboard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/building-the-marketing-dashboard">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We weren’t tracking at a holistic level how much marketing was contributing to the business. We only had detailed marketing metrics for our main customer acquisition channel, LinkedIn. We couldn’t see all at once how many earned versus paid leads were generated month over month and all the down funnel metrics there after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made it impossible to &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;forecast and set goals&lt;/a&gt; realistically and on a per channel basis. Additionally, we couldn’t see down a level in detail how each individual paid channel was performing month over month, what each channel’s conversion rates were, and many other metrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After implementing a &lt;a href=&quot;/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system&quot;&gt;marketing attribution system&lt;/a&gt;, the next step was to build a marketing dashboard to segment leads and opportunities by channel. I wanted to build two main dashboards for marketing: point-in-time for goal setting and cohort (based on demo request date) for precisely measuring conversion rates and cost per win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what it looked like and what I wanted to measure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-mktg-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Chili Piper Marketing Dashboard.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New Chili Piper Marketing Dashboard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;Building The Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I could start writing formulas into a spreadsheet, I had to make sure we had accurate and complete data in Salesforce (SFDC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1redefining-salesstages&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Redefining Sales Stages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done when I first built a &lt;a href=&quot;/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets&quot;&gt;new business revenue dashboard&lt;/a&gt; for Chili Piper. I more clearly defined what our sales funnel stages were and set up date stamp process builders in SFDC for the important stage changes: demo request date, booked meeting data, and became an opportunity (opp) date (I used the native close date in SFDC). These dates are critical to record &lt;strong&gt;when&lt;/strong&gt; things actually happen, especially for when a deal became an ‘official’ opp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Chili Piper, we created an Opportunity object when a booked meeting had been set, therefore the SFDC Opportunity create date reflects the date a meeting was set and accepted, not when a true opp was reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided not to count a deal as an opp in our sales funnel until the prospect 1) showed up to their demo and 2) was qualified. Doing it this way helped us better understand the quality and give more meaning to an opp while also providing a more accurate AE conversion rates by eliminating no shows and disqualifieds — prospects that are impossible for an AE to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2setting-up-marketing-attribution-system&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Setting Up Marketing Attribution System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system&quot;&gt;creating an attribution system&lt;/a&gt; and implementing it for future leads across all channels, I updated our old leads and opps with the new format to make reporting easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3creating-the-salesforce-reports-and-importing-them-automatically-into-a-googlesheet&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Creating the Salesforce Reports and Importing Them Automatically into a Google Sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the formulas easier, I created two Opportunity, Lead, and Contact object reports for earned and paid. Then I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/gconnector_for_salesforce/971770431958&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;G-Connector&lt;/a&gt; to automatically import the reports into data tabs in the spreadsheet and refresh the data daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the data was in there, I could build the point-in-time and cohort views of our marketing performance and isolate performance between earned and paid and roll it up to a total. So now I could see how much pipeline and revenue earned and paid was generating in any given month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4creating-dashboards-for-each-marketing-channel&quot;&gt;Step 4 — Creating Dashboards for Each Marketing Channel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the marketing attribution naming conventions were standardized, it was easy to build separate dashboards for each channel, including an overall funnel view and one broken up by campaign, audience, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what that looked like for our biggest audience on LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-mktg-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Marketing attribution channel breadk down for LinkedIn ads&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Marketing attribution channel breadk down for LinkedIn ads&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran campaigns targeting specific titles in all marketing, sales, and customer success. I built another dashboard for each of these audiences broken down by individual titles. So for marketing for example, we had a full breakdown from spend to close won revenue for VP of Marketing, CMO, Director of Marketing, Demand Gen Marketers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This level of detail was also done for our other channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some of the action items this data helped drive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set goals:&lt;/strong&gt; I had pretty accurate historical customer acquisition performance by outbound, events, earned inbound, and paid inbound. Now I could &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;set a reasonable plan and forecast to double revenue&lt;/a&gt;. Then I dynamically populated the goal data by stage (column AE above) and measured how the current month was trending to our goals, giving us a heads up in the middle of the month where we needed to take action the most to hit our monthly goal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spot weak parts in the funnel:&lt;/strong&gt; It became immediately clear what channels were converting better than others. Then I listened to AE calls to get an understanding of why prospects weren’t converting as well as other channels. Earned inbound converted the best because they had previous knowledge of the product / company and had intent. Outbound and paid acquisition didn’t close as strong and we created more marketing collateral for sales to improve pain identification and value props of our products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimize spend:&lt;/strong&gt; Now that I could see how our advertising budget was performing by each campaign and audience with down funnel metrics, it became much easier to spot losing and winning audiences and optimize our spend for the biggest ROI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimize messaging:&lt;/strong&gt; So while making dashboards is great for high level analysis and reporting, it’s too time consuming to make reports on the fly. However, all of this data is in SFDC so it’s very fast to make ad-hoc reports in SFDC. For example, if I wanted to see how well a certain vale prop was performing in one channel, across all channels, or by persona, it could be done in minutes in SFDC. This helped drive which value props resonated the most with which personas which we drove our brand, content, and product messaging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Implemented Marketing Attribution Infrastructure (Last Touch)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Implemented Marketing Attribution Infrastructure (Last Touch)" /><published>2019-05-27T18:10:51-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T18:10:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/implementing-a-marketing-attribution-system">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first came onboard, we were running paid acquisition campaigns on just LinkedIn and Capterra. To measure their performance, we were using a separate form for each channel and just three URL tracking parameters: ppc_campaign, ppc_ad, and ppc_keyword without any kind of naming conventions in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using multiple forms is an easy way to separate channel performance easily, but the upkeep of them as more channels are added is cumbersome and becomes unnecessary with a proper attribution system in place. And without standard naming conventions for campaigns, content, and term, it can be difficult to scale tracking and measuring performance of content and angles across channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upgrading ppc_campaign, ppc_ad, and ppc_keyword to the full main five tracking parameters used in Google Analytics (source, medium, campaign, content, and term) provided us with a standardized attribution system we could use across channels. Then we just needed one form we could use on all of our landing pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we didn’t have a marketing automation platform or a marketing attribution platform, we decided to move forward with a simple last-touch attribution system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1create-marketing-attribution-fields-in-salesforce&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Create Marketing Attribution Fields in Salesforce&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we changed the three existing tracking fields to ‘Marketing Campaign,’ ‘Marketing Content,’ and ‘Marketing Term’. Then we added ‘Marketing Source’ and ‘Marketing Medium’. For marketing reporting purposes, we also added ‘Latest Demo Request Date’ and a ‘Demo Requested’ toggle we use to fire other automation. These fields were created on the Lead object in Salesforce (SFDC), the Contact, and the Opportunity (Opp).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-attribution-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;New marketing attribution fields in Salesforce.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New marketing attribution fields in Salesforce.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2creating-the-form-and-capturing-url-parameters&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Creating the Form and Capturing URL Parameters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using Clearbit Forms, which allow us to capture values from URL parameters natively. All I needed to do was create the hidden fields and map them to the parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-automating-the-data-flow-in-salesforce&quot;&gt;Step 3— Automating the Data Flow in Salesforce&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Lead is converted to a Contact and Account, we set up the attribution fields to be carried over to the Contact. When converted to an Opp, they also flow to the Opp where once created are frozen so they can’t be overwritten by a subsequent form submissions. This was set up because we wanted to credit the last marketing campaign that generated the Opp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4standardizing-naming-conventions-in-a-urlbuilder&quot;&gt;Step 4 — Standardizing Naming Conventions in a URL Builder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the foundation has been built, I could build a URL Builder tool in a Google Sheet and standardize naming conventions used for channels, campaigns, content, audiences etc. This is essential for being able to uncover what’s working what isn’t within a single channel over time and across channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one tab (data tab) was columns for source, medium, campaign, and term. I broke content up into five sub data points that all combined into one that was to be used for content. They were product, value/benefit, audience, media, and copy/ad variant. In the rows under each column were a list of values. For example, under source was google, linkedin, capterra, etc. Under value/benefit was connecting, conversion-rate, speed-to-lead. That way, in any future campaign in any channel, we could come back to using these naming conventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On another tab was the actual URL Builder. Each column used data validation from the data tab so my team and I could build tracking URLs using a series of dropdown menus and if something didn’t match it threw an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked liked this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--wide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-attribution-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;URL Builder in a spreadsheet for Chili Piper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;URL Builder in a spreadsheet for Chili Piper&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final cell combined all the data using simple CONCATENATE formulas and resulted in a tracking URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every campaign started was built using this URL builder that ensured consistent naming conventions for marketing attributions. This allowed us to build accurate marketing reports broken down by channel, audience, and campaign. It allowed us to view the success specific pieces of content, ads, media type, or angles across channels. And because it’s all in SFDC, we could do quick ad-hoc analysis using any combination of these parameters to see what’s working or not and drive strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automated Customer Acquisition Funnel and Revenue Reporting from SFDC to Google Sheets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automated Customer Acquisition Funnel and Revenue Reporting from SFDC to Google Sheets" /><published>2019-05-27T09:58:23-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T09:58:23-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/automating-new-business-revenue-reporting-into-google-sheets">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tended to view whether we had a good month or not on the customer acquisition (CA) side based purely on how much healthy open pipeline we had at the end of the month and how much revenue from new logos was generated. We didn’t really review (or set goals to) all the metrics in the funnel, such as leads, MQLs, booked meetings, opportunities, pipeline, disqualified, no show, closed-won, etc and broken down by the three major CA functions: inbound, outbound, and events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made it difficult to &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;set goals and forecast&lt;/a&gt;, and know by mid month what we were trending to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution was to build a spreadsheet that recorded each stage of the funnel for each CA function in both a point-in-time and a cohort view all updated automatically. With all the numbers available in one view, it became much easier to see how well each function of CA performed compared to previous months, spot low converting stages in our funnel, and find new opportunities to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-idata-cleanliness-in-salesforce&quot;&gt;Part I — Data Cleanliness in Salesforce&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1documenting-processes-for-opportunities&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Documenting Processes for Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the data needed to make this dashboard would be from the Opportunity (Opp) object in Salesforce (SFDC). We needed to enforce through documented processes when sales reps should be creating Opps (and when they shouldn’t), how to properly update Opps, and build in rules to make certain fields required depending on the Opp stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2redefining-sales-funnelstages&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Redefining Sales Funnel Stages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started out with a very simple sales funnel: leads &amp;gt; opportunities &amp;gt; close. We added an additional stage between leads and opportunities we called ‘Booked Meeting,’ which signified that the initial discovery call/demo was booked by a sales rep and is scheduled to run, but hasn’t yet. This is the first stage on the Opp we called ‘Demo.’ Even though it was an Opp object, we didn’t call it a true opportunity because the prospect could still no show or be disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This now meant when something was an opportunity, it means the prospect is qualified and had a successful discovery call/demo. Plus, the conversion rate of opportunity to closed-won/lost was now a much better indicator for an AE’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-creating-point-in-time-stage-changedates&quot;&gt;Step 3— Creating Point-in-Time Stage Change Dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, SFDC records the Opp creation date and close date, but this limits our flexibility and reporting options. We created a few process builders to record the Opp creation date into a separate field on the Opp called ‘Became a Booked Meeting On,’ which allowed us to change it if needed. Once an Opp moved from the initial stage of ‘Demo’ to a positive next stage, we time stamped the date to a field called “Became an Opportunity On.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--full gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-revenue-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Salesforce view of stage change date stamps.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Salesforce view of stage change date stamps.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iibuilding-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;Part II — Building the Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have good data on our Opp objects, I built dashboards in a Google Sheet to measure CA performance both by point-in-time (what happened during this month) and cohort (what happened to Opps created during this month).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1automating-data-into-googlesheets&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Automating Data Into Google Sheets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/gconnector_for_salesforce/971770431958&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;G-Connector&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to login to SFDC from a Google Sheet, find our Opp report, and schedule a daily import into a separate tab in the spreadsheet. I scheduled it to update once a night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2building-the-point-in-time-dashboard&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Building the Point-In-Time Dashboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the data is in the spreadsheet, building the layout of the spreadsheet and adding the formulas were pretty straightforward. On the point-in-tab view, I created a simple linear trend to predict where we’d be at the end of the month if our current pace continued then compared that trend tour goals. With visual formatting, this helped show where we need to pick up the pace at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the point-in-time view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-revenue-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Chili Piper Revenue Dashboard.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Chili Piper Revenue Dashboard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3building-the-cohortview&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Building the Cohort View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, the cohort view is the same as the point-in-time view, but instead of using our new ‘Became an Opportunity On’ and close date fields, we stuck with the our new ‘Became a Booked Meeting On’ field throughout the funnel. So this view would answer questions like, “of all the booked meetings generated in April 2019, how much pipeline and revenue did we generate from them?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the dashboard is complete and auto updating everyday, we have a very concise, high-level view of how each CA function is doing. Here’s three example scenarios our new revenue dashboard helped us understand instantly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When revenue is down one month, why?&lt;/strong&gt; We can check which CA function (inbound, outbound, events) had low revenue and find out answer there. Or perhaps it was down across the board, and we can see that our AE conversion rates are down. We could then implement extra training to help address this issue and get feedback from the AEs about what supporting collateral they could use to help close more deals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pipeline from inbound was low one month, why?&lt;/strong&gt; Since leads and booked meetings are the direct driver of pipeline for inbound, we can check whether booked meetings were down and if leads were down. If leads weren’t down, perhaps it was a lead quality issue we could look into. If leads were down, we could look at our &lt;a href=&quot;building-the-marketing-dashboard&quot;&gt;marketing dashboard&lt;/a&gt; to see which channels were down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re trending 10% above our pipeline goal this month, what’s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; By pulling in the current month’s &lt;a href=&quot;/created-a-forecast-model-to-double-customer-acquisition-growth&quot;&gt;goal numbers from our plan and forecast&lt;/a&gt;, we could see how well we’re doing compared to goal. This could be answered by looking at which function is over achieving on pipeline generation and figure out why from there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automated SalesLoft Cold Outbound Cadence Reporting into SFDC &amp;amp; Google Sheets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/automating-salesloft-cadence-metrics-into-google-sheets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automated SalesLoft Cold Outbound Cadence Reporting into SFDC &amp; Google Sheets" /><published>2019-05-26T20:04:01-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-26T20:04:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/automating-salesloft-cadence-metrics-into-google-sheets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/automating-salesloft-cadence-metrics-into-google-sheets">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reporting on how individual sales reps and their cadences were doing was a manual process. With Chili Piper being a data-driven company, we wanted to be able to make decisions backed by data, which meant we were tracking and manually updating over 37 metrics per rep and per cadence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data took a lot of time to update and would become outdated quickly, so it became a bottleneck for learning what pain points, value props, and angles worked best and also limited how quickly we could run new cadence experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how the old one looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-outbound-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Cold Outbound Dashboard.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Old Cold Outbound Dashboard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of great data recorded, but updated manually each week which became quickly outdated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to automate this process as much as possible if we wanted to learn what works faster and run experiments more frequently. This would also free up time we could then spend on improving our cold outbound strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making this could be broken down into three parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-i-measuring-activitydata&quot;&gt;Part I— Measuring Activity Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part was getting the general activity from SalesLoft (SL) into SFDC and then automating that into a Google Sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-1getting-salesloft-data-into-salesforce&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Getting SalesLoft Data Into Salesforce&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, SL has a native integration with SFDC which writes each email, call, and LinkedIn connect/InMail as an Activity to the Contact record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-2building-the-salesforce-reports&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Building the Salesforce Reports&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I needed to make an SFDC Activity report for each cadence. With the SL and SFDC integration, it was as simple as using a filter for the cadence name. Next was customizing the columns to include all the data we wanted to capture and report on. Once the first report was created, all we needed to do was copy the report, change the cadence name we were filtering for, and save as a new report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-3automating-the-salesforce-reports-into-googlesheets&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Automating the Salesforce Reports Into Google Sheets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/gconnector_for_salesforce/971770431958&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;G-Connector&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to login to SFDC from a Google Sheet, find our cadence reports, and schedule a daily import of each cadence we wanted to track as a separate tab in the spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-4building-the-dashboard&quot;&gt;Step 4 — Building the Dashboard&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most difficult part of this process was building the tab that pulled all the data from these cadence reports. Once all the formulas were created to get the data we wanted, we could simply copy the formulas into each subsequent column for the next cadence. Using another tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/advanced_find_and_replace/460077608560&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Advanced Find and Replace&lt;/a&gt;, we could quickly replace all the tab references inside each formula with another without having to edit each individual cell’s formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what this dashboard looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-outbound-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Cold Outbound Dashboard.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;New Cold Outbound Dashboard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With everything in SFDC, we could easily break out cadence metrics by the Contact level (individuals) and an Account level. So for instance, we could see how many unique accounts were targeted in a cadence versus just the total people. We could then expand on that and look at the bounce rate, open rate, reply rate, calls, connects, etc at an Account level or at a Contact level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Using conditional formatting, we could quickly see which cadences and reps were performing better than others, find out why, and scale that to future cadences and the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-iimeasuring-down-funnel-metrics&quot;&gt;Part II — Measuring Down-Funnel Metrics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the response rate of a cadence won’t tell us whether it’s a success or failure on its own, we needed to connect booked meetings, opportunities, pipeline, and ultimately closed-won deals to each cadence. To do this, we need to push cadence data from a Contact to an Opportunity object and then pull an Opportunity report into our spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-1push-salesloft-cadence-data-from-the-contact-to-an-opportunity&quot;&gt;Step 1 — Push SalesLoft Cadence Data From the Contact to an Opportunity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is possible using a process builder in SFDC. When an opportunity is created, the process builder will pull the SL cadence data from the Primary Contact and write it to the Opportunity. Then those fields are locked so any new SL activities to that Contact won’t overwrite on the Opportunity. That way, we know the cadence data on the Opportunity is the last meaningful activity that generated the booked meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-2building-the-salesforce-opportunity-report&quot;&gt;Step 2 — Building the Salesforce Opportunity Report&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple Opportunity report filtering for only outbound opportunities with SL cadence data in the columns is essentially all we needed. Then we automated this report to our spreadsheet using G-Connector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-3adding-down-funnel-metrics-into-the-dashboard-tab&quot;&gt;Step 3 — Adding Down-Funnel Metrics Into the Dashboard Tab&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with just simple COUNTIF formulas, we can see all the down-funnel metrics a cadence produced from booked meeting to close won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we looked at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-outbound-3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We could see the number of booked meetings and their outcomes down to win/lost segmented by cadence.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We could see the number of booked meetings and their outcomes down to win/lost segmented by cadence.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we were able to measure how effective a cadence was by the rate of accounts worked to meetings booked (and pipeline generated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-iiifiguring-out-whatworks&quot;&gt;Part III — Figuring Out What Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we’re able to pull in the cadence name and cadence step names into SFDC and onto Opportunities, we can add keywords (or tags) to each cadence step name to segment performance. So for instance, we can measure how certain angles or content (images, GIFs, etc) perform. This is additional information we used to build new and improved cadences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-imeasure-performance-of-eachemail&quot;&gt;Step I — Measure Performance of Each Email&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using strict cadence name and cadence step naming conventions, we were able to easily break out performance by each email step for every cadence with one formula. We simply looked if cadence step name contained “Email 1” or “Email 2” etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what that looks like with conditional formatting, to easily spot winning emails:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-outbound-4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Conditional formatting made it easy to spot wins.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Conditional formatting made it easy to spot wins.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-iiadd-keywords-to-each-cadencename&quot;&gt;Step II — Add Keywords to Each Cadence Name&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SL won’t retroactively update what’s sent to SFDC in the integration, so we were only able to segment out by keywords for future cadences. First we tested influence and persuasion angles and we were able to measure the open and response rate for emails in that cadence that used that angle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-outbound-5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Segmenting metrics out by keyword helped us further identify what content in email worked best.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Segmenting metrics out by keyword helped us further identify what content in email worked best.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-iiiadding-titles-of-the-contacts-whobooked&quot;&gt;Step III — Adding Titles of the Contacts Who Booked&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to measure a part of our outbound targeting, we looked at the roles of each contact who we booked a meeting with. Because each person’s title is somewhat unique, we just listed out the title in an array where we could visually inspect the kind of roles people had who resonated with our messaging and product, which we used for refining future targeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--vwide gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chili-outbound-6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;List of titles of prospects who booked a meeting helped confirm the type of prospects who best resonated with our messaging and value points.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;List of titles of prospects who booked a meeting helped confirm the type of prospects who best resonated with our messaging and value points.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all this data, we now could measure over 140 metrics per cadence per rep, automatically (mostly). This is how we were able to quickly test and evolve our outbound strategy and cadences to be more effective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Problem</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stop Comparing Yourself to Others — Use This Benchmark Instead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop Comparing Yourself to Others — Use This Benchmark Instead" /><published>2019-02-13T12:11:11-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T12:11:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stop-comparing-yourself-to-others">&lt;p&gt;The frequently given advice to not compare yourself with others and only to who you were yesterday never quite satisfied me. It still left a lot of questions unanswered and I recently discovered on Reddit many other people feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/productivity/comments/ao04vn/stop_comparing_yourself_to_others_and_start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent post on r/productivity&lt;/a&gt;, there were some top comments refuting this advice with how they actually like to use jealousy, greed, and wanting to be better than other people as motivation to achieve “greatness.” Not only is comparing yourself to others the wrong way to achieve true greatness, so is comparing yourself to who you were yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being better than who you were yesterday should be the bare minimum you strive for, because it doesn’t allow you to achieve what you’re fully capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it doesn’t confirm you’re on the right path to begin with. On its own, “compare yourself to who you were yesterday” is only feel-good advice that has very little practical usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why there’s some rationality behind why we tend to compare ourselves to others. You can see in your physical or digital circle who the low achievers are and who the high achievers are — giving you the missing benchmark of effort and success. But in the end, it’s a terrible benchmark that will have devastating effects on your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparing-yourself-to-others-leads-you-to-falsepaths&quot;&gt;Comparing Yourself to Others Leads You to False Paths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, I was introduced to and befriended a very successful guy who day traded for a living. I didn’t know anything about the world of finance, but seeing the success he had and hearing how much he would make in any given day was exhilarating. &lt;strong&gt;As time went on, my benchmark for effort and success expanded to include his. I began to compare what I had achieved to him. “Success” now meant nothing short of what he had achieved.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told myself I needed to do everything I could to achieve that level of success. I decided to learn how to be a day trader and I went so far as to sell my dream car to get the cash to do it. With studying and his mentorship, I started to make a few hundred dollars per week. As my confidence and greed grew, I became less risk-averse. &lt;strong&gt;Half a year later, my losses totaled close to $10k.&lt;/strong&gt; I closed my account and threw my dreams of riches and day trading out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started to compare myself to him, and what I had to what he had, it led me to abandon my path and join the path that made him successful. I never had any prior interest in stocks or studied the financial markets. I was just chasing the money and that led to disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Using others as a benchmark for success can lead to conformity — it can take you away from what you’re happy and good at doing and put you on a false path — chasing money, status, or attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a never ending trap. There will always be someone to compare yourself to with more money, more status, and more fame that will lead you off your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everyone gets one life. Yours is almost used up, and instead of treating yourself with respect, you have entrusted your own happiness to the souls of others.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-fate-and-luck-always-play-a-significant-role-in-someones-success&quot;&gt;Understand Fate and Luck Always Play a Significant Role in Someone’s Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us is a completely unique individual with a unique genetic makeup. We’re all raised by different people, with different values, and in different environments — all of which significantly impact our character and what we do in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will shout, “you can do anything you set your mind to” or “you just need to work harder” or “you’re not sacrificing enough.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/u/65e0b0f45be5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nat Eliason&lt;/a&gt; made some noise when he called out Gary Vaynerchuk as an example of someone who does this in a piece he wrote titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@nateliason/no-more-struggle-porn-202153a01108&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;No More “Struggle Porn.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While we do need to have ruthless discipline to reach our greatest potential, we cannot ignore the limits imposed on us by the cards we’re dealt or we will forever be dissatisfied with who we are and what we’ve accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another reason why it doesn’t make sense to compare ourselves to others: luck. &lt;strong&gt;No one’s success is ever only down to luck, but we can’t ignore the role luck plays in success as an “x” factor — it’s unmanageable and unpredictable.&lt;/strong&gt; The only thing in your control is to continually put yourself in positions to catch lucky breaks. And remember: luck is not distributed evenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Q&amp;amp;A with White House interns, President Obama gave advice on the subject luck has with success and what to focus on instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A lot of times, it’s just happenstance. Or things work out. But being useful? And having a satisfying life? And making a contribution? That is entirely within your control. Orient yourself towards having an impact and making a difference. And you will and you’ll be happy doing it.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Former President Barack Obama, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5IDQDoxXHm0?start=516&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instead-of-comparing-yourself-to-others-or-who-you-were-yesterday-find-your-truepath&quot;&gt;Instead of Comparing Yourself to Others Or Who You Were Yesterday, Find Your True Path&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity is worthless if you’re on a false path. Your goal and motivation shouldn’t be about just being the best or better than the people in your circles, but creating something useful that can make a difference in peoples’ lives and your community. This is the truest benchmark for success and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People who labor all their lives but have no purpose to direct every thought and impulse toward are wasting their time — even when hard at work.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your true path is doing what you were made for — what you feel you have an inclination and natural ability for. This inclination is a reflection of your unique genetic code, deep underlying preferences for particular activities or forms of expression. When you find your true path, you’ll be less inclined to compare your success with someone else. &lt;strong&gt;You will quickly realize their path isn’t a good fit for you.&lt;/strong&gt; And you won’t be as inclined to envy their money, attention, or whatever, because craving those things is a false path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the end, the money and success that truly last come not to those who focus on such things as goals, but rather to those who focus on mastery and fulfilling their Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Robert Greene, &lt;a href=&quot;/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need to compare yourself to others is restrained when you’re happy and comfortable with who you are, which comes from being on your true path and working on your Life’s Task. You will no longer envy other peoples’ success and happiness, and you will instead be laser-focused on your own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Don’t aim at success — the more you aim at it and make it a target, the more you are going to miss it. For success, like happiness, cannot be pursued; it must ensue, and it only does so as the unintended side-effect of one’s dedication to a cause greater than oneself…”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Viktor Frankl, Man’s Search for Meaning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can’t be disciplined, happy, and confident all the time. I’ve made journaling a daily habit of mine to give myself the opportunity to reflect on and ground my thoughts. It’s an exercise that has helped me live a more level-headed and purposeful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Inspired by the journal method of Marcus Aurelius.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/stoic-journal-topics&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/stoic-journal-topics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;stoic journal topics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ignoring what goes on in other people’s souls — no one ever came to grief that way. But if you won’t keep track of what your own soul’s doing, how you can you not be unhappy?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing yourself to others is a recipe for disaster. Comparing yourself to who you were yesterday is a recipe for passivity. Life is not about being better than other people. It’s not about achieving more than people in our circles. &lt;strong&gt;Life is about being useful to others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">The frequently given advice to not compare yourself with others and only to who you were yesterday never quite satisfied me. It still left a lot of questions unanswered and I recently discovered on Reddit many other people feel the same way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="20 Stoic Journal Topics for Self-Development" /><published>2019-02-07T06:52:48-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T06:52:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stoic-journal-topics">&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, often called the philosopher emperor, is a famous stoic philosopher and known as the last good emperor of Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of his journal entries to himself have been recovered and curated into a single book title Meditations, which is widely recognized as one of the most influential pieces of stoic philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of journaling allowed Marcus Aurelius, and can allow us today, to think more clearly and live a more virtuous life. The following journal topics can help guide your journaling practice toward stoic thought exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-gratitude&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Gratitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a moment to reflect on the value added to your life by the people around you will help you appreciate them and the relationship you have with them, which in turn could spark behavior that strengthens those relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People to consider: significant other, family, friends, coworkers, and people who’ve impacted your life in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value has [person] added to my life? What wisdom, achievements, or fortunate events of mine can I give them some credit for?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value do I (or can I) add to [person’s] life in return?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does [person] affect and influence my life decisions, feelings, and behavior?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What characteristics does [person] have that I admire?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are my best characteristics who influenced me to develop them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also reflect on your achievements, major events, and material things in your life to establish gratitude for you’ve done and what you have, which will suppress feelings of unhappiness and cravings for new and better things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is an accomplishment I’m very proud of? Why am I proud of it? What can I do to do more things like that?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is one of my most cherished memories and why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of an item in your possession you want to upgrade. Is your current item functioning well enough? What do you appreciate about it? What sustained value will an upgrade add to your life?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at what you have and the things you value most. How much would you crave them if you didn’t have them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-to-suppress-negative-thoughts&quot;&gt;Journal Topics to Suppress Negative Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negative and low value thoughts are fuel for chaos, passivity, and unhappiness. These topics can help control your negative thoughts by thinking through them rationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Like seeing roasted meat and other dishes in front of you and suddenly realizing: This is a dead fish. A dead bird. A dead pig. Or that this noble vintage is grape juice,… Perceptions like that — latching onto things and piercing through them, so we see what they really are. That’s what we need to do all the time… to lay them bare and see how pointless they are…”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of an item you craved to have and eventually purchased. How do you feel about that item now? Was the craving warranted?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you really want to buy right now? What value will that add to your life? What value will be lost if you don’t buy it? Is there a better use for the money you would have to spend to acquire it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of something you‘ve done that you regret. Write an apology to yourself and a response of forgiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-improving-your-character&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Improving Your Character&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his journal, it was apparent that Marcus Aurelius wrote about recurring philosophical tenets in order to continually practice his philosophy. Try doing the same for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To feel grief, anger, or fear is to try to escape from something decreed by the ruler of all things, now or in the past or in the future. And that ruler is law, which governs what happens to each of us. To feel grief or anger or fear is to become a fugitive — a fugitive from justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of a philosophical or ethical tenet that you struggle to live by. Write down the tenet and again in your own words. Try crafting your own analogy. Do this as often as you need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of someone you admire. Write yourself advice you think they would give you from their point-of-view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of 12 year-old you. What “secrets of life” have you acquired that you would want to share with yourself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;journal-topics-for-daily-reflection--improvement&quot;&gt;Journal Topics for Daily Reflection &amp;amp; Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our daily behavior is the best indicator of the type of person we are. Work on improving what you do each day and you will in turn be improving the type of person you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Remember that our own worth is measured by what we devote our energy to.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius, &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;Meditations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;counter-reset&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I lose control of my emotions today? What triggered it? Was that a reasonable response?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I do today that was out of character? What triggered it? Was that a reasonable response?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did you do today that was not a good use of your time?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you miss accomplishing an important habit or step in your routine today? What do you think was the reason for it and how can you prevent it from happening again?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I crave today? Describe what you craved in its most simplistic form. Did it warrant that level of craving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Make New Habits Stick When Motivation Runs Out&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The 6 best tips from Atomic Habits on building habits that last&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-make-habits-stick&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how to make new habits stick.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;how to make new habits stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to Break Bad Habits for Good&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The best tips from Atomic Habits on breaking your worse habits&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/how-to-break-bad-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/how-to-break-bad-habits.png&quot; alt=&quot;how to break bad habits&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“Done” App Review: My Favorite Habit Tracker&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;And one you’ll actually stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/done-review-of-my-favorite-habit-tracking-app&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/done-app-review.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;done app review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Marcus Aurelius, often called the philosopher emperor, is a famous stoic philosopher and known as the last good emperor of Rome.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mastery by Robert Greene — Summary, Notes, + Quotes" /><published>2019-02-05T22:48:39-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-05T22:48:39-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mastery-summary-quotes-robert-greene">&lt;p&gt;Mastery by Robert Greene is a practical read on helping people find and pursue their Life’s Task (purpose).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally felt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt; was a bit disorganized at times, which was especially apparent looking back at my notes. So below are quotes and thoughts that stuck out to me in the best order I could provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure no-dark-filter figure--sml gtc-1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mastery.png&quot; alt=&quot;Buy Mastery on Amazon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot;&gt;Buy Mastery on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-mastery-and-why-pursueit&quot;&gt;What is Mastery and Why Pursue It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mastery — the feeling that we have a greater command of reality, other people, and ourselves. Although it might be something we experience for only a short while, for others — Masters of their field — it becomes their way of life, their way of seeing the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pursuit of mastery is the pursuit of purpose, whatever your Life’s Task, as Greene refers to it, may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is not mastery for the purpose of dominating nature or other people, but for determining our fate… You are contributing to the most important cause of all — the survival and prosperity of the human race, in a time of stagnation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because being on the path of mastery requires discipline and a strong work ethic towards a craft you enjoy, you will be working towards something great and something you can be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;James Clear points out your daily habits define who you are in Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;, Greene also says pursuing mastery is important because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…people get the mind and quality of brain that they deserve through their actions in life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road to mastery can be defined by three phases and Mastery goes into depth on each phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apprenticeship — you’re a student learning from others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative-Active — you’re a practitioner, adding your own creativity and style to your craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mastery — you have complete command of the craft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”[Masters] excel by their ability to practice harder and move faster through the process, all of this stemming from the intensity of their desire to learn and from the deep connection they feel to their field of study. And at the core of this intensity of effort is in fact a quality that is genetic and inborn — not talent or brilliance, which is something that must be developed, but rather a deep and powerful inclination toward a particular subject.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masters become masters not because they seek fame, money, or an outcome, but because they’re obsessed with their craft. There are no shortcuts to mastery. It takes time. It takes effort. There will be failures along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-most-people-dont-achieve-mastery-in-their-lives&quot;&gt;Why Most People Don’t Achieve Mastery in Their Lives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A natural response when people feel overwhelmed is to retreat into various forms of passivity… The less we attempt, the less chances of failure. If we can make it look like we are not really responsible for our fate, for what happens to us in life, then our apparent powerlessness is more palatable. For this reason we become attracted to certain narratives: it is genetics that determines much of what we do; we are just products of our times…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are born into a reality that has existed before us with masters already present. We see them online, in TV, we read about them. When we start working toward a particular field, we learn who the masters are already. It’s easy to become envious and to think, “I’ll never be as good, as famous, as well liked by the community. They were born with more natural talent. Why should I try too hard?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the attitude of most people and it can have devastating consequences toward your Life’s Task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This [attitude] can diminish your levels of effort and discipline below the point of effectiveness. Conforming to social norms, you will listen more to others than to your own voice. You may choose a career path based on what peers and parents tell you, or on what seems lucrative. If you lose contact with this inner calling, you can have some success in life, but eventually your lack of true desire catches up with you. Your work becomes mechanical. You come to live for leisure and immediate pleasures. In this way you become increasingly passive, and never move past the first phase. You may grow frustrated and depressed, never realizing that the source of it is your alienation from your own creative potential.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you get past this passive attitude? For one, you must find your Life’s Task — your natural inclination towards a particular field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This intense connection and desire allows them to withstand the pain of the process — the self doubts, the tedious hours of practice and stuffy, the inevitable setbacks, the endless barbs from the envious. They develop a resiliency and confidence that others lack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you know you Life’s Task, you can work through inevitable roadblocks, challenges, and failures. You will find it easier to get back up again, to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discovering-your-calling-the-lifestask&quot;&gt;Discovering Your Calling: The Life’s Task&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a difference between wishing you were a master at something, and wishing you were doing something to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…he didn’t care so much about the finished product; it was the search and process in creating something that had always excited him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to love the work. You have to feel a profound connection to it. You must be obsessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Work is often seen as a means for making money so we can enjoy that second life that we lead.… This is a depressing attitude, because in the end we spend a substantial part of our waking life at work. If we experience this time as something to get through on the way to real pleasure, then our hours at work represent a tragic waste of the short time we have to live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you find work that you love to do, it doesn’t feel like work is something you have to do to live, but an opportunity to create something beyond yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find work you like, Greene recommends trying various fields you’ve always been interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Eventually, you will hit upon a particular field, niche, or opportunity that suits you perfectly. You will recognize it when you find it because it will spark that childlike sense of wonder and excitement; it will feel right. Once found, everything will fall into place. You will learn more quickly and more deeply. Your skill level will reach a point where you will be able to claim your independence from within the group you work for and move out on your own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you grow older as an adult, it’s harder to find these natural inclinations. For years, we’ve already been influenced by the culture we live in, our peers, our family, the influencers we look up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You must dig for signs of such inclinations in your earliest years. Look for its traces in visceral reactions to something simple; a desire to repeat an activity that you never tired of; a subject that stimulated an unusual degree of curiosity; feelings of power attached to particular actions… You have nothing to create; you merely need to dig and refine what has been buried inside of you all along. If you reconnect with this core at any age, some element of that primitive attraction will spark back to life, indicating a path that can ultimately become your Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you find this inclination, practice journaling and reflecting on your feelings toward different types of work and ask yourself why you feel this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Become who you are by learning who you are.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pindar, Ancient Greek poet&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you allow yourself to learn who you really are by paying attention to that voice and force within you, then you can become what you were fated to become — an individual, a Master.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a two pathways you can take for finding your field. First, find a deep narrow niche in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”[once you’ve found a field you like] …look for side paths that particularly attract you… When it is possible, you make a move to this narrower field. You continue this process until you eventually hit upon a totally unoccupied niche, the narrower the better. In some ways, this niche corresponds to your uniqueness…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can combine two entirely different fields into one and create a new category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Once you have mastered your first field, you look for other subjects or skills that you can conquer, on your own time if necessary. You can now combine this added field of knowledge to the original one, perhaps creating a new field, or at least making novel connections between them. You continue this process as long as you wish… Ultimately you create a field that is uniquely your own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know you’re on the path of your Life’s Task, don’t let anything stand in the way — nothing is more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In dealing with your career and its inevitable change, you must think in the following way: You are not tied to a particular position; your loyalty is not to career or a company. You are committed to your Life’s Task, to giving it full expression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t let the field itself to evolve beneath you and leave you behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…it is up to you to foresee the changes going on right now in your profession. You must adapt your Life’s Task to these circumstances. You do not hold on to past ways of doing things. Because that will ensure you will fall behind and suffer for it. You are flexible and always looking to adapt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be lured to other paths that seem easier or more lucrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The road to mastery requires patience. You will have to keep your focus on five or ten years down the road, when you will reap the rewards of your efforts… In the end, the money and success that truly last come not to those who focus on such things as goals, but rather to those who focus on mastery and fulfilling their Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…direct yourself toward the small things you are good at. Do not dream or make grand plans for the future, but instead concentrate on becoming proficient at these simple and immediate skills. This will bring you confidence and become a base from which you can expand to other pursuits. Proceeding in this way, step by step, you will hit upon your Life’s Task.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-i-submit-to-reality-the-ideal-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;Phase I. Submit to Reality: The Ideal Apprenticeship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apprenticeship phase begins when you’ve identified the particular field you have a deep interest and inclination for. You may not have found exactly your Life’s Task, but you’re on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-best-kind-of-apprenticeships&quot;&gt;The Best Kind of Apprenticeships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the goal of an apprenticeship is not money, a good position, a title, or a diploma, but rather the transformation of your mind and character — the first transformation on the way to mastery. You enter a career as an outsider.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start an apprenticeship that offers the best opportunities for learning. Sometimes this means accepting the lowest position at a good company. It would be a mistake to seek out the best pay if it’s at a company that won’t mold you to be an expert in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must value learning above everything else.… opt for the situation that will give you the most opportunities to learn, particularly with hands-on work.… choose a place that has people and mentors who can inspire and teach you. A job with mediocre pay has the added benefit of training you to get by with less — a valuable life skill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentors who you can learn from are essential to your career and skill growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Practical knowledge… is what will pay you dividends for decades to come — far more than the paltry increase in pay you might receive at some seemingly lucrative position that offers fewer learning opportunities. This means that you move toward challenges that will toughen and improve you, where you will get the most objective feedback on your performance and progress. You do not choose apprenticeships that seem easy and comfortable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid of a challenging job with low pay. Your reward in an apprenticeship is not money — it is in skills and character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-you-do-when-you-have-an-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;What You Do When You Have an Apprenticeship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting an apprenticeship, a good attitude is an essential foundation for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You are naïve and full of misconceptions about this new world. Your head is full of dreams and fantasies about the future. Your knowledge of the world is subjective, based on emotions, insecurities, and limited experience. Slowly, you will ground yourself in reality, in the objective world represented by the knowledge and skills that make people successful in it. You will learn how to work with others and handle criticism. In the process you will transform yourself from someone who is impatient and scattered into someone who is disciplined and focused, with a mind that can handle complexity. In the end, you will master yourself and all of your weaknesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep a humble a mind and to not attempt to rise to the top. At some points, you may think you know everything and that you’re ready to go out on your own, but you will see there is a lot to learn before proceeding to the next phase of adding your own style and ideas to the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The greatest mistake you can make in the initial months of your apprenticeship is to imagine that you have to get attention, impress people, and prove yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“These thoughts will dominate your mind and close it off from the reality around you. Any positive attention you receive is deceptive; it is not based on your skills or anything real, and it will turn against you. Instead, you will want to acknowledge the reality and submit to it, muting your colors and keeping in the background as much as possible, remaining passive and giving yourself the space to observe. You will also want to drop any preconceptions you might have about this world you are entering. If you impress people in these first months, it should be because of the seriousness of your desire to learn, not because you are trying to rise to the top before you are ready.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to impress in any way other than through your hard work, determination, and desire to learn. You need to learn your new environment inside and out. How companies in the field work, even at the levels above you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the ability to observe any unfamiliar environment will become a critical lifelong skill. You will develop the habit of stilling your ego and looking outward instead of inward. You will see in any encounter what most people miss because they are thinking of themselves. You will cultivate a keen eye for human psychology, and strengthen your ability to focus… This will be a very important skill for the next, creative phase in life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By being able to critically observe all aspects of your environment, you will be able to make better decisions with your work by seeing the whole picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to accept that apprenticeships will require monotonous and tedious work. This is something you will have to push through and embrace. Even if you don’t think you have anything left to learn, you will learn the power of disciple — the ability to do what you know needs to be done even when your body and mind don’t want you to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discipline-and-the-resistance-practice&quot;&gt;Discipline and the Resistance Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”[The Resistance Practice means] you go in the opposite direction of all of your natural tendencies when it comes to practice. First, you resist the temptation to be nice to yourself. You become your own worst critic; you see your work as if through the eyes of others. You recognize your weaknesses, precisely the elements you are not good at.… Second, you resist the lure of easing up on your focus. You train yourself to concentrate in practice with double the intensity, as if it were the real thing times two. In devising your own routines, you become as creative as possible. You invent exercises that work upon your weaknesses. You give yourself arbitrary deadlines to meet certain standards, constantly pushing yourself past perceived limits. In this way you develop your own standards for excellence, generally higher than those of others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is a super power. If you can develop strong discipline, you can consistently do the work required to be on the path for mastery and success. Set high standards for yourself, even if your friends, peers, or even family think you’re crazy. They most likely won’t have the same levels of expectations for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Mistakes and failures are precisely your means of education. They tell you about your own inadequacies. It is hard to find out such things from people, as they are often political with their praise and criticisms. Your failures also permit you to see the flaws of your ideas, which are only revealed in the execution of them. You learn what your audience really wants, the discrepancy between your ideas and how they affect the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one becomes a master with 100% perfect record. It is okay to fail because with patience and time, you will recover and grow even more skillful and stronger due to those learning experiences. Be the own judge of your quality — coworkers and even bosses will not say as much as they think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You want to learn as many skills as possible, following the direction that circumstances lead you to, but only if they are related to your deepest interests. Like a hacker, you value the process of self-discovery and making things that are of the highest quality. You avoid the trap of following one set career path. You are not sure where this will all lead, but you are taking full advantage of the openness of information, all of the knowledge about skills now at our disposal. You see what kind of work suits you and what you want to avoid at all cost. You move by trial and error.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning lots of different skills allows you to combine different skills later in life, and get you closer to discovering your Life’s Task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You are not wandering about because you are afraid of commitment, but because you are expanding your skill base and your possibilities. At a certain point, when you are ready to settle on something, ideas and opportunities will inevitably present themselves to you. When that happens, all of the skills you have accumulated will prove invaluable. You will be the Master at combining them in ways that are unique and suited to your individuality. You may settle on this one place or idea for several years, accumulating in the process even more skills, then move in a slightly different direction when the time is appropriate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching work like this will keep you from finding yourself locked in a boring career and instead provide opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;big-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The very desire to find shortcuts makes you eminently unsuited for any kind of mastery.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;absorb-the-masters-power-the-mentordynamic&quot;&gt;Absorb the Master’s Power: The Mentor Dynamic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the apprenticeship phase, it’s critical to find and work under a master as a mentee. With their experience, they can guide you on the right path and help you grow your skills far faster than you could alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best mentor-mentee relationships are with people you work with on a daily basis, such as your manager. If your direct manager isn’t a suitable mentee, then possibly another leader at your company you have the ability to interact with. If no one at your workplace is suitable, find a better company or the next best thing is finding a mentor online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To learn requires a sense of humility. We must admit that there are people out there who know our field much more deeply than we do. Their superiority is not a function of natural talent or privilege, but rather of time and experience. Their authority in the field is not based on politics or trickery. It is very real.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect masters for what they have accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Even if we have teachers in our lives, we tend not to pay full attention to their advice, often preferring to do things our own way. In fact, we come to believe that being critical of Masters or teachers is somehow a sign of our intelligence, and that being a submissive pupil is a sign of weakness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a huge mistake to think you know better than a master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As the relationship progresses you can make this absorption process more conscious and direct, questioning them about the principles underlying their way of doing things. If you are clever,… getting them to analyze their own creativity for you, and mining all kinds of rich ideas in the process. They are often grateful for the opportunity to reveal the inner workings of their power, particularly to someone they do not perceive as a threat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-people-as-they-are-the-social-intelligence&quot;&gt;See People As They Are: The Social Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat the work you do, no matter how small the job and responsibility is as art — as a demonstration of your craft. But don’t do it alone. When appropriate, bring other people in, be open to feedback, and create something together to make not just yourself win, but others with you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…your work is the single greatest means at your disposal for expressing your social intelligence. By being efficient and detail oriented in what you do, you demonstrate that you are thinking of the group at large and advancing its cause. By making what you write or present clear and easy to follow, you show your care for the audience or public at large. By involving other people in your projects and gracefully accepting their feedback, you reveal your comfort with the group dynamic. Work that is solid also protects you from the political conniving and malevolence of others — it is hard to argue with the results you produce. If you are experiencing the pressures of political maneuvering within the group, do not lose your head and become consumed with all of the pettiness. By remaining focused and speaking socially through your work, you will both continue to raise your skill level and stand out among all the others who make a lot of noise but produce nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your work speak for yourself while others around you try to get ahead by playing political games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also keep up a healthy appearance. Even if you don’t think it’s true, people are and will judge you based on your appearance. Use this to your advantage by crafting an appearance that portrays the character you want to be known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…turn this dynamic around by consciously molding these appearances, creating the image that suits you, and controlling people’s judgments. At times you will find it appropriate to stand back and create some mystery around you, heightening your presence. At other times you will want to be more direct and impose a more specific appearance. In general, you never settle on one image or give people the power to completely figure you out. You are always one step ahead of the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t go too far in trying to always persuade and figure out what the people around you are thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In dealing with fools you must adopt the following philosophy: they are simply a part of life, like rocks or furniture. All of us have foolish sides. Moments in which we lose our heads and think more of our ego or short-term goals. It is human nature. Seeing this foolishness within you, you can then accept it in others. This will allow you to smile at their antics, to tolerate their presence as you would a silly child. And to avoid the madness of trying to change them. It is all part of the human comedy, and it is nothing to get upset about or lose sleep over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius’s stoic philosophy also teaches this mindset in dealing with other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h5&gt;RECOMMENDED&lt;/h5&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-ii-awaken-the-dimensional-mind-the-creative-active&quot;&gt;Phase II. Awaken the Dimensional Mind: The Creative-Active&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Dimensional Mind has two essential requirements: one, a high level of knowledge about a field or subject; and two, the openness and flexibility to use this knowledge in new and original ways.… Once the mind is freed from having to learn these basics, it can focus on higher, more creative matters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dimensional Mind is a concept that combines knowledge and skepticism — having deep knowledge about a particular subject, but not so set in stone in order to be open to new ideas and perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-how-to-obtain-a-dimensional-mind&quot;&gt;Here’s How to Obtain a Dimensional Mind:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…first, choosing the proper Creative Task, the kind of activity that will maximize our skills and knowledge; second, loosening and opening up the mind through certain Creative Strategies; and third, creating the optimal mental conditions for a Breakthrough or Insight. Finally, throughout the process we must also be aware of the Emotional Pitfalls — complacency, boredom, grandiosity, and the like — that continually threaten to derail or block our progress. If we can move through the steps while avoiding these traps, we cannot fail to unleash powerful creative forces from within.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat all your work like art. Hone your craft. Do not think about false goals like money or fame, but focus on creating the best thing you’re capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you go at your work with half a heart, it will show in the lackluster results and in the laggard way in which you reach the end. If you are doing something primarily for money and without a real emotional commitment, it will translate into something that lacks a soul and that has no connection to you. You may not see this, but you can be sure that the public will feel it and that they will receive your work in the same lackluster spirit it was created in. If you are excited and obsessive in the hunt, it will show in the details. If your work comes from a place deep within, its authenticity will be communicated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very difficult to even think about “going down” in your level of lifestyle, but to achieve mastery, you can’t be afraid of that happening. You most likely will have to make some sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must let go of your need for comfort and security. Creative endeavors are by their nature uncertain. You may know your task, but you are never exactly sure where your efforts will lead. If you need everything in your life to be simple and safe, this open-ended nature of the task will fill you with anxiety. If you are worried about what others might think and about how your position in the group might be jeopardized, then you will never really create anything.… your ideas will grow stale and flat. If you are worried about failure or going through a period of mental and financial instability,… your worries will be reflected in the results. Think of yourself as an explorer. You cannot find anything new if you are unwilling to leave the shore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the challenging path of mastery worth it? Because we don’t get anywhere near the same level of satisfaction from exercising our creativity as anything else. It defines who we are. It makes an impact on our community; to the human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Engaged in the creative process we feel more alive than ever, because we are making something and not merely consuming, Masters of the small reality we create. In doing this work, we are in fact creating ourselves. Although it involves much pain, the pleasure that comes from the overall process of creativity is of an intensity that makes us want to repeat it. That is why creative people return again and again to such endeavors, despite all of the anxiety and doubt they stir up. It is nature’s way of rewarding us for the effort; if we had no such rewards, people would not engage in such activity, and mankind would suffer irreparably from this loss. This pleasure will be your reward as well, to whatever degree you pursue the process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With discipline, good work, and time, your skills will grow towards Mastery. And if time is a part of the process, then the more time you have, the more your skills will grow. Time, therefore is an ally. Have patience. By trying to rush to the next level quickly, you’re removing time from the equation and therefore decreasing your skill output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must come to embrace slowness as a virtue in itself. When it comes to creative endeavors, time is always relative. Whether your project takes months or years to complete, you will always experience a sense of impatience and a desire to get to the end. The single greatest action you can take for acquiring creative power is to reverse this natural impatience. You take pleasure in the laborious research process; you enjoy the slow cooking of the idea, the organic growth that naturally takes shape over time. You do not unnaturally draw out the process, which will create its own problems (we all need deadlines), but the longer you can allow the project to absorb your mental energies, the richer it will become. Imagine yourself years in the future looking back at the work you have done. From that future vantage point, the extra months and years you devoted to the process will not seem painful or laborious at all. It is an illusion of the present that will vanish. Time is your greatest ally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fuse-the-intuitive-with-the-rational-mastery&quot;&gt;Fuse the Intuitive With the Rational: Mastery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the path to Mastery, it’s important to lose sight of your goal. Mindset is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…you must also maintain a sense of destiny, and feel continuously connected to it. You are unique, and there is a purpose to your uniqueness. You must see every setback, failure, or hardship as a trial along the way, as seeds that are being planted for further cultivation, if you know how to grow them. No moment is wasted if you pay attention and learn the lessons contained in every experience. By constantly applying yourself to the subject that suits your inclinations and attacking it from many different angles, you are simply enriching the ground for these seeds to take root. You may not see this process in the present, but it is happening. Never losing your connection to your Life’s Task, you will unconsciously hit upon the right choices in your life. Over time, mastery will come to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerful tool as you face increasing challenges is learning how to manage stress and anxiety — and even better, learn how to use it to your advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We must learn how to quiet the anxiety we feel whenever we are confronted with anything that seems complex or chaotic. In our journey from apprenticeship to mastery we must patiently learn the various parts and skills that are required, never looking too far ahead. In moments of perceived crisis, we must develop the habit of maintaining our cool and never overreacting. If the situation is complex and others are reaching for simple black-and-white answers, or for the usual conventional responses, we must make a point of resisting such a temptation. We maintain our Negative Capability and a degree of detachment. What we are doing is gaining a tolerance and even a taste for chaotic moments, training ourselves to entertain several possibilities or solutions. We are learning to manage our anxiety, a key skill in these chaotic times.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path to mastery is a long road. Temptations to abandon your path will come from all angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The problem is that we humans are deep conformists. Those qualities that separate us are often ridiculed by others, or criticized by teachers.… anything that is peculiar to our makeup is precisely what we must pay the deepest attention to and lean on in our rise to mastery. Mastery is like swimming — it is too difficult to move forward when we are creating our own resistance or swimming against the current. Know your strengths and move with them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing in mastery is to stay true to who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Your false self is the accumulation of all the voices you have internalized from other people — parents and friends who want you to conform to their ideas of what you should be like and what you should do, as well as societal pressures to adhere to certain values that can easily seduce you. It also includes the voice of your own ego, which constantly tries to protect you from unflattering truths.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Greene is my one my favorite writers because the way he likes to weave historical stories into practical advice. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007V65PBK/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=victoriou-20&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007V65PBK&amp;amp;linkId=16f9945504940eb7c0e610c9227d3907&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt;, Greene helps people find their purpose in life, which he thinks is better called your Life’s Task. Although long and a little disorganized, Mastery was a fun read that revealed a desire for creativity and craft within me for my work. I still think I’m young in my career (apprenticeship phase) and Mastery provided some practical advice on how to make best use of my position and time to move closer to mastery. I wanted a bit more detail with the practical advice, but I still found it quite useful. I rate Mastery an 8/10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-might-alsoenjoy&quot;&gt;You might also enjoy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Lessons on life from an ancient Roman Emperor.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/meditations-from-marcus-aurelius-summary-notes-quotes&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/meditations marcus aurelius summary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;meditations marcus aurelius summary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;rec-art many&quot; aria-label=&quot;Recommended Article&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;rec-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-info&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Atomic Habits - Summary, Notes, + Quotes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Who you’ll become in your future can be answered by your behavior today.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;rec-img&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure&gt;
                &lt;a href=&quot;/atomic-habits-review-notes-lessons&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/atomic habits summary review.png&quot; alt=&quot;atomic habits summary review&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</content><author><name>Reggie Paquette</name></author><summary type="html">Mastery by Robert Greene is a practical read on helping people find and pursue their Life’s Task (purpose).</summary></entry></feed>